<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: design | GuoChen | Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/categories/design/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-23T21:39:26+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[GuoChen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to design your blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/design/development/2014/03/23/How-to-design-your-blog/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-23T18:18:25Z</updated>
    <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/design/development/2014/03/23/How-to-design-your-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently i redesigned my <a href="http://blog.hguochen.com">blog</a>. It was an enjoyable experience as i try to apply my new-acquired <a href="http://design.tutsplus.com/articles/50-totally-free-lessons-in-graphic-design-theory--psd-2916">design theories</a> learnt from <a href="http://design.tutsplus.com">tutsplus.com</a>. My goal was to create an <strong>elegant</strong> and <strong>easy-to-read</strong> blog that represents myself both visually and content-wise. In this post, i will bring you through some of my design considerations for my blog.</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at63512pm.png" width="500" alt="hguochen blog" /></p>

<p><em>A look behind the scene of my blog redesign</em></p>

<hr />

<h2>Define your brief</h2>

<p>As with any projects, it&rsquo;s important to figure what exactly you want to achieve and jot it down clearly. This can be a constant reminder as you progress through the design stages. At this point, we just need to figure out our ultimate goal without being worried about the details.</p>

<p>I wanted to design a blog that is <strong>simple to navigate</strong> on index page and contains <strong>easy-to-read</strong> blogposts across different devices. All of these pages should clearly define me and my thoughts.</p>

<h2>Research and idea generation</h2>

<p>Do some googling to get the creativity flowing. Inspirations can come from anywhere. Some of the best places i recommend to check out are:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://pinterest.com">Pinterest</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.smashingmagazine.com">Smashing Magazine</a></li>
<li><a href="http://wordpress.org/themes/">Wordpress Themes</a></li>
<li><a href="http://medium.com">Medium</a></li>
</ul>


<p>As you go through these websites, grab a pen and sketchbook to jot down some of the things such as positions of blog elements, layout, colours, typefaces and navigation details commonly used. This will give you a basic idea of the contents to cover in designing your blog.</p>

<h2>Design considerations</h2>

<p>I wanted users to easily browse through my blog and focus on what i&rsquo;ve written, so i&rsquo;m not going to have too many &lsquo;content&rsquo; pages such as about me, work, contact me etc. These side dishes are more for a portfolio page rather than a blog. In fact, i&rsquo;m only going to have 2 main pages:</p>

<ul>
<li>Index page</li>
<li>Content page</li>
</ul>


<p>Based on my these ideas, it seems that i will need total control of designing my blog. I can&rsquo;t afford to use ready made templates such as from <a href="http://wordpress.com">Wordpress</a>. Instead, i&rsquo;m using a blog engine called <a href="http://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a> where i have the freedom to configure every element of my blog.</p>

<h3>Index page</h3>

<p>This will be the main page of the blog, which is also what greets users when they type in my blog url. Considering a typical user has a short attention-span of only 5 seconds on a webpage, i will need to present the entirety of my blog in that timeframe. Its good to give a short introduction of myself and the genre of this blog.</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at72040pm.png" width="500" alt="blog intro" /></p>

<p>Next i need a way to quickly tell visitor what kind of topics i write about, and there&rsquo;s no better way than allowing them to glance through my blog topics in a short scroll. Many blogs present their latest blogposts at the top. I think this is a bad practice as your latest blogpost might not necessarily be of visitors' interest. Sieving through your entire post to look at your other blogposts is just too much of a pain to get to know you. I&rsquo;d advise against irritating your visitors.</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at73003pm.png" width="500" alt="blog index browsing" /></p>

<p>With the year-annotated scrolling, my visitors will be able to quickly scroll through my list of blogposts and look for interests. We are providing a &lsquo;simple to navigate&rsquo; index page, as part of our objective listed above.</p>

<h3>Content page</h3>

<p>This is the meat of the blog. In fact, most visitors will be entering your blog through a blogspot than index page itself. It is important to establish some form of coherence between the content page and the index page. I chose to do it subtlely by appending my blog thumbnail picture at the top of the page. Followed by the date of the blogpost and topic.</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at74802pm.png" width="500" alt="blogpost header" /></p>

<p>Footer of the blogpost should be dedicated to interactivity. If visitors has taken the time to read to the bottom, he/she most probably have enjoyed the post. It is good to elicit further action by either allowing the visitor to share on social domains or provide a comment for further discussion.</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at74945pm.png" width="500" alt="blogpost footer" /></p>

<h3>On Measure</h3>

<p><img src="http://www.markboulton.co.uk/images/uploads/measure_1.gif" alt="measure" /></p>

<p>Measure, is the name given to the width of a body of type. There are several units of measurement used for defining the measure&rsquo;s width. Three basic units are:</p>

<ul>
<li>One point = 1/72 of an inch</li>
<li>One pic = 12 points</li>
<li>One em = Distance horizontally equal to the type of size, in points. you are using. Eg. 1em of 12pt type is 12pt.</li>
</ul>


<p>For a full width monitor, the optimum measure for reading is between <strong>66-72 words</strong> a line. If you scale that down to a mobile screen, measure would come down to about <strong>8-13 words</strong> a line.</p>

<h3>On font-size</h3>

<p>Appropriate font size will greatly enhance the readability of texts. I shall not go into detail here but some tried and tested font sizes for blog contents adopts the following pixel sizes:</p>

<ul>
<li>16px &ndash; Body copy and leading</li>
<li>24px &ndash; Main heading &amp; section headings</li>
<li>18px &ndash; Subheadings</li>
<li>13px &ndash; All other headed elements</li>
</ul>


<p>This will give the following styles visually:</p>

<p><img src="http://www.markboulton.co.uk/images/uploads/typo4_headings.gif" width="300" alt="font sizes" /></p>

<p>For the frontend designers, your CSS could look like this with the specifications above:</p>

<pre><code>body {
    font: 16px/1.5em "Lucida Grande";
}

h1, h2, h3, h4, h5, h6 {
    font-family: helvetica, arial, verdana, sans-serif;
    font-weight: normal;
}

h1 {
    font-size: 218%;
}

h2 {
    font-size: 164%;
}

h3 {
    font-size: 145%;
}

h4 {
    font-size: 118%;
}
</code></pre>

<h3>On typefaces</h3>

<p>We read most easily with what we are most familiar with. This would mean the traditional serif family of typefaces. But even in the serif family, there are countless kinds of typefaces to choose from. On choosing a typeface, i&rsquo;ve had a long trial and error on this. Here are 3 different serif types i&rsquo;ve experimented with using on the same content:</p>

<hr />

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at82316pm.png" width="400" alt="helvetica_neue" />
<strong>helvetica neue</strong></p>

<p>Helvetica is a great font for texts, but it is not such a great typeface for continuous smooth reading. It lacks the &lsquo;legs&rsquo; seen on other typefaces which provides the smooth gliding feel when reading on a screen.</p>

<hr />

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at82347pm.png" width="400" alt="sans-serif" />
<strong>sans-serif</strong></p>

<p>Serif is a safe font. Generally you won&rsquo;t go wrong with this font. However, since i prefer a lighter shade of texts, i have to reduce the font-weight from normal 300 to 200. This didn&rsquo;t fare well with serif typeface and words appear to thin to read properly.</p>

<hr />

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at82121pm.png" width="400" alt="georgia" />
<strong>georgia</strong></p>

<p>Part of the serif typeface family, georgia has always been a strong choice for continous texts. Some of the most popular web such as <a href="http://medium.com">Medium</a> and <a href="http://www.nytimes.com">NyTimes</a> uses georgia to render their texts. An additional advantage of georgia typeface is that it&rsquo;s distinctive enough that font colors normally won&rsquo;t erode its readability.</p>

<hr />

<p>After weighing the considerations, i&rsquo;ve decided to use &lsquo;Helvetica Neue&rsquo; for headings and &lsquo;georgia&rsquo; for paragraph texts. Here&rsquo;s how it looks like:</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at74802pm.png" width="500" alt="blogpost header" /></p>

<h3>On font color</h3>

<p>Black text on white background offers the best readability. However, prolonged exposure on black contrasted texts could be painful to our eyes since modern screen brightness are getting better and better. As such, i&rsquo;ve decided to reduce the contrast of texts by changing paragraph texts to a &lsquo;greyier&rsquo; color while not compromising readability. After some trial and error, the color i&rsquo;ve chosen is a grey with hexcode: #333332.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.colorhexa.com/333332.png" height="150" width="200" alt="333332" /></p>

<h2>Responsive Design</h2>

<p>The last of my consideration is to make sure my blog is readable on both mobile and desktop devices alike.</p>

<p>I like to use a grid because it provides a structural foundation, whiel making the development process easier and more efficient. Using a flexible grid enables a website to sclae dynamically to fit any device width. Below is the CSS for my responsive grid, which is my variations from <a href="http://getbootstrap.com">bootstrap</a>&rsquo;s responsive grid.</p>

<pre><code>/* 12 col responsive grid */

.row {
    clear: both;
    max-width: 1040px;
    margin: 0 auto;
}

[class^="col-"]:last-child {
    margin: 0;
}

[class^="col-"] {
    float: left;
    margin: 0 3.84615384615% 0 0;
    list-style: none;
    position: relative;
}


.col-xs-1 { width: 4.8076923077% }
.col-xs-2 { width: 13.4615384615% }
.col-xs-3 { width: 22.1153846154% }
.col-xs-4 { width: 30.7692307692% }
.col-xs-5 { width: 39.4230769231% }
.col-xs-6 { width: 48.0769230769% }
.col-xs-7 { width: 56.7307692308% }
.col-xs-8 { width: 65.3846153846% }
.col-xs-9 { width: 74.0384615385% }
.col-xs-10 { width: 82.6923076923% }
.col-xs-11 { width: 91.3461538462% }
.col-xs-12 { width: 100%; margin: 0 }
</code></pre>

<p>My breakpoints for my responsive blog are:</p>

<ul>
<li>360px max-width for mobile</li>
<li>768px max-width for tablets</li>
<li>1024px max-width for desktops</li>
</ul>


<p>Keep in mind that with a growing array of devices, there is no longer a &lsquo;common&rsquo; width concepts. It is best to optimize for whichever devices you intend to serve.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s my blog&rsquo;s responsive layout on a few devices:</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/E88F66B9-1921-4E9E-8F48-FB5AF6571F4B.png" width="150" alt="iPhone" /></p>

<p><strong>iPhone 5</strong></p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/photo.png" width="300" alt="ipad" /></p>

<p><strong>iPad Mini</strong></p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at85832pm.png" width="500" alt="desktop" /></p>

<p><strong>Desktop</strong></p>

<p>So, i&rsquo;ve designed and tested out my new blog layout. It is my first time designing a blog from scratch and i&rsquo;ve really learnt alot in the process! Designing is like a constant war between your left brain and right brain while still trying to grip on to established design principles. ROAR! But still, it is fun :) Hopefully my experience has provided you with a guideline to designing blogs. I&rsquo;d love to hear about your experiences in designing your own blog!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lesson 9 The Rose]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/design/2014/03/07/Lesson-9-The-Rose/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-07T19:00:28Z</updated>
    <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/design/2014/03/07/Lesson-9-The-Rose</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We will warm up for the rose by drawing simple shapes. It is always good to warm up by drawing serveral simple basic shapes.</p>

<ol>
<li>Draw two guide dota horizontally across from each other.</li>
<li>Connect the dots with a foreshortened circle.</li>
<li>Draw the body of the bowl.</li>
<li>Using a guide line in direction SW, position the light source in the top right. Shade the bowl with blended shading from drak to light, creating a smooth blended surface.</li>
<li>Before drawing the rose, let&rsquo;s try drawing the &ldquo;peeking&rdquo; line. This tiny detail of a small overlapping line that defines a fold or a wrinkle will have a huge visual effect in enabling you to make the rose petals appear to be curling around the bud in three dimensions.
5a. Draw a vertical flagpole.
5b. Draw two guide dots.
5c. Draw three-quarters of a foreshortened circle.
5d. Draw the vertical thickness of the flag.
5e. Curve the near bottom edge of the flag a bit more than the line above it. The bottom of the flag is a bit farther from your eye, so you need to distort it, curve it more than the top edge.
5f. Draw the &ldquo;peeking&rdquo; line, the most important line in this exercise. This teeny tiny dash will make or break the drawing and holds an enormous amount of visual power.</li>
</ol>


<p>Let&rsquo;s finally get to drawing a rose.</p>

<ol>
<li>Draw a foreshortened bowl, and add a stem.</li>
<li>Draw a guide dot in the middle of the rose bowl.</li>
<li>Begin to spiral out the rose petal with three-quarters of a foreshortened circle.</li>
<li>Keep spiraling, and keep these spiraled foreshortened circles squished. It&rsquo;s the distorted shape that will form the 3 dimensional rosebud.</li>
<li>Complete the spiral at the center of the petal. Erase the extra line.</li>
<li>Draw the center thickness of the rose petal and the first peeking thickness line.</li>
<li>Draw the next outer peeking line.</li>
<li>Draw the remaining thickness line. There it is, depth focused on our beautiful rose.</li>
<li>Draw the very dark, very small, nook and cranny shadows. Notice i even darkened a shadow along the edge of the rose petal.</li>
<li>Place the light source in the top right, and blend the shadin on each of the curved surfaces opposite. Draw a few thorns on the stem, and draw the leaves.</li>
</ol>


<p>Here is my work!
<img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/81630E2C-81A0-4EC6-9376-50AF1E655568.jpg" alt="lesson9-1" /></p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/9BD6F67E-D8D1-47A8-A47A-A85D4FBD472F.jpg" alt="lesson9-2" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lesson 8 Cool Koalas]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/design/2014/03/03/Lesson-8-Cool-Koalas/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-03T19:59:12Z</updated>
    <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/design/2014/03/03/Lesson-8-Cool-Koalas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Let&rsquo;s take a break from boxes and structures and draw a koala bear.</p>

<ol>
<li>Lightly sketch three circles in a row.</li>
<li>On the first circle, use curving dashes to create a &ldquo;soft fur texture along the outside edge&rdquo;.</li>
<li>Continuing to work on the first circle, use more curving dashes to fill in the left side of the circle, creating the illusion of shading with texture. You can use texture to shade an object.</li>
<li>Let&rsquo;s take this one step further. On the second circle, draw sharp lines around the outside, creating the feel of sharp spikes.</li>
<li>Place the light source in the top right corner of your page, and add a few more rows of spikes to the left side of the shape.</li>
<li>Draw scribbles around the third circle. Keep scribbling more circling lines around and around the shape to create a messy-looking ball of dryer lint. Continue to explore this idea of texture as a tool for shading.</li>
<li>Now its time to start drawing the Koala. Begin with a light circle.</li>
<li>Lightly sketch in the ears.</li>
<li>Lightly slope down the shoulders</li>
<li>When you draw the &ldquo;tapered nose, be sure to leave a small white area&rdquo;. This create the illusion of a light reflection off the shiny nose. You will do this same thing when drawing other animals, cats dogs etc.</li>
<li>Draw the koala&rsquo;s eyes, transferring the idea of reflection by leaving a small white spot in each pupil.</li>
<li>Let&rsquo;s take closer look at the ear. This is what is known in the art world as doing a study of a small portion of a picture.</li>
<li>Draw the overlapped line of the &ldquo;concha&rdquo;.</li>
<li>Draw the bump at the bottom of the aer. This is the &ldquo;tragus&rdquo;</li>
<li>Now Repeat this ear structure on the right ear.</li>
<li>Look back at the furry ball you drew at the beginning of this season. Notice how you created the soft feel of fur as ompared to the sharp feel of the spike ball. Draw the soft, furry texture around the outline of the koala.</li>
<li>Use more furry texture to shade the koala&rsquo;s head, ears, and body. Emphasize the undershadow under his chin and in his ear under the top helix line.</li>
</ol>


<p>Here&rsquo;s how my final drawing looks like:</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/0AB47825-2D43-42C9-978A-5D92445FCD41.jpg" alt="lesson8" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lesson 7 Advanced Level Cubes]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/design/2014/03/03/Lesson-7-Advanced-Level-Cubes/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-03T19:35:37Z</updated>
    <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/design/2014/03/03/Lesson-7-Advanced-Level-Cubes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this lesson we are going to draw three-dimensional cubes. We are also going to build on it by drawing advanced shapes.</p>

<ol>
<li>Use guide dots to draw a foreshortened square.</li>
<li>Lightly draw the sides down, and draw the middle line longer.</li>
<li>Then draw the bottom of the cube using the lines you have already drawn as a reference. Go ahead and extend all of your direction NW and NE lines out as a guide.</li>
<li>Draw the guide dot just below the near corner. This guide dot determines the angle of your foreshortened second layer. If your guide dot is placed low, it will distort the layer and throw the entire building out of alignment.</li>
<li>Using lines drawn as a reference, draw the near edges of the second tier in NE and NW.</li>
<li>Look at your NE angle at the top foreshortened square of your box. Now, take your pencil and trace over those direction lines lightly to embed the angle of the line into your hand memory. Repeat the same technique to draw the NW line on the other side to create the top of the second layer of the building.</li>
<li>Complete the second layer of the building. Double check your bottom lines against drawing compass direction arrows NW and NE.</li>
<li>Begin drawing the doors on the top level with two vetical lines on each side. To make sure your lines are actually vertical, straight up and down, look at the edge of your paper.</li>
<li>Curve the tops of both doorways on the top floor of the building.</li>
<li>To create the illusion that these doors actually exist as 3 dimensional entrances to this building, we need to add thickness to them. If the door is on the right, the thickness is on the right. If door is on the left, the thickness is on the left.</li>
<li>Complete the door by following the line of the exterior door as it curves up.</li>
<li>Look at the door on the left side. Using the drawing compass direction NE lines you drew earlier as reference, draw the thickness on the left-side door on the left side of the entrance.</li>
<li>Erase your side lines at the bottom of each door. With a well placed line in drawing directions NW and NE, you can easily create the visual illusion that there is a hallway or a room inside each doorway.</li>
<li>Let&rsquo;s create ramp on the left side first. Draw the vertical back edge of the ramp against the wall, and extend the bottom edge of the ramp out in drawing compass direction SW.</li>
<li>Draw the thickness of the ramp with two lines in direction NW, matching the angles with the linesyou drew earlier in direction NW.</li>
<li>Complete the far edge of the ramp by matching the angle of the front edge.</li>
<li>Erase guide lines behind the ramp. Using the lines you already drew in direction NE as reference, draw the ramp on the right side.</li>
<li>Complete your two-layered foreshortened ramp building by drawing the horizon line above the building, positioning your light source, and shading all the surfaces opposite your light position. Using your reference lines to angle the cast shadow correctly direction SW is really simple when you are drawing buildings; just extend the bottom lines. We are done!</li>
</ol>


<p>Here&rsquo;s how my piece looks like:
<img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/6C580A37-C2F4-4F72-B97D-CB89CABA6BBC.jpg" alt="lesson7" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lesson 6 Stacking Tables]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/design/2014/02/26/Lesson-6-Stacking-Tables/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-26T21:34:18Z</updated>
    <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/design/2014/02/26/Lesson-6-Stacking-Tables</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I will be drawing stacking tables with proper lighting conditions in this lesson. This lesson will gel all of the concepts and laws learnt so far.</p>

<ol>
<li>Begin with a foreshortened square.</li>
<li>Draw two short edges to create the top of the table.</li>
<li>Draw the middle line longer, according to the foreshortened square concept.</li>
<li>Using the lines you have already drawn as areference, draw bottom of the table top in direction of Northeast and Northwest.</li>
<li>Draw middle line longer to create the near edge of the table post.</li>
<li>Draw the sides of the table post. Each side line is drawn halfway from the far edge to the middle line.</li>
<li>Using lines drawn as reference, draw the bottom of the table post in direction NW and NE.</li>
<li>Draw horizon line just above the table. and position light source aboce and to the right. The horizon line tells our eye that the object is below the horizon line, which communicates to our brain that the thickness, shadows, and foreshorteneing are from this perspective.</li>
<li>Place a guide dot directly below the near corner of the table post. If you don&rsquo;t use the guide dot on every stacked table, your drawing may get progressively more skewed and impossibly distorted.</li>
<li>Using lines already drawn as a reference, draw the front edge of the pedestal in directions NW and NE.</li>
<li>Now draw the back edges of the opt of the pedestal, be sure to go behind the corner of the post.</li>
<li>Complete the pedestal, makjing sure to draw the near corner lower. As always, use the lines you have already drawn as reference angles for drawing the bottom lines of the pedestal in directions NW and NE.</li>
<li>Finally, add the cast shadow opposite your positioned light source, shade the table and pedestal and add the dark undershadows of both sides of the post.</li>
</ol>


<p>So here&rsquo;s how my final drawing looks:
<img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/AFA53C8F-34F6-4A7D-8C20-6DD868130467.jpg" alt="lesson7" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
