<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: design | GuoChen | Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/categories/design/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-23T14:54:50+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[GuoChen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lesson 9 The Rose]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/design/2014/03/07/Lesson-9-The-Rose/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-07T19:00:28Z</updated>
    <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/design/2014/03/07/Lesson-9-The-Rose</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We will warm up for the rose by drawing simple shapes. It is always good to warm up by drawing serveral simple basic shapes.</p>

<ol>
<li>Draw two guide dota horizontally across from each other.</li>
<li>Connect the dots with a foreshortened circle.</li>
<li>Draw the body of the bowl.</li>
<li>Using a guide line in direction SW, position the light source in the top right. Shade the bowl with blended shading from drak to light, creating a smooth blended surface.</li>
<li>Before drawing the rose, let&rsquo;s try drawing the &ldquo;peeking&rdquo; line. This tiny detail of a small overlapping line that defines a fold or a wrinkle will have a huge visual effect in enabling you to make the rose petals appear to be curling around the bud in three dimensions.
5a. Draw a vertical flagpole.
5b. Draw two guide dots.
5c. Draw three-quarters of a foreshortened circle.
5d. Draw the vertical thickness of the flag.
5e. Curve the near bottom edge of the flag a bit more than the line above it. The bottom of the flag is a bit farther from your eye, so you need to distort it, curve it more than the top edge.
5f. Draw the &ldquo;peeking&rdquo; line, the most important line in this exercise. This teeny tiny dash will make or break the drawing and holds an enormous amount of visual power.</li>
</ol>


<p>Let&rsquo;s finally get to drawing a rose.</p>

<ol>
<li>Draw a foreshortened bowl, and add a stem.</li>
<li>Draw a guide dot in the middle of the rose bowl.</li>
<li>Begin to spiral out the rose petal with three-quarters of a foreshortened circle.</li>
<li>Keep spiraling, and keep these spiraled foreshortened circles squished. It&rsquo;s the distorted shape that will form the 3 dimensional rosebud.</li>
<li>Complete the spiral at the center of the petal. Erase the extra line.</li>
<li>Draw the center thickness of the rose petal and the first peeking thickness line.</li>
<li>Draw the next outer peeking line.</li>
<li>Draw the remaining thickness line. There it is, depth focused on our beautiful rose.</li>
<li>Draw the very dark, very small, nook and cranny shadows. Notice i even darkened a shadow along the edge of the rose petal.</li>
<li>Place the light source in the top right, and blend the shadin on each of the curved surfaces opposite. Draw a few thorns on the stem, and draw the leaves.</li>
</ol>


<p>Here is my work!
<img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/81630E2C-81A0-4EC6-9376-50AF1E655568.jpg" alt="lesson9-1" /></p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/9BD6F67E-D8D1-47A8-A47A-A85D4FBD472F.jpg" alt="lesson9-2" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lesson 8 Cool Koalas]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/design/2014/03/03/Lesson-8-Cool-Koalas/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-03T19:59:12Z</updated>
    <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/design/2014/03/03/Lesson-8-Cool-Koalas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Let&rsquo;s take a break from boxes and structures and draw a koala bear.</p>

<ol>
<li>Lightly sketch three circles in a row.</li>
<li>On the first circle, use curving dashes to create a &ldquo;soft fur texture along the outside edge&rdquo;.</li>
<li>Continuing to work on the first circle, use more curving dashes to fill in the left side of the circle, creating the illusion of shading with texture. You can use texture to shade an object.</li>
<li>Let&rsquo;s take this one step further. On the second circle, draw sharp lines around the outside, creating the feel of sharp spikes.</li>
<li>Place the light source in the top right corner of your page, and add a few more rows of spikes to the left side of the shape.</li>
<li>Draw scribbles around the third circle. Keep scribbling more circling lines around and around the shape to create a messy-looking ball of dryer lint. Continue to explore this idea of texture as a tool for shading.</li>
<li>Now its time to start drawing the Koala. Begin with a light circle.</li>
<li>Lightly sketch in the ears.</li>
<li>Lightly slope down the shoulders</li>
<li>When you draw the &ldquo;tapered nose, be sure to leave a small white area&rdquo;. This create the illusion of a light reflection off the shiny nose. You will do this same thing when drawing other animals, cats dogs etc.</li>
<li>Draw the koala&rsquo;s eyes, transferring the idea of reflection by leaving a small white spot in each pupil.</li>
<li>Let&rsquo;s take closer look at the ear. This is what is known in the art world as doing a study of a small portion of a picture.</li>
<li>Draw the overlapped line of the &ldquo;concha&rdquo;.</li>
<li>Draw the bump at the bottom of the aer. This is the &ldquo;tragus&rdquo;</li>
<li>Now Repeat this ear structure on the right ear.</li>
<li>Look back at the furry ball you drew at the beginning of this season. Notice how you created the soft feel of fur as ompared to the sharp feel of the spike ball. Draw the soft, furry texture around the outline of the koala.</li>
<li>Use more furry texture to shade the koala&rsquo;s head, ears, and body. Emphasize the undershadow under his chin and in his ear under the top helix line.</li>
</ol>


<p>Here&rsquo;s how my final drawing looks like:</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/0AB47825-2D43-42C9-978A-5D92445FCD41.jpg" alt="lesson8" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lesson 7 Advanced Level Cubes]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/design/2014/03/03/Lesson-7-Advanced-Level-Cubes/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-03T19:35:37Z</updated>
    <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/design/2014/03/03/Lesson-7-Advanced-Level-Cubes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this lesson we are going to draw three-dimensional cubes. We are also going to build on it by drawing advanced shapes.</p>

<ol>
<li>Use guide dots to draw a foreshortened square.</li>
<li>Lightly draw the sides down, and draw the middle line longer.</li>
<li>Then draw the bottom of the cube using the lines you have already drawn as a reference. Go ahead and extend all of your direction NW and NE lines out as a guide.</li>
<li>Draw the guide dot just below the near corner. This guide dot determines the angle of your foreshortened second layer. If your guide dot is placed low, it will distort the layer and throw the entire building out of alignment.</li>
<li>Using lines drawn as a reference, draw the near edges of the second tier in NE and NW.</li>
<li>Look at your NE angle at the top foreshortened square of your box. Now, take your pencil and trace over those direction lines lightly to embed the angle of the line into your hand memory. Repeat the same technique to draw the NW line on the other side to create the top of the second layer of the building.</li>
<li>Complete the second layer of the building. Double check your bottom lines against drawing compass direction arrows NW and NE.</li>
<li>Begin drawing the doors on the top level with two vetical lines on each side. To make sure your lines are actually vertical, straight up and down, look at the edge of your paper.</li>
<li>Curve the tops of both doorways on the top floor of the building.</li>
<li>To create the illusion that these doors actually exist as 3 dimensional entrances to this building, we need to add thickness to them. If the door is on the right, the thickness is on the right. If door is on the left, the thickness is on the left.</li>
<li>Complete the door by following the line of the exterior door as it curves up.</li>
<li>Look at the door on the left side. Using the drawing compass direction NE lines you drew earlier as reference, draw the thickness on the left-side door on the left side of the entrance.</li>
<li>Erase your side lines at the bottom of each door. With a well placed line in drawing directions NW and NE, you can easily create the visual illusion that there is a hallway or a room inside each doorway.</li>
<li>Let&rsquo;s create ramp on the left side first. Draw the vertical back edge of the ramp against the wall, and extend the bottom edge of the ramp out in drawing compass direction SW.</li>
<li>Draw the thickness of the ramp with two lines in direction NW, matching the angles with the linesyou drew earlier in direction NW.</li>
<li>Complete the far edge of the ramp by matching the angle of the front edge.</li>
<li>Erase guide lines behind the ramp. Using the lines you already drew in direction NE as reference, draw the ramp on the right side.</li>
<li>Complete your two-layered foreshortened ramp building by drawing the horizon line above the building, positioning your light source, and shading all the surfaces opposite your light position. Using your reference lines to angle the cast shadow correctly direction SW is really simple when you are drawing buildings; just extend the bottom lines. We are done!</li>
</ol>


<p>Here&rsquo;s how my piece looks like:
<img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/6C580A37-C2F4-4F72-B97D-CB89CABA6BBC.jpg" alt="lesson7" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lesson 6 Stacking Tables]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/design/2014/02/26/Lesson-6-Stacking-Tables/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-26T21:34:18Z</updated>
    <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/design/2014/02/26/Lesson-6-Stacking-Tables</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I will be drawing stacking tables with proper lighting conditions in this lesson. This lesson will gel all of the concepts and laws learnt so far.</p>

<ol>
<li>Begin with a foreshortened square.</li>
<li>Draw two short edges to create the top of the table.</li>
<li>Draw the middle line longer, according to the foreshortened square concept.</li>
<li>Using the lines you have already drawn as areference, draw bottom of the table top in direction of Northeast and Northwest.</li>
<li>Draw middle line longer to create the near edge of the table post.</li>
<li>Draw the sides of the table post. Each side line is drawn halfway from the far edge to the middle line.</li>
<li>Using lines drawn as reference, draw the bottom of the table post in direction NW and NE.</li>
<li>Draw horizon line just above the table. and position light source aboce and to the right. The horizon line tells our eye that the object is below the horizon line, which communicates to our brain that the thickness, shadows, and foreshorteneing are from this perspective.</li>
<li>Place a guide dot directly below the near corner of the table post. If you don&rsquo;t use the guide dot on every stacked table, your drawing may get progressively more skewed and impossibly distorted.</li>
<li>Using lines already drawn as a reference, draw the front edge of the pedestal in directions NW and NE.</li>
<li>Now draw the back edges of the opt of the pedestal, be sure to go behind the corner of the post.</li>
<li>Complete the pedestal, makjing sure to draw the near corner lower. As always, use the lines you have already drawn as reference angles for drawing the bottom lines of the pedestal in directions NW and NE.</li>
<li>Finally, add the cast shadow opposite your positioned light source, shade the table and pedestal and add the dark undershadows of both sides of the post.</li>
</ol>


<p>So here&rsquo;s how my final drawing looks:
<img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/AFA53C8F-34F6-4A7D-8C20-6DD868130467.jpg" alt="lesson7" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lesson 5 Hollow Cubes]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/design/2014/01/20/Lesson-5-Hollow-Cubes/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-20T21:28:09Z</updated>
    <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/design/2014/01/20/Lesson-5-Hollow-Cubes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m gona be drawing hollow cubes for this lesson. Drawing lines that <strong>sync</strong> with each other is pretty important when drawing cubes.</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>Parallel and Perpendicular Lines</strong>
Parallel lines are two lines going in the same direction, spaced equally apart. Perpendicular lines are two lines that intersect at right angles to each other.</p></blockquote>

<ol>
<li>Sketch a foreshortened cube.</li>
<li>Slant back two parallel lines on the top of the cube.</li>
<li>Think of a compass, the 4 most commonly used directions are, <strong>Northwest</strong>, <strong>Northeast</strong>, <strong>Southwest</strong>, and <strong>Southeast</strong>.</li>
<li>Draw the parallel side of the box lid lifting up with two parallel lines.</li>
<li>Use the bottom of the box angles to guide your line directions, complete near the flaps, aligning them up in direction NE and NW. By always referring the lines you have already drawn and by continually checking your angles against the drawing direction reference cube, your drawings will look solid, focused, and 3D.</li>
<li>When casting shadows, we are casting at the SW direction instead of downwards. This will go well with the light source which is in NE direction.</li>
</ol>


<p>Try drawing the cube a few more times to get the directional cues correct. Here&rsquo;s what i&rsquo;ve drawn:
<img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/62514743-DAE5-4271-B0D7-102441EB3893.jpg" alt="lesson5" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
