<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
        <channel>
                <title>GuoChen&#39;s Blog</title>
                <description>A glimpse of my life, my passion and my thoughts.</description>
                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com</link>
                <atom:link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Ignorance of MLM marketeers</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m totally against Multi-Level-Marketing(MLM) or any form of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ponzi_scheme&quot;&gt;Ponzi schemes&lt;/a&gt; because it&amp;rsquo;s a questionable business model that does not offer any real values to the society Here&amp;rsquo;s my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/notes/guochen-hou/mlm-thanks-but-no-thanks/460181587333803&quot;&gt;reasons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of which, most MLM marketeers are just pure ignorant about the product they are trying to promote. Let&amp;rsquo;s be honest here, they are not really interested in &amp;lsquo;growing&amp;rsquo; you, they are just interested in entry fee you paid up upon joining the organization. More suckers like you joining as their downlinks means more loyalty fees into their pocket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s more of a joke is that most of these marketeers who approaches you doesn&amp;rsquo;t have the slightest idea about their product or the industry they are in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every month or so i&amp;rsquo;ll receive at least 1 of such invites to MLM. AND THEY JUST DONT DIE OFF! So last week i received this message on linkedin:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-02-16at30123pm.png&quot; alt=&quot;message1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Income diversification&amp;rsquo; is like an instant red flag to me. But being polite, i replied:
&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-02-16at30929pm.png&quot; alt=&quot;message2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon afterwards it start to sound more fishy in her reply:
&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-02-16at31133pm.png&quot; alt=&quot;message3&quot; /&gt;
Ok seriously??? you are running an e-commerce business and your website is only accessible to a selected few??? It&amp;rsquo;s like saying,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;i&amp;rsquo;m opening a restaurant that only serves my friends and family.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great work so far Amirah. I decided to serve her own medicine back to her.
&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-02-16at31714pm.png&quot; alt=&quot;message4&quot; /&gt;
At this point, the last that she can do to save her sinking ship is to send me some PDFS, DOCS, WEBSITES depicting her business to get me interested. But it seems she doesn&amp;rsquo;t have any to begin with. Alas, this short and apparently-less-friendly message without signoffs came back:
&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-02-16at32155pm.png&quot; alt=&quot;message5&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OKAY. BITCHING TIME. My dear Amirah, it seems you don&amp;rsquo;t even understand the difference between &amp;lsquo;a wholesale/retail distribution channel&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;e-commerce distribution business&amp;rsquo;. A wholesale/retail distribution channel via internet is like &lt;a href=&quot;www.ebay.com.sg&quot;&gt;eBay&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;www.amazon.com&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; where you provide a medium for e-commerce business to operate and transact. An e-commerce business is where you USE this medium to perform ecommerce activities. Building an ebay shopfront to sell your products within ebday is totally different from building ebay.com itself. I can&amp;rsquo;t appreciate how you want to hire me to work for you, or as your down-link in your organization, when you can&amp;rsquo;t even figure out this simple difference about the industry you are supposedly to be an expert in. Preaching about a questionable business model is already being frowned upon. The worst you can do is to demonstrate that you know nothing about the industry you are in. Please Amirah, stop this madness.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2014 14:18:11 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//random/2014/02/16/Ignorance-of-MLM-marketeers/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//random/2014/02/16/Ignorance-of-MLM-marketeers/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Lion city&#39;s message</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/singapore.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;singapore&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Great cities attract ambitious people. You can sense it when you walk around one. In a hundred subtle ways, the city sends you a message: you could do more; you should try harder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The surprising thing is how different these messages can be. New York tells you, above all: you should make more money. There are other messages too, of course. You should be hipper. You should be better looking. But the clearest message is that you should be richer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I like about Boston (or rather Cambridge) is that the message there is: you should be smarter. You really should get around to reading all those books you&amp;rsquo;ve been meaning to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you ask what message a city sends, you sometimes get surprising answers. As much as they respect brains in Silicon Valley, the message the Valley sends is: you should be more powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s not quite the same message New York sends. Power matters in New York too of course, but New York is pretty impressed by a billion dollars even if you merely inherited it. In Silicon Valley no one would care except a few real estate agents. What matters in Silicon Valley is how much effect you have on the world. The reason people there care about Larry and Sergey is not their wealth but the fact that they control Google, which affects practically everyone.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash; Paul Graham&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Graham once wrote this article on different messages that a city sends you when you are in it. I like the article alot.
In my words, the message is the city&amp;rsquo;s attitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What message does Singapore, the flower city of asia, send?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow the rules; Live a secure life.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People living in singapore are good citizens, almost too good for their own good. They follow rules to the letter and abide by government policies rain or shine. Flouting the law is seen as blasphemous and challenging authority in itself almost seemed a criminal activity. You know you are safe as long as you stay within social boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city tells you to prepare for the unexpected. What if you lost your job tomorrow? What if you couldn&amp;rsquo;t pay your house mortgages anymore? What if your children couldn&amp;rsquo;t perform academically?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it is this constant vibe that the city is giving out, people no longer dare to challenge themselves, the status quo or the rules but default to security. Failure as a result of a challenge is too much to handle, too much of a loss to bear and too shameful to be seen. Oh wait, arn&amp;rsquo;t those the exact sentiments for life&amp;rsquo;s mediocrity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is hard to ask a city to change. So we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t stay in a city for too long as we will subconsciously inherit the city&amp;rsquo;s message and live by it as our mantra. Travel around when you are still young. Look at what other cities has to offer. Perhaps that&amp;rsquo;s why people say, &lt;em&gt;Life is a journey&lt;/em&gt; and not &lt;em&gt;Life is a place&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://paulgraham.com/cities.html&quot;&gt;http://paulgraham.com/cities.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
                                <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2014 17:30:28 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//random/2014/01/21/Lion-city%27s-message/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//random/2014/01/21/Lion-city%27s-message/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Lesson 5 Hollow Cubes</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m gona be drawing hollow cubes for this lesson. Drawing lines that &lt;strong&gt;sync&lt;/strong&gt; with each other is pretty important when drawing cubes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Parallel and Perpendicular Lines&lt;/strong&gt;
Parallel lines are two lines going in the same direction, spaced equally apart. Perpendicular lines are two lines that intersect at right angles to each other.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sketch a foreshortened cube.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slant back two parallel lines on the top of the cube.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Think of a compass, the 4 most commonly used directions are, &lt;strong&gt;Northwest&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Northeast&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Southwest&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Southeast&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw the parallel side of the box lid lifting up with two parallel lines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the bottom of the box angles to guide your line directions, complete near the flaps, aligning them up in direction NE and NW. By always referring the lines you have already drawn and by continually checking your angles against the drawing direction reference cube, your drawings will look solid, focused, and 3D.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When casting shadows, we are casting at the SW direction instead of downwards. This will go well with the light source which is in NE direction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Try drawing the cube a few more times to get the directional cues correct. Here&amp;rsquo;s what i&amp;rsquo;ve drawn:
&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/62514743-DAE5-4271-B0D7-102441EB3893.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lesson5&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2014 21:28:09 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//design/2014/01/20/Lesson-5-Hollow-Cubes/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//design/2014/01/20/Lesson-5-Hollow-Cubes/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Bizad Charity Run 2014</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/47CF7B85-FE8E-4A36-9E14-0CE43C88796C.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Race bib&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So i&amp;rsquo;ve just completed my first race in 2014 of distance &lt;strong&gt;10KM&lt;/strong&gt;. I came in &lt;strong&gt;9th&lt;/strong&gt; position with a timing of &lt;strong&gt;40min12s&lt;/strong&gt;. I was expecting a better timing and position actually, but oh wells.. that leaves a lot of room for improvement! I&amp;rsquo;m gona share abit on how i trained for 10km races, hopefully this is helpful for you :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having signed up for the race only about 1 month before D-Day, i have little time to prepare a comprehensive training schedule. Luckily i&amp;rsquo;ve been doing consistent base trainings so my fitness is not too bad to begin with. This is my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/calendar/embed?src=jc3k7b210i05f3s7d9ldtkhdlg%40group.calendar.google.com&amp;amp;ctz=Asia/Singapore&quot;&gt;Google Calendar training schedule&lt;/a&gt; over the month leading up to the race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summarising my schedule:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First session was a time trial which i got a timing of &lt;strong&gt;47min23s&lt;/strong&gt; with the exact race route.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subsequent weekly trainings consists of 1 Speed interval day, 1 endurance interval day and 2 long run sessions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speed intervals consists of 6 &amp;ndash; 8 sets of 600m with 50% run:rest ratio.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Endurance intervals consists of 8 &amp;ndash; 10 sets of 1KM with 50% run:rest ratio.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The rest of the days were littered with recovery runs and i rest every saturday.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I taper off by having a 8km recovery run 2 days before and a rest day on the day before. Strictly speaking, 10KM distances are too short to actually do tapering but since its my first 10KM in awhile, i wanted to better prepare myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the day before the race, i ate small meals consisting of pasta, bananas and apples and drank about 4 litres of water in total. Carbo-loading to prepare for a race is pretty important not only for the physical benefits but also mentally, you can tell yourself &amp;lsquo;i&amp;rsquo;ve prepared well for it.&amp;rsquo; Sometimes, if i didn&amp;rsquo;t prepare well enough for a race, a small part of me will haunt me during the race saying &amp;lsquo;it&amp;rsquo;s ok. dont push so hard, you are not fully prepared&amp;hellip;&amp;rsquo; Screw it, get that out of the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Race Day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Woke up at 6 and made my way to venue. The race starts at 8am though. I just wanted to be early so i can do race pack collection, warm-up, stretching and drills without time pressure. ( It&amp;rsquo;s important to stay relaxed on race day! )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were a couple of kenyans joining the race as well and pretty much thrashed every singaporean/caucasian around. The actual route was pretty hilly and had many flights of unnecessary stairs. Seriously&amp;hellip;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shoutout to race organziers: DONT PUT SUCH OBSTACLES IN A RACE, THIS IS NOT A VERTICAL MARATHON. BE MORE PROFESSIONAL&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we were the first pack of runners, we have to rely alot on the road marshallers to guide us the correct path but the marshallers seem even more lost than we are and lead us to many wrong turns. For competitive runners, every little mistake like this could make a difference between &lt;em&gt;Personal Best&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Normal Run&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was cruising at a pace between 4min/km to 4.30min/km for the race. I would say the first kilometer was a bit of screwed up. It was a 53m general elevation and yet i did a time of 3min50s. I definitely over-exerted myself there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my split timings:
&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-01-11at10828pm.png&quot; alt=&quot;Splits&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Afterthoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a good start of the year with a base race timing to improve on and i&amp;rsquo;m pretty happy with the month of intensive training for the race. I&amp;rsquo;m hoping to do more progressive races throughout the year and gun for a &lt;strong&gt;Personal Best&lt;/strong&gt; for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.marathonsingapore.com/&quot;&gt;Stan Chart Marathon&lt;/a&gt; at end of the year. Cheers to running!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh by the way, I&amp;rsquo;m personally a fan of nike inspirations so i use their &lt;a href=&quot;http://nikeplus.nike.com/plus/products/gps_app/&quot;&gt;Nike Running App&lt;/a&gt; to document my runs. If you use it too, add me at &lt;a href=&quot;http://nikeplus.nike.com/plus/profile/hguochen/&quot;&gt;hguochen&lt;/a&gt;.
My new nike toy is a &lt;a href=&quot;http://nikeplus.nike.com/plus/products/sport_watch/&quot;&gt;Nike+ Sportswatch&lt;/a&gt;, used keep track of pace and distances. Its packed with a nifty GPS which maps your running route everytime and syncs with the running app afterwards.
Here&amp;rsquo;s my love:
&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/14E541F7-C975-4949-B5B3-7799BAD72DA9.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;nike sportswatch&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P/S: Special thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/audrey.lim.7777?ref=ts&amp;amp;fref=ts&quot;&gt;Audrey&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/daniel.leong.2006?fref=ts&quot;&gt;Daniel&lt;/a&gt; for staying back with me on countless training days to do my painful intervals and running with me, you guys are awesome :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2014 13:06:08 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//run/2014/01/11/Bizad-Charity-Run-2014/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//run/2014/01/11/Bizad-Charity-Run-2014/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>My jekyll workflow</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;I just automated my blogging with jekyll with the following routines. My goal is to cut down on inputting a string of commands into the terminal using &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hguochen/jekyll-rakefile&quot;&gt;Rakefile&lt;/a&gt; and standard terminal commands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jason Seifer has an awesome &lt;a href=&quot;http://jasonseifer.com/2010/04/06/rake-tutorial&quot;&gt;Rake Tutorial&lt;/a&gt; for developers new to Rake.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;My Github pages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve set up &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hguochen/hguochen.github.io&quot;&gt;my github pages&lt;/a&gt; to consist of two branches: source and master. The source branch consists of the entire project and as such tracks all changes. The master branch consists solely of the compiled site, which can be found in the _site subdirectory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;My Local environment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;blog/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;|&amp;mdash;blog.hguochen.com/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;|&amp;mdash;hguochen.github.io/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Main folder blog has 2 sub directories. blog.hguochen.com which holds jekyll generated site content. hguochen.github.io holds jekyll raw files such as &lt;em&gt;posts, &lt;/em&gt;layouts, _includes etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;My workflow&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Automate terminal commands by adding the following alias into .bashrc file:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;alias blogdir=&quot;cd /path/to/blog/hguochen.github.io&quot;

alias build_blog=&quot;&quot;blogdir; jekyll build; sudo cp -r /path/to/blog/hguochen.github.io/_site/* /path/to/blog/blog.hguochen.com; cd /path/to/blog/blog.hguochen.com; git add --all; git commit -m &quot;Blogpost on [&quot;Date&quot;]&quot;; git push origin master;&quot;

alias bb=&quot;build_blog&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Move to jekyll raw files folder:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ blogdir
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create new post with Rake:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ rake post[&quot;Title&quot;]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous command automatically fires up the default text editor for the file just created. In this case, i&amp;rsquo;m using &lt;a href=&quot;http://mouapp.com&quot;&gt;Mou&lt;/a&gt; for .markdown file extensions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once i&amp;rsquo;m done with my blog, i&amp;rsquo;m ready to build and publish my blog by pushing into github pages repository, with a simple alias we made earlier:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ bb
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it! So this is my 3 step process to publishing my blog, powered by &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/leetucksing&quot;&gt;@leetucksing&lt;/a&gt; for introducing me this awesome blogging tool!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/athanhcong&quot;&gt;@athanhcong&lt;/a&gt; made an amazing app &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogwith.co/&quot;&gt;BlogWith&lt;/a&gt; which connects evernote to jekyll powered blogs and allows you to edit blogs directly on &lt;a href=&quot;http://evernote.com&quot;&gt;Evernote&lt;/a&gt;. Gona try how it works with jekyll later :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2014 16:48:29 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//development/2014/01/08/My-jekyll-workflow/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//development/2014/01/08/My-jekyll-workflow/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Markdown language syntax</title>
                                <description>&lt;h1&gt;Mou&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://mouapp.com/Mou_128.png&quot; alt=&quot;Mou icon&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mou&lt;/strong&gt;, the missing Markdown editor for &lt;em&gt;web developers&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Syntax&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Strong and Emphasize&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;strong&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;strong&lt;/strong&gt; ( Cmd + B )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;emphasize&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;emphasize&lt;/em&gt; ( Cmd + I )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sometimes I want a lot of text to be bold.
Like, seriously, a &lt;em&gt;LOT&lt;/em&gt; of text&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Blockquotes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Right angle brackets &amp;gt; are used for block quotes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Links and Email&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An email &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#x6d;&amp;#x61;&amp;#105;&amp;#x6c;&amp;#116;&amp;#x6f;&amp;#x3a;&amp;#101;&amp;#x78;&amp;#x61;&amp;#x6d;&amp;#x70;&amp;#108;&amp;#x65;&amp;#64;&amp;#101;&amp;#120;&amp;#x61;&amp;#x6d;&amp;#112;&amp;#108;&amp;#x65;&amp;#46;&amp;#99;&amp;#x6f;&amp;#109;&quot;&gt;&amp;#101;&amp;#120;&amp;#97;&amp;#109;&amp;#112;&amp;#x6c;&amp;#101;&amp;#x40;&amp;#x65;&amp;#120;&amp;#97;&amp;#109;&amp;#112;&amp;#x6c;&amp;#x65;&amp;#x2e;&amp;#x63;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&lt;/a&gt; link.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simple inline link &lt;a href=&quot;http://chenluois.com&quot;&gt;http://chenluois.com&lt;/a&gt;, another inline link &lt;a href=&quot;http://smallerapp.com&quot;&gt;Smaller&lt;/a&gt;, one more inline link with title &lt;a href=&quot;http://resizesafari.com&quot; title=&quot;a Safari extension&quot;&gt;Resize&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;http://mouapp.com&quot; title=&quot;Markdown editor on Mac OS X&quot;&gt;reference style&lt;/a&gt; link. Input id, then anywhere in the doc, define the link with corresponding id:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Titles ( or called tool tips ) in the links are optional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Images&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An inline image &lt;img src=&quot;http://smallerapp.com/favicon.ico&quot; title=&quot;Title here&quot; alt=&quot;Smaller icon&quot; /&gt;, title is optional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;img src=&quot;http://resizesafari.com/favicon.ico&quot; title=&quot;Title&quot; alt=&quot;Resize icon&quot; /&gt; reference style image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Inline code and Block code&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inline code are surround by &lt;code&gt;backtick&lt;/code&gt; key. To create a block code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Indent each line by at least 1 tab, or 4 spaces.
var Mou = exactlyTheAppIwant; 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Ordered Lists&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ordered lists are created using &amp;ldquo;1.&amp;rdquo; + Space:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ordered list item&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ordered list item&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ordered list item&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Unordered Lists&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unordered list are created using &amp;ldquo;*&amp;rdquo; + Space:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unordered list item&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unordered list item&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unordered list item&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Or using &amp;ldquo;&amp;ndash;&amp;rdquo; + Space:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unordered list item&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unordered list item&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unordered list item&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Hard Linebreak&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End a line with two or more spaces will create a hard linebreak, called &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; in HTML. ( Control + Return )&lt;br/&gt;
Above line ended with 2 spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Horizontal Rules&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three or more asterisks or dashes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Headers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setext-style:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;This is H1&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;This is H2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;atx-style:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;This is H1&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;This is H2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;This is H3&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;This is H4&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;This is H5&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;h6&gt;This is H6&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Extra Syntax&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Footnotes work mostly like reference-style links. A footnote is made of two things: a marker in the text that will become a superscript number; a footnote definition that will be placed in a list of footnotes at the end of the document. A footnote looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s some text with a footnote.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Strikethrough&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrap with 2 tilde characters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;Strikethrough&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Fenced Code Blocks&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start with a line containing 3 or more backticks, and ends with the first line with the same number of backticks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
Fenced code blocks are like Stardard Markdown’s regular code
blocks, except that they’re not indented and instead rely on
a start and end fence lines to delimit the code block.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Tables&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A simple table looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;First Header &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt; Second Header &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt; Third Header&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Content Cell &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Content Cell  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Content Cell&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Content Cell &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Content Cell  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Content Cell&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you wish, you can add a leading and tailing pipe to each line of the table:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt; First Header &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt; Second Header &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt; Third Header &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Content Cell &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Content Cell  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Content Cell |&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Content Cell &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Content Cell  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Content Cell |&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Specify alignement for each column by adding colons to separator lines:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;First Header &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Second Header &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&quot;right&quot;&gt; Third Header&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;Left         &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Center        &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt; Right&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;Left         &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Center        &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt; Right&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Shortcuts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;View&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Toggle live preview: Shift + Cmd + I&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Toggle Words Counter: Shift + Cmd + W&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Toggle Transparent: Shift + Cmd + T&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Toggle Floating: Shift + Cmd + F&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Left/Right = 1/1: Cmd + 0&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Left/Right = 3/1: Cmd + +&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Left/Right = 1/3: Cmd + &amp;ndash;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Toggle Writing orientation: Cmd + L&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Toggle fullscreen: Control + Cmd + F&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Actions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Copy HTML: Option + Cmd + C&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strong: Select text, Cmd + B&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emphasize: Select text, Cmd + I&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inline Code: Select text, Cmd + K&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strikethrough: Select text, Cmd + U&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Link: Select text, Control + Shift + L&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Image: Select text, Control + Shift + I&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select Word: Control + Option + W&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select Line: Shift + Cmd + L&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select All: Cmd + A&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deselect All: Cmd + D&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convert to Uppercase: Select text, Control + U&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convert to Lowercase: Select text, Control + Shift + U&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convert to Titlecase: Select text, Control + Option + U&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convert to List: Select lines, Control + L&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convert to Blockquote: Select lines, Control + Q&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convert to H1: Cmd + 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convert to H2: Cmd + 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convert to H3: Cmd + 3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convert to H4: Cmd + 4&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convert to H5: Cmd + 5&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convert to H6: Cmd + 6&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convert Spaces to Tabs: Control + [&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convert Tabs to Spaces: Control + ]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insert Current Date: Control + Shift + 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insert Current Time: Control + Shift + 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insert entity &amp;lt;: Control + Shift + ,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insert entity &gt;: Control + Shift + .&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insert entity &amp;amp;: Control + Shift + 7&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insert entity Space: Control + Shift + Space&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insert Scriptogr.am Header: Control + Shift + G&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shift Line Left: Select lines, Cmd + [&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shift Line Right: Select lines, Cmd + ]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New Line: Cmd + Return&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comment: Cmd + /&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hard Linebreak: Control + Return&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Edit&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Auto complete current word: Esc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find: Cmd + F&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Close find bar: Esc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Post&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post on Scriptogr.am: Control + Shift + S&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post on Tumblr: Control + Shift + T&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Export&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Export HTML: Option + Cmd + E&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Export PDF:  Option + Cmd + P&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s the footnote.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
                                <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jan 2014 07:58:18 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//2014/01/04/markdown-language-syntax/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//2014/01/04/markdown-language-syntax/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Lesson 4 The Cube</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;Ok I&amp;rsquo;m moving on to drawing cubes in this lesson. Contrary to my belief, i realized drawing cubes is actually harder than drawing spheres. Let&amp;rsquo;s get started!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Starting off, draw two dots across from each other. these 2 dots will determine the diagonal length of the cube.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Place finger between the dots using the opposite hand you are drawing with. Then draw a dot above your finger. These 2 dots should be closer to each other.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shoot the first line across.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw the next line connecting the left dot with the bottom one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A third line to connect the bottom dot with right dot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complete the foreshortened square. Foreshortening means to &lt;strong&gt;distort&lt;/strong&gt; an object to create the illusion that part of it is closer to your eye.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next, draw the sides of the cube with two vertical lines. Use the sides of your sketchbook page as a visual reference to keep your drawings from tilting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using the two side lines as reference lines, draw the middle line a bit longer and lower. Using lines you have already drawn to establish angles and positions for your next lines is a crucial technique in creating 3D picture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using the top right edge of the top foreshortened square as a reference line. draw the bottom right side of the cube.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then draw the bottom left side of the cube by referring to the angle of the line above it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw the light source on the top right hand side of the cube and start shading the other sides. Remember nooks and crannies?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So here&amp;rsquo;s my result:
&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/B3F670C0-3739-4BF2-B625-EAD5F52C0560.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing_lesson4.1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try practicing more with drawing cube like objects. Gift boxes, packages, shoe boxes etc. Once ready, let&amp;rsquo;s go on to &lt;a href=&quot;/design/2014/01/20/lesson-5-hollow-cube/&quot;&gt;Lesson 5 &amp;ndash; Hollow Cubes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//design/2014/01/04/lesson-4-the-cube/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//design/2014/01/04/lesson-4-the-cube/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Lesson 3 Advanced Level Spheres</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;Feeling comfortable with drawing 3D spheres yet? This lesson we are going to draw a lot more overlapping spheres, to get a feel of how things look like when they are grouped together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By the way, listening to music while drawing could be a real pleasure :)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Again, we start with drawing a circle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw another circle behind the first. Push it up a bit ( placement ). Tuck it behind the first ( overlapping ). Draw it a bit smaller ( size ).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw the next circle over to the right behind the first one, push it up, tuck it behind and draw it a bit smaller than the first circle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Onward into the third row of spheres. The row is definitely getting smaller and much higher on the page as you move away from the front sphere. When you draw objects smaller to create the illusion that they are deeper in your picture, you are using the size law. Size is a powerful tool to create depth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fill in the far gap with a peeking over-the-top sphere. Remember that small equals deeper.This will create a 3D illusion, even before adding shadows, shading and blendin!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complete the third row with the end sphere smaller, higher, and behind. Much of 3D is in repition and practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw the fourth and fifth row of spheres. Pushing each row deeper into your picture with size, placement, and overlapping.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw rows six and seven receding into the depths of your sketch page. Size really kicks in on these distant rows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, we determine the position of our light source. For consistency, we will keep the light positioned in the top right. Go ahead and cast shadows off to the left, on the ground, and opposite your light source position.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next, draw the horizontal background reference line, the horizon line. The horizon line will help you create the illusion of depth in your drawing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Still remember Nook and Cranny? Push hard on your pencil and darken the edges and little spots between each ball.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continue your shading process with a first pass over all the objects, scribbling the shading lightly over all opposite edges away from the light source.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make some more scribble shading passes. Blend the shading with your finger. Carefully smudge the dark shaded areas up toward the hot spots, lighter and lighter as you go.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Looking at your masterpiece already? Here&amp;rsquo;s mine:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/C3E57AE1-969A-43C1-BA13-4AC36BD901FC.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing_lesson_3.1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;BONUS CHALLENGE&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a look at this drawing. The largest sphere is the farthest away. The smallest sphere is the closest. Following the guides above, try to recreate this drawing yourself, and have fun!
&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-01-06at41633pm.png&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing_lesson_3.2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my result:
&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/CFB9E05F-A086-4D12-AC69-EF9D44133052.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing_lesson_3.3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s so much for spheres! &lt;a href=&quot;/design/2014/01/04/lesson-4-the-cube/&quot;&gt;Next lesson&lt;/a&gt; i will go on to drawing cubes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//design/2014/01/04/lesson-3-advanced-level-spheres/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//design/2014/01/04/lesson-3-advanced-level-spheres/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Lesson 2 Overlapping Sphere</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;We are going to build on our sphere drawing in lesson 1 by drawing more than 1 spheres. In particular, we are going to overlap them. Still remember the skills to draw a 3D sphere? Let&amp;rsquo;s do this again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw a circle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw a second sphere behind the first one. As you draw the second sphere, make it a bit smaller than the first sphere, a bit higher up on the paper, and tucked behind the first sphere. With this, we are using &lt;code&gt;size&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;placement&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;overlapping&lt;/code&gt; laws. Recap the 9 fundamental laws &lt;a href=&quot;/2014/01/02/lesson-1-the-sphere/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Determine where your imaginary light source will be positioned. You will need to do this so you can get a consistent shading in order to appear three-dimensional.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cast a shadow in the direction opposite the light.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To separate objects in your drawing, draw a dark defining shadow in between the two spheres(called a nook and cranny shadow). This will help identify the two objects. Nook and cranny shadows are always applied under and behind near objects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hold your pencil loosely and scribble the first layer of shading on both spheres. Shade the surfaces opposite your light source. Try to make shading lines below all lined up away from the sun.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make a second darker, more focused shading pass over the spheres. Detail in the very dark edges, and let your scribbles get lighter and lighter as you move slowly toward your established light source. The spot on the sphere adjacent to the light source should be the brightest spot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using your finger, carefully blend the shading from dark to light, trying to keep the hit spot crisp white.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;BONUS CHALLENGE&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s try placing two tennis balls on the table in front of you, overlapping. Make sure to notice the object&amp;rsquo;s placement, shadows, and shading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-01-06at41612pm.png&quot; alt=&quot;tennis_ball_pic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my result:
&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/8CF76EAF-FE0B-4628-8C87-9B65811E5727.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing_lesson_2.2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try practicing more on make the shadows look natural. Ready up for &lt;a href=&quot;/design/2014/01/04/lesson-3-advanced-level-spheres/&quot;&gt;Lesson 3&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//design/2014/01/03/lesson-2-overlapping-sphere/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//design/2014/01/03/lesson-2-overlapping-sphere/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Lesson 1 The Sphere</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;Learning drawing has a lot to do with controlling the lighting in the picture. This lesson teaches how to identify the light source and where to shade objects in your drawing. We will draw a 3D sphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we start drawing, there are 9 fundamental laws of drawing to create the illusion of depth. As follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Foreshortening&lt;/strong&gt;: Distort an object to create the illusion that one part of it is closer to your eye.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Placement&lt;/strong&gt;: Place an object lower on the surface of a picture to make it appear closer to your eye.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Size&lt;/strong&gt;: Draw an object larger to make it appear closer to your eye.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overlapping&lt;/strong&gt;: Draw an object in front of another object to create the visual illusion that it is closer to your eye.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shading&lt;/strong&gt;: Draw darkness on an object opposite the positioned light source to creat the illusion of depth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shadow&lt;/strong&gt;: Draw darkness on the ground next to the object, opposite the positioned light source, to create the illusion of depth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contour lines&lt;/strong&gt;: Draw curving lines wrapping around the shape of a round object to give it volume and depth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Horizon line&lt;/strong&gt;: Draw a horizontal reference line to create the illusion that objects in the picture are varying distances from your eye.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Density&lt;/strong&gt;: Create the illusion of distance by drawing objects lighter and with less detail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t be overwhelmed by these laws. All of these will be covered in the following lessons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw a circle. If it&amp;rsquo;s too difficult, use a coffee mug or coin to trace&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Determine the light source &amp;ndash; direction where the light is coming from. Reasonably, the opposite side of the circle would cast a shadow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now cast a shadow on your sphere opposite your light source position. Remember 2 points, position your light source, and cast a shadow on the ground next to the object and opposite the light source.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scribble shading ON the circle opposite the light source. The furthest place from the light source should be darkest and gets lighter as we go toward the light source.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use your finger to smudge-blend your shading to give it an even shade.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my drawing. Still ugly, but looking abit better than pretest drawings i guess?
&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/72C108EB-CB8D-4DF8-9368-FBB18F29B68E.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing_lesson_1.1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;BONUS CHALLENGE&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s draw an apple in 3D form. Take a look at the photograph of an apple with the light source and on the right:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/ScreenShot2014-01-06at40814pm.png&quot; alt=&quot;apple_pic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/FA143621-E8AC-4AE0-BCE7-4C8BAB4B9256.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing_lesson_1.2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improving already? Move on to &lt;a href=&quot;/design/2014/01/03/lesson-2-overlapping-sphere/&quot;&gt;Lesson 2&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//design/2014/01/02/lesson-1-the-sphere/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//design/2014/01/02/lesson-1-the-sphere/</guid>
                        </item>
                
        </channel>
</rss>