<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
        <channel>
                <title>GuoChen&#39;s Blog</title>
                <description>A glimpse of my life, my passion and my thoughts.</description>
                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com</link>
                <atom:link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Beebeta Engineering</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/leeagustiadi&quot;&gt;Agus&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/jaielhaevin&quot;&gt;Joel&lt;/a&gt; conceptualized the Beebeta project sometime ago and invited me to handle the technical aspect of it. I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what Beebeta was then but the moment i heard of the idea, i loved it! We spent our valuable weekends hacking out Beebeta and we are going to release it very soon! &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.beebeta.com&quot;&gt;Beebeta v1.0&lt;/a&gt; is finally out for public thrashing and hating! Ok but please be nice :(&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having architected the Beebeta backend, i thought it would be fun to give an idea of Beebeta from an engineering perspective. This is how we think an online polling system should be built. Feel free to disagree, we would love to hear your opinions :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, Beebeta is a web platform to gather crowdsourced knowledge. It is an online timeless repository of public opinions which is easily accessible through a poll-like web interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Why Beebeta?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Search engines are vast, and non-targeted. While you will definitely be able to find valuable facts and informations on topics, it is not built to reflect the public&amp;rsquo;s opinions on questions at hand. That&amp;rsquo;s what Beebeta is for. It gives you insights to what the crowd thinks. Which could be questions as trivial as &amp;lsquo;Which restaurant serves the best Ramen?&amp;rsquo; or global issues such as &amp;lsquo;Should gay marriage be allowed?&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok so much for pitching, that&amp;rsquo;s not the purpose of this post. We are here for the nerd stuff arn&amp;rsquo;t we?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Engineering Goal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the implementation of Beebeta, we had a few goals in mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t do unnecessary stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t reinvent the wheel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be versatile in technology options&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;OS/Hosting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beebeta runs Ubuntu 13.10(Saucy Salamander) on Amazon EC2. We tried Linux AMI(CentOS) on EC2 but find the environment not as usable as Ubuntu, plus the software updates were not consistently updated. Also, stress tests on the CentOS server resulted in unpredictable crashes. Since Beebeta is a small project, we ruled out self-hosting as an option. We definitely don&amp;rsquo;t want to waste time setting up servers ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Load Balancing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All server requests goes through our load balancers. We use Amazon&amp;rsquo;s Elastic Load Balancer(ELB) with 2 Nginx instances behind it. I admit now may be abit too early to devote load balancing resources but in case of unexpected traffic spikes, it will be good to pick up from here and scale instead of getting caught off-guard. I skipped using anything to handle the DNS though. But i may revisit the issue with Amazon&amp;rsquo;s Route53 in future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Application Server&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.python.org/download/releases/2.7.5/&quot;&gt;Python 2.7.5&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.djangoproject.com/&quot;&gt;Django 1.6.2&lt;/a&gt; was used on Amazon micro-instance machines. To encourage decoupling with the machine itself, we used &lt;a href=&quot;www.virtualenv.org&quot;&gt;virtualenv&lt;/a&gt; to sandbox the development environment. As such, the machines become stateless and we can easily spring up more instances and deploy direct when it comes to scaling up. Dedicated IP is also allocated to the instance. I&amp;rsquo;m guessing that most of the requests would be CPU-intensive than memory-intensive, so at the moment, a micro-instance would suffice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mod_wsgi is used as our WSGI server, together with Apache and Mysql. A typical LAMP stack. I&amp;rsquo;m exploring the possibility of shifting to &lt;a href=&quot;http://gunicorn.org&quot;&gt;Gunicorn&lt;/a&gt; in future. I read some tutorials on gunicorn and found it easier to configure. But the standard mod_wsgi is good for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Data storage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meta-data&amp;rsquo;s such as tags, url strings etc lives in MySql table rows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our BLOB data lives in Amazon&amp;rsquo;s S3 standard storage. I thought of using glacier storage for original files and standard storage for rendered files but unfortunately S3 does not provide glacier storage in Singapore region yet. I forsee using glacier storage would cut costs by about 30% for every 10GB of data. Will keep in view for future changes, once glacier storage is opened up in Singapore. Content Distribution wise, we use &lt;a href=&quot;http://aws.amazon.com/cloudfront&quot;&gt;Amazon CloudFront&lt;/a&gt;, which helps with page load times from users at different parts of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caching wise, we use memcached and currently have 1 memcached instance, which is connected to using pylibmc &amp;amp; libmemcached. I&amp;rsquo;m aware there&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://aws.amazon.com/elasticache/&quot;&gt;Amazon&amp;rsquo;s Elastic Cache&lt;/a&gt; service for this, but i havent got around to reading up on that yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Django apps&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of our goal not to reinvent the wheel. we used quite a few out-of-the-box django apps to facilitate building of Beebeta platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://boto.readthedocs.org/en/latest/ref/s3.html&quot;&gt;S3Boto&lt;/a&gt; is used to connect the server scripts with different Amazon web services seamlessly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pythonhosted.org/django-analytical/services/mixpanel.html&quot;&gt;Django-analytical&lt;/a&gt; is used to track various site metrics on the application itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pypi.python.org/pypi/django-debug-toolbar&quot;&gt;Django-debug-toolbar&lt;/a&gt;(my favourite debugging tool!) is used on development environments for almost all debugging tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pypi.python.org/pypi/django-pagination&quot;&gt;Django-pagination&lt;/a&gt; is used to paginate database querysets into proper pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://south.readthedocs.org/en/latest/&quot;&gt;Django-south&lt;/a&gt; is used to easily perform database migration tasks between ORM and the database itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bitbucket.org/ubernostrum/django-registration/&quot;&gt;Django-registration&lt;/a&gt; is used to handle user registration/login/logout issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Monitoring&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are using &lt;a href=&quot;https://mixpanel.com&quot;&gt;Mixpanel&lt;/a&gt; to track user activites on the site. These tracking statistics are filtered up to 2 timeless campaigns. First campaign to track site traffic activites such as page traffic, user sign ups etc. Second campaign to track question and choices interactions of all questions on the site. At any one time we will know which questions are most popular or which group of users are most active at different times of the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For backend monitoring, we are using &lt;a href=&quot;http://newrelic.com&quot;&gt;New Relic&lt;/a&gt; to track application performance and server performance. We establish a certain threshold for performance issues on both of these assets and issue warning emails to administrators when the threshold is almost reaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Pyhon error reporting, we use &lt;a href=&quot;http://sentry.readthedocs.org/en/latest/&quot;&gt;Sentry&lt;/a&gt;, an open-source Django app written by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://disqus.com&quot;&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt; folks. We can closely monitor error messages at real-time relatively easy with this handy tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s your stack?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s so much for Beebeta stack. Feel free to leave your comments below if you think we&amp;rsquo;ve made a terrible mistake. Otherwise, I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear how you implement your stacks!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, i&amp;rsquo;ve been playing this song on repeats all day in my coding time. It just energizes me for the tasks at hand. Hope you like it too! :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;420&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/c_H3MWVx6JU?color=white&amp;theme=light&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

</description>
                                <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2014 16:19:30 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//web%20development/2014/03/31/Beebeta-Engineering/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//web%20development/2014/03/31/Beebeta-Engineering/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>How to design your blog</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently i redesigned my &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.hguochen.com&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;. It was an enjoyable experience as i try to apply my new-acquired &lt;a href=&quot;http://design.tutsplus.com/articles/50-totally-free-lessons-in-graphic-design-theory--psd-2916&quot;&gt;design theories&lt;/a&gt; learnt from &lt;a href=&quot;http://design.tutsplus.com&quot;&gt;tutsplus.com&lt;/a&gt;. My goal was to create an &lt;strong&gt;elegant&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;easy-to-read&lt;/strong&gt; blog that represents myself both visually and content-wise. In this post, i will bring you through some of my design considerations for my blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at63512pm.png&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; alt=&quot;hguochen blog&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A look behind the scene of my blog redesign&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Define your brief&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with any projects, it&amp;rsquo;s important to figure what exactly you want to achieve and jot it down clearly. This can be a constant reminder as you progress through the design stages. At this point, we just need to figure out our ultimate goal without being worried about the details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to design a blog that is &lt;strong&gt;simple to navigate&lt;/strong&gt; on index page and contains &lt;strong&gt;easy-to-read&lt;/strong&gt; blogposts across different devices. All of these pages should clearly define me and my thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Research and idea generation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do some googling to get the creativity flowing. Inspirations can come from anywhere. Some of the best places i recommend to check out are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pinterest.com&quot;&gt;Pinterest&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.smashingmagazine.com&quot;&gt;Smashing Magazine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wordpress.org/themes/&quot;&gt;Wordpress Themes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://medium.com&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you go through these websites, grab a pen and sketchbook to jot down some of the things such as positions of blog elements, layout, colours, typefaces and navigation details commonly used. This will give you a basic idea of the contents to cover in designing your blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Design considerations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted users to easily browse through my blog and focus on what i&amp;rsquo;ve written, so i&amp;rsquo;m not going to have too many &amp;lsquo;content&amp;rsquo; pages such as about me, work, contact me etc. These side dishes are more for a portfolio page rather than a blog. In fact, i&amp;rsquo;m only going to have 2 main pages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Index page&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Content page&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Based on my these ideas, it seems that i will need total control of designing my blog. I can&amp;rsquo;t afford to use ready made templates such as from &lt;a href=&quot;http://wordpress.com&quot;&gt;Wordpress&lt;/a&gt;. Instead, i&amp;rsquo;m using a blog engine called &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; where i have the freedom to configure every element of my blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Index page&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be the main page of the blog, which is also what greets users when they type in my blog url. Considering a typical user has a short attention-span of only 5 seconds on a webpage, i will need to present the entirety of my blog in that timeframe. Its good to give a short introduction of myself and the genre of this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at72040pm.png&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; alt=&quot;blog intro&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next i need a way to quickly tell visitor what kind of topics i write about, and there&amp;rsquo;s no better way than allowing them to glance through my blog topics in a short scroll. Many blogs present their latest blogposts at the top. I think this is a bad practice as your latest blogpost might not necessarily be of visitors&#39; interest. Sieving through your entire post to look at your other blogposts is just too much of a pain to get to know you. I&amp;rsquo;d advise against irritating your visitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at73003pm.png&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; alt=&quot;blog index browsing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the year-annotated scrolling, my visitors will be able to quickly scroll through my list of blogposts and look for interests. We are providing a &amp;lsquo;simple to navigate&amp;rsquo; index page, as part of our objective listed above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Content page&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the meat of the blog. In fact, most visitors will be entering your blog through a blogspot than index page itself. It is important to establish some form of coherence between the content page and the index page. I chose to do it subtlely by appending my blog thumbnail picture at the top of the page. Followed by the date of the blogpost and topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at74802pm.png&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; alt=&quot;blogpost header&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Footer of the blogpost should be dedicated to interactivity. If visitors has taken the time to read to the bottom, he/she most probably have enjoyed the post. It is good to elicit further action by either allowing the visitor to share on social domains or provide a comment for further discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at74945pm.png&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; alt=&quot;blogpost footer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;On Measure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.markboulton.co.uk/images/uploads/measure_1.gif&quot; alt=&quot;measure&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measure, is the name given to the width of a body of type. There are several units of measurement used for defining the measure&amp;rsquo;s width. Three basic units are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One point = 1/72 of an inch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One pic = 12 points&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One em = Distance horizontally equal to the type of size, in points. you are using. Eg. 1em of 12pt type is 12pt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For a full width monitor, the optimum measure for reading is between &lt;strong&gt;66-72 words&lt;/strong&gt; a line. If you scale that down to a mobile screen, measure would come down to about &lt;strong&gt;8-13 words&lt;/strong&gt; a line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;On font-size&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Appropriate font size will greatly enhance the readability of texts. I shall not go into detail here but some tried and tested font sizes for blog contents adopts the following pixel sizes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;16px &amp;ndash; Body copy and leading&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;24px &amp;ndash; Main heading &amp;amp; section headings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;18px &amp;ndash; Subheadings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;13px &amp;ndash; All other headed elements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This will give the following styles visually:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.markboulton.co.uk/images/uploads/typo4_headings.gif&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; alt=&quot;font sizes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the frontend designers, your CSS could look like this with the specifications above:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;body {
    font: 16px/1.5em &quot;Lucida Grande&quot;;
}

h1, h2, h3, h4, h5, h6 {
    font-family: helvetica, arial, verdana, sans-serif;
    font-weight: normal;
}

h1 {
    font-size: 218%;
}

h2 {
    font-size: 164%;
}

h3 {
    font-size: 145%;
}

h4 {
    font-size: 118%;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;On typefaces&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We read most easily with what we are most familiar with. This would mean the traditional serif family of typefaces. But even in the serif family, there are countless kinds of typefaces to choose from. On choosing a typeface, i&amp;rsquo;ve had a long trial and error on this. Here are 3 different serif types i&amp;rsquo;ve experimented with using on the same content:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at82316pm.png&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; alt=&quot;helvetica_neue&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;helvetica neue&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helvetica is a great font for texts, but it is not such a great typeface for continuous smooth reading. It lacks the &amp;lsquo;legs&amp;rsquo; seen on other typefaces which provides the smooth gliding feel when reading on a screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at82347pm.png&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; alt=&quot;sans-serif&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;sans-serif&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Serif is a safe font. Generally you won&amp;rsquo;t go wrong with this font. However, since i prefer a lighter shade of texts, i have to reduce the font-weight from normal 300 to 200. This didn&amp;rsquo;t fare well with serif typeface and words appear to thin to read properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at82121pm.png&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; alt=&quot;georgia&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;georgia&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the serif typeface family, georgia has always been a strong choice for continous texts. Some of the most popular web such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://medium.com&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com&quot;&gt;NyTimes&lt;/a&gt; uses georgia to render their texts. An additional advantage of georgia typeface is that it&amp;rsquo;s distinctive enough that font colors normally won&amp;rsquo;t erode its readability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After weighing the considerations, i&amp;rsquo;ve decided to use &amp;lsquo;Helvetica Neue&amp;rsquo; for headings and &amp;lsquo;georgia&amp;rsquo; for paragraph texts. Here&amp;rsquo;s how it looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at74802pm.png&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; alt=&quot;blogpost header&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;On font color&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Black text on white background offers the best readability. However, prolonged exposure on black contrasted texts could be painful to our eyes since modern screen brightness are getting better and better. As such, i&amp;rsquo;ve decided to reduce the contrast of texts by changing paragraph texts to a &amp;lsquo;greyier&amp;rsquo; color while not compromising readability. After some trial and error, the color i&amp;rsquo;ve chosen is a grey with hexcode: #333332.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.colorhexa.com/333332.png&quot; height=&quot;150&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; alt=&quot;333332&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Responsive Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last of my consideration is to make sure my blog is readable on both mobile and desktop devices alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to use a grid because it provides a structural foundation, whiel making the development process easier and more efficient. Using a flexible grid enables a website to sclae dynamically to fit any device width. Below is the CSS for my responsive grid, which is my variations from &lt;a href=&quot;http://getbootstrap.com&quot;&gt;bootstrap&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s responsive grid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;/* 12 col responsive grid */

.row {
    clear: both;
    max-width: 1040px;
    margin: 0 auto;
}

[class^=&quot;col-&quot;]:last-child {
    margin: 0;
}

[class^=&quot;col-&quot;] {
    float: left;
    margin: 0 3.84615384615% 0 0;
    list-style: none;
    position: relative;
}


.col-xs-1 { width: 4.8076923077% }
.col-xs-2 { width: 13.4615384615% }
.col-xs-3 { width: 22.1153846154% }
.col-xs-4 { width: 30.7692307692% }
.col-xs-5 { width: 39.4230769231% }
.col-xs-6 { width: 48.0769230769% }
.col-xs-7 { width: 56.7307692308% }
.col-xs-8 { width: 65.3846153846% }
.col-xs-9 { width: 74.0384615385% }
.col-xs-10 { width: 82.6923076923% }
.col-xs-11 { width: 91.3461538462% }
.col-xs-12 { width: 100%; margin: 0 }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My breakpoints for my responsive blog are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;360px max-width for mobile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;768px max-width for tablets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1024px max-width for desktops&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that with a growing array of devices, there is no longer a &amp;lsquo;common&amp;rsquo; width concepts. It is best to optimize for whichever devices you intend to serve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my blog&amp;rsquo;s responsive layout on a few devices:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/E88F66B9-1921-4E9E-8F48-FB5AF6571F4B.png&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; alt=&quot;iPhone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;iPhone 5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/photo.png&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; alt=&quot;ipad&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;iPad Mini&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at85832pm.png&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; alt=&quot;desktop&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Desktop&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, i&amp;rsquo;ve designed and tested out my new blog layout. It is my first time designing a blog from scratch and i&amp;rsquo;ve really learnt alot in the process! Designing is like a constant war between your left brain and right brain while still trying to grip on to established design principles. ROAR! But still, it is fun :) Hopefully my experience has provided you with a guideline to designing blogs. I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear about your experiences in designing your own blog!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Sun, 23 Mar 2014 18:18:25 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//design/development/2014/03/23/How-to-design-your-blog/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//design/development/2014/03/23/How-to-design-your-blog/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>How to learn Javascript</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;One of my side projects required the use of jQuery and AJAX to add interactivity to the website. What is jQuery and AJAX? They are both frameworks built on top of its base language, javascript.I haven&amp;rsquo;t alot of experiences dealing with javascript before so i&amp;rsquo;ve no choice but to start from the base language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of prior programming experiences, i would still recommend learning a new programming language the proper way. Grasping the correct syntax and coding conventions could help a long way. I took about 4 days going through a series of web resources to learning javascript and shortlisted some of the best tutorials. Just follow through step by step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;0. Read up on fundamentals of Javascript&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Javascript is the language of the browser.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Javascript used to be a client-side programming language running client web scripts. It&amp;rsquo;s primary purpose is to add interactivity to an otherwise static page. Javascript is normally used in conjunction with HTML &amp;amp; CSS to enrich your web contents. However, it has become more popular as a server scripting language in recent years, with &lt;a href=&quot;http://nodejs.org/%E2%80%8E&quot;&gt;Node.js&lt;/a&gt; being the new kid in town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://eloquentjavascript.net/index.html&quot;&gt;Eloquent Javascript&lt;/a&gt; by Marjin Haverbeke, is available freely online. Besides introduction to the language in depth, it also covers coding style and using javascript in the browser. &amp;ldquo;eloquent&amp;rdquo; isn&amp;rsquo;t an overstatement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/A_re-introduction_to_JavaScript&quot;&gt;A Re-introduction to JavaScript&lt;/a&gt;. This introduction is on the Mozilla Developers Network, and it&amp;rsquo;s pretty dense in contents with many code examples. It would recommend quickly reading through to get a first impression of the language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;1. Go through the Javascript course at Codecademy.com&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;www.codecademy.com&quot;&gt;Codecademy&lt;/a&gt; revamped its courses to learning javascript and touted itself as &amp;ldquo;the easiest way to learn how to code&amp;rdquo;. There are currently two courses on JS: &amp;ldquo;Getting started with Programming&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Javascript Quick Start Guide&amp;rdquo; Both of these courses are awesome way to dip into the JS pool and get a feel of the syntax of the language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are already familiar with other programming languages, you can start with &amp;ldquo;Javascript Quick Start Guide&amp;rdquo;. If you are fresh to programming, &amp;ldquo;Getting started with programming&amp;rdquo; is tailored for you. Codecademy is free, but sign up is required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;2. Screencast tutorials at TheNewBoston&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://thenewboston.org/list.php?cat=10&quot;&gt;The New Boston&lt;/a&gt; for javascript has an awesome set of screencast tutorials geared for beginners. It&amp;rsquo;s a good way for beginners to follow and get a feel of how javascript programs are structured. I generally like screencast tutorials alot more because it&amp;rsquo;s easier to follow than written scripts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;3. Install and Learn Firebug(or Chrome Developer Tools)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://getfirebug.com/&quot;&gt;Firebug&lt;/a&gt; is a plugin for Firefox browser that assists you in building and debugging web pages. If you prefer &lt;a href=&quot;www.google.com/chrome/&quot;&gt;Google Chrome&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/sg/safari/%E2%80%8E&quot;&gt;Safari&lt;/a&gt;, check out the built-in developer tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Open developer tools panel by press &lt;code&gt;Option + Cmd +I&lt;/code&gt; on mac, or &lt;code&gt;Ctrl+Shift+I&lt;/code&gt; on the PC.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out some of the useful guides on using both of these tools:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Firebug

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://css-tricks.com/video-screencasts/15-introduction-to-firebug/&quot;&gt;Introduction to Firebug&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;http://css-tricks.com/&quot;&gt;CSS-Tricks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://net.tutsplus.com/tutorials/other/10-reasons-why-you-should-be-using-firebug/&quot;&gt;10 Reasons Why You Should Be Using Firebug&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developer Tools

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://code.google.com/chrome/devtools/&quot;&gt;Developer Tools Website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nOEw9iiopwI&amp;amp;feature=player_embedded&quot;&gt;Google Chrome Developer Tools: 12 Tricks to Develop Quicker&lt;/a&gt; by Paul Irish&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;4. Begin Learning a JavaScript Library &amp;ndash; jQuery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of a javascript library is to sugar down the painful stuff, which could mean extensive amounts of coding just to achieve simple functionalities. There are quite a number of javascript libraries available for free over the web but &lt;a href=&quot;http://jquery.com/&quot;&gt;jQuery&lt;/a&gt; is probably the most popular and widely used library. For a start, read through the &lt;a href=&quot;http://learn.jquery.com/about-jquery/&quot;&gt;jQuery Documentations&lt;/a&gt; to get an idea of the ease of using javascript libraries as opposed to javascript raw language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;5. Work through the tutorial at Try jQuery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://try.jquery.com/&quot;&gt;Try jQuery&lt;/a&gt; is just like codecademy which offers hands on tutorial to learning jQuery. I find it most beneficial by constantly referring back to &lt;a href=&quot;http://api.jquery.com&quot;&gt;jQuery API&lt;/a&gt; while going through the tutorial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;6. Screencast jQuery tutorials at TheNewBoston&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, &lt;a href=&quot;http://thenewboston.org/list.php?cat=32&quot;&gt;The New Boston&lt;/a&gt; for jQuery is a pretty good goto place to quickly get on hand with using jQuery optimally and see how professional use the library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the above pretty much summed up my 4 day adventure into javascript. I hope this plan can help you become good at javascript and build wonderful websites! If you have any other good javascript tutorials to recommend, please leave them in the comments below!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2014 15:35:12 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//web%20development/2014/03/15/How-to-learn-Javascript/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//web%20development/2014/03/15/How-to-learn-Javascript/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>The Ukraine problem explained</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;The hottest global news recently has been about ouster of Ukraine president Viktor Yanukovych and the russian invasion of Ukraine. I&amp;rsquo;m generally indifferent towards international politics but it&amp;rsquo;s becoming pretty big of an issue such that even technology blogs that i follow started posting news about these messy squabbles. I spent about 2 hours reading up whatever i can find on this issue and i&amp;rsquo;ll try to explain it as clear as possible. So other political frog-in-a-well people (like me) can understand. Beware, what&amp;rsquo;s going on below is extremely complicated. I suggest you close this tab right now if you have something better to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still up for this shit? Here goes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;How did Ukraine come about?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.lonelyplanet.com/maps/europe/ukraine/map_of_ukraine.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ukraine map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is Ukraine, the second largest country in europe by area and Crimea peninsula is that little almost-island like area below. During the crimean war, A.D 1853- A.D 1856, it was sort of the Catholics vs the Orthodox but in grandier scale it was the European powers vs Russia as the Ottoman empire decline. Eventually Russia was defeated and the war accumulated a death of 500,000. In a claim of territory for the victors, many european moved over to what is present day Ukraine and settled there, together with some of the indigenious russians. But trouble never ceased and somewhat contributed to the World War I 60 years later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of World War I, Russian revolution begun and gave birth to communism. The russians were too busy overthrowing their own government and had no time to bother its neighbours such as Ukraine. It was these brief period that Ukraine had some days of independence. Finally when Russia became USSR, under the soviet regime, they incited its neighbouring countries to embrace communism. So between 1917 &amp;ndash; 1921, another 1.5million people died around the russian neighbours and eventually led to Ukraine being a satellite country of the mighty USSR. Things became worse after that. When Joseph Stalin took over, the purging began and almost 10 million Ukrainians died between 1932 &amp;ndash; 1933. What&amp;rsquo;s worse, during World War II, Stalin deported the entire population of Crimea to central asia and moved Russians into Ukraine. Imagine a foreigner coming to your home and kicking you out? That&amp;rsquo;s what happened to Crimea. Nikita Khrushchev, stalin&amp;rsquo;s successor, then decided to transfer the Crimean Peninsula from Russia to Ukraine in 1954. Why? Because Crimean Peninsula is not geographically attached to Russia mainland. It will be easier to administer places where you are geographically connected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;What are the Ukraine ethnic groups?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/b/ba/Nativelanguage2001ua.PNG/420px-Nativelanguage2001ua.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;language&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, 67% of people in Ukraine speaks Ukrainian as their first language. 30% speaks Russian, although only about 17% of them identify themselves as Russian. When USSR dissolved, many Russians from Crimea returned to their homes in Russian so as of today, only 12% of Russians are located in the Crimean Peninsula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;What kind of government did Ukraine had?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In December 1991, after the Soviet Union broke up, Ukraine had a nation-wide referendum and 90% of its people, including people in Crimean Peninsula, voted for independence from Russia. But in effect, Ukraine had much closer ties with Russia than any other previous Soviet satellite countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2004, there was a general election. The election was plagued with vote rigging and eventually the pro-Russian leader Viktor Yanukovych(the dude who got overthrown) was elected to become the president. His opponent, the opposition, Viktor Yushchenko led a series of massive protest on the injustice and rigged election. Eventually Viktor Yushchenko was disfigured, crucified and purged. In the following years, since Putin came to power in Russia, the number of assassinations and poisoning of political dissidents skyrocketed in Ukraine. Coincidence? Nope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viktor Yanukovych had almost dictatorial power in Ukraine. But despite being an economist, he wasn&amp;rsquo;t particularly gifted in bringing the country&amp;rsquo;s economy to prosperity and people suffered under his rule. Furthermore, his friendliness towards the western european countries angered Russia whom cut off gas supplies briefly in 2006 and led to few national disasters in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2010 election, Viktor Yanukovych was elected president.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Ok enought history lesson. What is the latest Ukraine issue about?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November 2013, Viktor Yanukovych denounced an agreement to strengthen ties with the European Union and become a closer ally with Russia. This single event sparked the massive protest in the nation, starting from The Independence Square. The protests lasted several months and dozens of protesters were killed by military police and government troops. On 1st March 2014, Viktor Yanukovych fled from his house in Kiev. The protesters had won. Following on, the people called for new elections. Putin was not happy with this outcome. He ostensibly pushed his troops into the Crimean Peninsula in the name of protecting the ethnic Russians in the region. This violated the territory integrity of Ukraine and Ukraine kicked up a big freaking deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this moment, Crimea is already an autonomous province. It had rights to govern itself without much interference from Ukraine. Although it&amp;rsquo;s electricity and water still comes from Ukraine. So what does Crimea want? Independence? Unification with Russia? Well, Crimea doesn&amp;rsquo;t know what she wants herself. And that&amp;rsquo;s why there has been so much fuss on the international stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ukraine has a law that Ukraine is only to be governed by Ukrainians. Sounds legit right? But the problem is, many people in the country still speak russian instead of Ukrainian. Furthermore, the new government wants to be a part of European Union which might mean that it will bring in North Atlantic Treat Organization(NATO) military defences into Ukraine. This is a huge deal for Russia as it means now we have missles deployed right at its doorstep. That is unacceptable to Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the viewpoint of western countries, Ukrain had a tyrannical leader who ordered the murder of peaceful protestors and was chased away from power and replaced with a government that will transition Ukraine to a free and fair election. Russia responded to that by invading Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would attribute much of the present day tension between east and west to the differences in these viewpoints. Russia took a pre-emptive measure to secure its borders from unfriendly states while the western countries worried for a resurgence of Soviet Union and trampling of a democratic state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s ironical is that the word &amp;lsquo;Ukraine&amp;rsquo; means border-land and it has been the border between eastern and western countries for decades. Much of what we are seeing now is just another re-enactment of previous clashes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;rsquo;s about it. Do you have a good solution to this? I don&amp;rsquo;t. I&amp;rsquo;m just a programmer who writes &amp;lsquo;hello world&amp;rsquo; and wishes for world peace.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2014 23:03:29 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//random/2014/03/09/The-Ukraine-problem-explained/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//random/2014/03/09/The-Ukraine-problem-explained/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Lesson 9 The Rose</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;We will warm up for the rose by drawing simple shapes. It is always good to warm up by drawing serveral simple basic shapes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw two guide dota horizontally across from each other.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect the dots with a foreshortened circle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw the body of the bowl.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using a guide line in direction SW, position the light source in the top right. Shade the bowl with blended shading from drak to light, creating a smooth blended surface.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Before drawing the rose, let&amp;rsquo;s try drawing the &amp;ldquo;peeking&amp;rdquo; line. This tiny detail of a small overlapping line that defines a fold or a wrinkle will have a huge visual effect in enabling you to make the rose petals appear to be curling around the bud in three dimensions.
5a. Draw a vertical flagpole.
5b. Draw two guide dots.
5c. Draw three-quarters of a foreshortened circle.
5d. Draw the vertical thickness of the flag.
5e. Curve the near bottom edge of the flag a bit more than the line above it. The bottom of the flag is a bit farther from your eye, so you need to distort it, curve it more than the top edge.
5f. Draw the &amp;ldquo;peeking&amp;rdquo; line, the most important line in this exercise. This teeny tiny dash will make or break the drawing and holds an enormous amount of visual power.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s finally get to drawing a rose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw a foreshortened bowl, and add a stem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw a guide dot in the middle of the rose bowl.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Begin to spiral out the rose petal with three-quarters of a foreshortened circle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep spiraling, and keep these spiraled foreshortened circles squished. It&amp;rsquo;s the distorted shape that will form the 3 dimensional rosebud.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complete the spiral at the center of the petal. Erase the extra line.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw the center thickness of the rose petal and the first peeking thickness line.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw the next outer peeking line.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw the remaining thickness line. There it is, depth focused on our beautiful rose.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw the very dark, very small, nook and cranny shadows. Notice i even darkened a shadow along the edge of the rose petal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Place the light source in the top right, and blend the shadin on each of the curved surfaces opposite. Draw a few thorns on the stem, and draw the leaves.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here is my work!
&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/81630E2C-81A0-4EC6-9376-50AF1E655568.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lesson9-1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/9BD6F67E-D8D1-47A8-A47A-A85D4FBD472F.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lesson9-2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2014 19:00:28 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//design/2014/03/07/Lesson-9-The-Rose/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//design/2014/03/07/Lesson-9-The-Rose/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Lesson 8 Cool Koalas</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s take a break from boxes and structures and draw a koala bear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lightly sketch three circles in a row.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the first circle, use curving dashes to create a &amp;ldquo;soft fur texture along the outside edge&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continuing to work on the first circle, use more curving dashes to fill in the left side of the circle, creating the illusion of shading with texture. You can use texture to shade an object.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s take this one step further. On the second circle, draw sharp lines around the outside, creating the feel of sharp spikes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Place the light source in the top right corner of your page, and add a few more rows of spikes to the left side of the shape.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw scribbles around the third circle. Keep scribbling more circling lines around and around the shape to create a messy-looking ball of dryer lint. Continue to explore this idea of texture as a tool for shading.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now its time to start drawing the Koala. Begin with a light circle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lightly sketch in the ears.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lightly slope down the shoulders&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you draw the &amp;ldquo;tapered nose, be sure to leave a small white area&amp;rdquo;. This create the illusion of a light reflection off the shiny nose. You will do this same thing when drawing other animals, cats dogs etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw the koala&amp;rsquo;s eyes, transferring the idea of reflection by leaving a small white spot in each pupil.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s take closer look at the ear. This is what is known in the art world as doing a study of a small portion of a picture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw the overlapped line of the &amp;ldquo;concha&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw the bump at the bottom of the aer. This is the &amp;ldquo;tragus&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now Repeat this ear structure on the right ear.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look back at the furry ball you drew at the beginning of this season. Notice how you created the soft feel of fur as ompared to the sharp feel of the spike ball. Draw the soft, furry texture around the outline of the koala.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use more furry texture to shade the koala&amp;rsquo;s head, ears, and body. Emphasize the undershadow under his chin and in his ear under the top helix line.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s how my final drawing looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/0AB47825-2D43-42C9-978A-5D92445FCD41.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lesson8&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2014 19:59:12 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//design/2014/03/03/Lesson-8-Cool-Koalas/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//design/2014/03/03/Lesson-8-Cool-Koalas/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Lesson 7 Advanced Level Cubes</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;In this lesson we are going to draw three-dimensional cubes. We are also going to build on it by drawing advanced shapes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use guide dots to draw a foreshortened square.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lightly draw the sides down, and draw the middle line longer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then draw the bottom of the cube using the lines you have already drawn as a reference. Go ahead and extend all of your direction NW and NE lines out as a guide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw the guide dot just below the near corner. This guide dot determines the angle of your foreshortened second layer. If your guide dot is placed low, it will distort the layer and throw the entire building out of alignment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using lines drawn as a reference, draw the near edges of the second tier in NE and NW.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look at your NE angle at the top foreshortened square of your box. Now, take your pencil and trace over those direction lines lightly to embed the angle of the line into your hand memory. Repeat the same technique to draw the NW line on the other side to create the top of the second layer of the building.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complete the second layer of the building. Double check your bottom lines against drawing compass direction arrows NW and NE.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Begin drawing the doors on the top level with two vetical lines on each side. To make sure your lines are actually vertical, straight up and down, look at the edge of your paper.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Curve the tops of both doorways on the top floor of the building.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the illusion that these doors actually exist as 3 dimensional entrances to this building, we need to add thickness to them. If the door is on the right, the thickness is on the right. If door is on the left, the thickness is on the left.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complete the door by following the line of the exterior door as it curves up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look at the door on the left side. Using the drawing compass direction NE lines you drew earlier as reference, draw the thickness on the left-side door on the left side of the entrance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Erase your side lines at the bottom of each door. With a well placed line in drawing directions NW and NE, you can easily create the visual illusion that there is a hallway or a room inside each doorway.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s create ramp on the left side first. Draw the vertical back edge of the ramp against the wall, and extend the bottom edge of the ramp out in drawing compass direction SW.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw the thickness of the ramp with two lines in direction NW, matching the angles with the linesyou drew earlier in direction NW.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complete the far edge of the ramp by matching the angle of the front edge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Erase guide lines behind the ramp. Using the lines you already drew in direction NE as reference, draw the ramp on the right side.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complete your two-layered foreshortened ramp building by drawing the horizon line above the building, positioning your light source, and shading all the surfaces opposite your light position. Using your reference lines to angle the cast shadow correctly direction SW is really simple when you are drawing buildings; just extend the bottom lines. We are done!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s how my piece looks like:
&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/6C580A37-C2F4-4F72-B97D-CB89CABA6BBC.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lesson7&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2014 19:35:37 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//design/2014/03/03/Lesson-7-Advanced-Level-Cubes/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//design/2014/03/03/Lesson-7-Advanced-Level-Cubes/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Lesson 6 Stacking Tables</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;I will be drawing stacking tables with proper lighting conditions in this lesson. This lesson will gel all of the concepts and laws learnt so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Begin with a foreshortened square.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw two short edges to create the top of the table.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw the middle line longer, according to the foreshortened square concept.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using the lines you have already drawn as areference, draw bottom of the table top in direction of Northeast and Northwest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw middle line longer to create the near edge of the table post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw the sides of the table post. Each side line is drawn halfway from the far edge to the middle line.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using lines drawn as reference, draw the bottom of the table post in direction NW and NE.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw horizon line just above the table. and position light source aboce and to the right. The horizon line tells our eye that the object is below the horizon line, which communicates to our brain that the thickness, shadows, and foreshorteneing are from this perspective.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Place a guide dot directly below the near corner of the table post. If you don&amp;rsquo;t use the guide dot on every stacked table, your drawing may get progressively more skewed and impossibly distorted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using lines already drawn as a reference, draw the front edge of the pedestal in directions NW and NE.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now draw the back edges of the opt of the pedestal, be sure to go behind the corner of the post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complete the pedestal, makjing sure to draw the near corner lower. As always, use the lines you have already drawn as reference angles for drawing the bottom lines of the pedestal in directions NW and NE.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, add the cast shadow opposite your positioned light source, shade the table and pedestal and add the dark undershadows of both sides of the post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So here&amp;rsquo;s how my final drawing looks:
&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/AFA53C8F-34F6-4A7D-8C20-6DD868130467.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lesson7&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2014 21:34:18 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//design/2014/02/26/Lesson-6-Stacking-Tables/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//design/2014/02/26/Lesson-6-Stacking-Tables/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Don&#39;t distinguish between work and life</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.jamieleighto.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/07/Love-Your-Work.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;work&quot; /&gt;
Work is your life because work is your passion. If your work isn&amp;rsquo;t your passion, only a means of getting to your passion, then take it as a necessity and look it in as positive a light as possible. Your work doesnt suck because it is getting you to where you want to be. Its necessary and unavoidable if you want to get to where you want to be, for the life you wish to lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dont distinguish between work and life. It is one in the same and the sooner you accept that, the sooner you can release all that negativity you feel every time you think about all the work that needs to be done.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2014 11:33:09 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//random/2014/02/25/Dont-distinguish-between-work-and-life/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//random/2014/02/25/Dont-distinguish-between-work-and-life/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Ignorance of MLM marketeers</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m totally against Multi-Level-Marketing(MLM) or any form of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ponzi_scheme&quot;&gt;Ponzi schemes&lt;/a&gt; because it&amp;rsquo;s a questionable business model that does not offer any real values to the society Here&amp;rsquo;s my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/notes/guochen-hou/mlm-thanks-but-no-thanks/460181587333803&quot;&gt;reasons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of which, most MLM marketeers are just pure ignorant about the product they are trying to promote. Let&amp;rsquo;s be honest here, they are not really interested in &amp;lsquo;growing&amp;rsquo; you, they are just interested in entry fee you paid up upon joining the organization. More suckers like you joining as their downlinks means more loyalty fees into their pocket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s more of a joke is that most of these marketeers who approaches you doesn&amp;rsquo;t have the slightest idea about their product or the industry they are in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every month or so i&amp;rsquo;ll receive at least 1 of such invites to MLM. AND THEY JUST DONT DIE OFF! So last week i received this message on linkedin:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-02-16at30123pm.png&quot; alt=&quot;message1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Income diversification&amp;rsquo; is like an instant red flag to me. But being polite, i replied:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-02-16at30929pm.png&quot; alt=&quot;message2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon afterwards it start to sound more fishy in her reply:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-02-16at31133pm.png&quot; alt=&quot;message3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok seriously??? you are running an e-commerce business and your website is only accessible to a selected few??? It&amp;rsquo;s like saying,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;i&amp;rsquo;m opening a restaurant that only serves my friends and family.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great work so far Amirah. I decided to serve her own medicine back to her.
&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-02-16at31714pm.png&quot; alt=&quot;message4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, the last that she can do to save her sinking ship is to send me some PDFS, DOCS, WEBSITES depicting her business to get me interested. But it seems she doesn&amp;rsquo;t have any to begin with. Alas, this short and apparently-less-friendly message without signoffs came back:
&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-02-16at32155pm.png&quot; alt=&quot;message5&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OKAY. BITCHING TIME. My dear Amirah, it seems you don&amp;rsquo;t even understand the difference between &amp;lsquo;a wholesale/retail distribution channel&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;e-commerce distribution business&amp;rsquo;. A wholesale/retail distribution channel via internet is like &lt;a href=&quot;www.ebay.com.sg&quot;&gt;eBay&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;www.amazon.com&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; where you provide a medium for e-commerce business to operate and transact. An e-commerce business is where you USE this medium to perform ecommerce activities. Building an ebay shopfront to sell your products within ebay is totally different from building ebay.com itself. I can&amp;rsquo;t appreciate how you want to hire me to work for you, or as your down-link in your organization, when you can&amp;rsquo;t even figure out this simple difference about the industry you are supposedly to be an expert in. Preaching about a questionable business model is already being frowned upon. The worst you can do is to demonstrate that you know nothing about the industry you are in. Please Amirah, stop this madness.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2014 14:18:11 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//random/2014/02/16/Ignorance-of-MLM-marketeers/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//random/2014/02/16/Ignorance-of-MLM-marketeers/</guid>
                        </item>
                
        </channel>
</rss>