<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
        <channel>
                <title>GuoChen&#39;s Blog</title>
                <description>A glimpse of my life, my passion and my thoughts.</description>
                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com</link>
                <atom:link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Django environment optimal setup</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.djangoproject.com&quot;&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt; is a great web framework based on MVC architecture that allows you to quickly and correctly build and deploy web projects. However, staring a new Django project can be a little daunting and often the wrong setup can lead to long term problems for your project. Here i&amp;rsquo;m sharing with you my preferred workflow on starting a new Django project. A small bit of planning goes a long way towards making life easier!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A working knowledge of python language and Django framework is assumed. You will also have to know &lt;a href=&quot;http://git-scm.com&quot;&gt;git&lt;/a&gt; for version control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Install Python&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Head over to &lt;a href=&quot;http://python.org&quot;&gt;python.org&lt;/a&gt; and find the install instructions for your specific OS. For my development environment, i&amp;rsquo;m running MAC OSX Mavericks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To check you have installed python correctly, type&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ python
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;into terminal command line and you should get the following output:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Python 2.7.5 (default, Mar  9 2014, 22:15:05) 
[GCC 4.2.1 Compatible Apple LLVM 5.0 (clang-500.0.68)] on darwin
Type &quot;help&quot;, &quot;copyright&quot;, &quot;credits&quot; or &quot;license&quot; for more information.
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Install pip&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pip.readthedocs.org/en/latest/index.html&quot;&gt;Pip&lt;/a&gt; is a great tool for installing and managing python packages. We are going to use pip to install all third party packages to supplement our project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The easy way to install pip is to first download &lt;a href=&quot;https://bootstrap.pypa.io/get-pip.py&quot;&gt;get-pip.py&lt;/a&gt;. Then run the following command in the folder with the downloaded file on your terminal:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ python get-pip.py
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you are done installing! You can test pip installed correctly with the command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;pip -V
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which shows the version of your pip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Install virtualenv&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://virtualenv.readthedocs.org/en/latest/&quot;&gt;Virutalenv&lt;/a&gt; is a great tool to sandbox your development environments so you don&amp;rsquo;t have to switch back and forth between different versions of softwares. What&amp;rsquo;s more, the excellent extension &lt;a href=&quot;http://virtualenvwrapper.readthedocs.org/en/latest/&quot;&gt;virtualenvwrapper&lt;/a&gt; makes using virtualenv alot easier. This is common, recommend practice among python, Django users alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also going to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://pypi.python.org/pypi&quot;&gt;pip&lt;/a&gt; to install packages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, let&amp;rsquo;s install virtualenv. Note that you can get both virtualenv and virtualenvwrapp install just by install ing virtualenvwrapper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ pip install virtualenvwrapper
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After it&amp;rsquo;s installed, add following lines to your .bashrc file:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;export WORKON_HOME=$HOME/.virtualenvs
export PROJECT_HOME=$HOME/directory-you-do-development-in
source /usr/local/bin/virtualenvwrapper.sh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then type the following command to &amp;lsquo;activate&amp;rsquo; your modified .bashrc file:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ source .bashrc
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Creating new environment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To create a new virtual environment, type:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ mkvirtualenv django_project
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where django_project is whatever name your project is. You should see your shell is now prepended by (django_project).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The django_project prepending is a reminder that you are using virtualenv instal of your system&amp;rsquo;s Python installation. To exit, the virtual environment, simple type deactivate. When you want to resume work on your project, it&amp;rsquo;s as easy as typing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ workon django_project
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where you run the command doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Install Django&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we are working in virtualenv, we have to install Django into this virtual environment. This makes sure that the version of Django we use for this project is not confused with other versions used by the system or other virtual environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ pip install django
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This should give you the latest version of Django which will be installed in your virtualenv area. You can confirm this by doing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ which django-admin.py
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which should point to your $HOME/.virtualenvs/ directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Setup project folder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we can create our project directory. I highly recommend using &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/twoscoops/django-twoscoops-project&quot;&gt;two scoops Django&lt;/a&gt; project template for all Django projects. If you are new to two scoops django, it is actually a compilation of some of the best practices for developing Django projects. You can purchase a copy of this amazing book &lt;a href=&quot;http://twoscoopspress.org/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now go ahead and setup the project with this command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ django-admin.py startproject --template=https://github.com/twoscoops/django-twoscoops-project/archive/master.zip --extension=py,rst,html django_project
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that this command creates a django_project directory with the two scoops django template. I&amp;rsquo;ll leave you to read more about &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/twoscoops/django-twoscoops-project&quot;&gt;two scoops django template&lt;/a&gt; yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Source control&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Git is automatically installed in your virtual environment when you created it with virtualenvwrapper earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since our folder and file structure is up now, let&amp;rsquo;s commit them to source control right from the start. Here&amp;rsquo;s how to do that in git:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ git init
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creates a git repository in the current directory. Now let&amp;rsquo;s stage all of our files to git to be commited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ git add django_project
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we commit them to our new repository:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ git commit -m &quot;Initial commit of django_project&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s add the remote repository in &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com&quot;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ git remote add origin &amp;lt;remote repository URL&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, let&amp;rsquo;s push our changes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ git push origin master
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;South for database migrations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;South is a great tool that detects changes to your models layer and automatically sync the changes to your database without you having to dabble with the database itself. This is done through a migration file that South creates. This lets you both migrate the database forward for new change and backward to undo a change or series of changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our virtualenv, install south using pip:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ pip install south
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then setup south with the project by adding it to our INSTALLED_APPS in settings/base.py file for the project.
After which, run the command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# python manage.py syncdb
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;to sync the changes and south will be registered along with the project. South will also automatically setup the database with the tables it needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we commit, we will want tot rack our install Python packages. We want to track the name and version of the python packages we are using so we can recreate our environment easily in the production area. There&amp;rsquo;s a pip command that does this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ pip freeze &amp;gt; requirements.txt
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pushed the output of pip freeze to a file called requirements.txt which we will add to source control so we always have an updated list of packages being used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As before, we commit the changes to git and push to remote repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Install Fabric&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To easily deploy a Django application, we use &lt;a href=&quot;http://fabric.readthedocs.org/en/1.3.3/api/contrib/django.html&quot;&gt;Fabric&lt;/a&gt;. Fabric has a number of purposes but it really helps in quick deployments. Install Fabric with the command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ pip install fabric
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fabric expects a fabfile.py which defines all of the actions we can take. Let&amp;rsquo;s create that file and put the following in fabfile.py in your project&amp;rsquo;s root directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;from fabric.api import local

def prepare_deployment(branch_name):
local(&#39;python manage.py test django_project&#39;)
local(&#39;git add -p &amp;amp;&amp;amp; git commit&#39;) # or local(&#39;hg add &amp;amp;&amp;amp; hg commit&#39;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will run the test and commit your changes only if your tests pass. A simple &amp;ldquo;pull&amp;rdquo; in your production area becomes your deployment. Let&amp;rsquo;s add the following code to fabfile.py to actually deploy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;from fabric.api import lcd, local

def deploy():
with lcd(&#39;/path/to/my/prod/area/&#39;):

    # With git...
    local(&#39;git pull /my/path/to/dev/area/&#39;)

    # With Mercurial...
    local(&#39;hg pull /my/path/to/dev/area/&#39;)
    local(&#39;hg update&#39;)

    # With both
    local(&#39;python manage.py migrate myapp&#39;)
    local(&#39;python manage.py test myapp&#39;)
    local(&#39;/my/command/to/restart/webserver&#39;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will pull your changes from the development master branch, run any migrations you&amp;rsquo;ve made, run tests, and restart your web server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use this file, we simply type the following in production environment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ fab prepare_deployment
$ fab deploy
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;rsquo;s it! The skeleton for an optimal django environment is setup and ready to be developed! Remember, commit often, test everything. Let me know if i&amp;rsquo;ve missed out something! Rock on folks!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P/S: For your convenience, i have setup a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hguochen/django_template&quot;&gt;django_template&lt;/a&gt; on github based on the above instructions. You may wish to fork it for your own use!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EDIT: Thanks to Chng Nai Yun, i&amp;rsquo;ve corrected a silly error which incorrectly states that git is installed when you install virtualenvwrapper. In reality, git is only installed when you setup the virtualenv environment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2014 17:08:54 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//web%20development/2014/07/22/Django-environment-optimal-setup/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//web%20development/2014/07/22/Django-environment-optimal-setup/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>[Tip] Python class debugging tools</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;It can be tough trying to debug classes, inherited classes, class methods etc in general. Here&amp;rsquo;s 2 useful debugging utility functions i love to use to sort through the mess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;1. Printing attributes and values&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;def print_attr(obj):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    Traverses the items in the object&#39;s dictionary and prints each attribute name and its corresponding value.
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    for attr in obj.__dict__:
        print attr, getattr(obj, attr)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As explained in docstring, function print_attr() takes in an object and spits out each of its attributes and its corresponding value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The built-in function getattr() takes an object and an attribute name(as string) and returns the attribute&amp;rsquo;s value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;2. Find defining class&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;def find_defining_class(obj, method_name):
&quot;&quot;&quot;
Uses method resolution method(MRO) to get the list of class objects(types) that will be searched for methods.
Return the class to which the method &#39;method_name&#39; belong to.
&quot;&quot;&quot;
for origin in type(obj).mro():
    if method_name in origin.__dict__:
        return origin
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Useful if your class belongs to a long chain of super classes and you are trying to find out which class does a particular method belong to. This method works because of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.python.org/download/releases/2.3/mro/&quot;&gt;Method Resolution Order&lt;/a&gt; rule in python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hand = Hand()
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; print find_defining_class(hand, &#39;shuffle)
&amp;lt;class &#39;Card.Deck&#39;&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the shuffle method for this Hang object is the one in Deck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope this 2 utility debugging functions can save you time traversing those pesky bugs. Please share your secret debugging functions too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy debugging! Ok fine, that&amp;rsquo;s a fallacy&amp;hellip;Don&amp;rsquo;t die debugging!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2014 17:59:42 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//programming/python/2014/06/21/%5BTip%5D-Python-class-debugging-tools/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//programming/python/2014/06/21/%5BTip%5D-Python-class-debugging-tools/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Prim&#39;s Algorithm</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;Given six cities and the costs(in millions of dollars) of rebuilding roads between them. The road commission has decided to rebuild enough roads so that each pair of cities will be connected, either directly or by going through other cities, by rebuilt roads. Find a minimum cost set of roads meeting its criterion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Screenshot2014-06-17004156.png&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; alt=&quot;city roads&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We visited this question previously with &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.hguochen.com/programming/greedy%20algorithm/2014/06/17/Kruskal%27s-Algorithm/&quot;&gt;Kruskal&amp;rsquo;s Algorithm&lt;/a&gt;. Now let&amp;rsquo;s try a different approach using &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prim&#39;s_algorithm&quot;&gt;Prim&amp;rsquo;s Algorithm&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prim&amp;rsquo;s algorithm is another greedy algorithm that finds a minimal spanning tree in a connected, weighted graph. Unlike Kruskal&amp;rsquo;s algorithm, whose partial solutions are not necessarily connected, a partial solution in prim&amp;rsquo;s algorithm is a tree. Prim&amp;rsquo;s algorithm begins with a start vertex and no edges and then applies the greedy rule: Add an edge of minimum weight that has one vertex in the current tree and the other not in the current tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big idea is to maintain a table that stores each vertex with its corresponding edge weight value adjacent to the starting vertex in question. Additionally, we need an array to store the &amp;lsquo;parent&amp;rsquo; vertex that has access to the vertex in question. We then go about selecting the least weight value in the table and select it as the edge path to pick. The symbol for choosing this edge could be deleting the row entirely from the table. After each edge selection, we update the table with the newly accessible vertex. When there are no more rows left in the table, then we would have selected every edge required  of a minimum spanning tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the table above, we can use a python dictionary with key as the vertex and value as the edge weight with its &amp;lsquo;parent&amp;rsquo; vertex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also require a container to store the vertices each vertex is able to reach directly. For this container, we can use an adjacency list. adj[i] is a reference to the first node in a linked list of nodes representing the vertices adjacent to vertex i. Here&amp;rsquo;s the adjacency list implementation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;class Node:
&quot;&quot;&quot;
Node class defines the basic structure of a node.
&quot;&quot;&quot;
def __init__(self, vertex=None, weight=None, next=None):
    self.vertex = vertex
    self.weight = weight
    self.next = next    

class LinkedList:
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    LinkedList class defines a  linked list of nodes in which node.next reference the next node in the list
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    def __init__(self):
        self.head = Node()

    def get_head(self):
        &quot;&quot;&quot;
        Returns a reference to the head node
        &quot;&quot;&quot;
        return self.head

    def add(self, vertex, weight):
        &quot;&quot;&quot;
        Append a new node with node.vertex as vertex to the last element in the linked list
        &quot;&quot;&quot;
        new_node = Node(vertex, weight)
        trav = self.head
        while(trav.next != None):
            trav = trav.next
            trav.next = new_node

    def print_list(self):
        trav = self.head.next
        while trav != None:
            print &quot;(%d, %d)&quot; % (trav.vertex, trav.weight),
        trav = trav.next
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By calling the function adj_list.print_list() method, we should get the following printout, which is the content of each adjacent node in the list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(2, 4) (3, 2) (5, 3) None
(1, 4) (4, 5) None
(1, 2) (5, 6) (6, 3) (4, 1) None
(2, 5) (3, 1) (6, 6) None
(1, 3) (3, 6) (6, 2) None
(5, 2) (3, 3) (4, 6) None
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we define an Edges class to contain the table mentioned earlier. The class has a 2d list attribute like the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;edges = [[vertex, weight, parent_vertex],...]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each row of the table is represented by edges[i].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edges class has the following attributes and methods:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;class Edges:
&quot;&quot;&quot;
Edge table consisting of vertex, weight and parent_vertex in a row.
&quot;&quot;&quot; 
edge_table = []

def __init__(self, adj_ref, start): 
    while adj_ref != None:          
        self.edge_table.append([adj_ref.vertex, adj_ref.weight, start])
        adj_ref = adj_ref.next  

def get_table(self):
    return self.edge_table

def add_row(self, vertex, weight, parent_vertex):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    Add a row in table with vertex, weight and parent_vertex attributes
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    self.edge_table.append([vertex, weight, parent_vertex])

def pop_row(self):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    Delete the row in table with the smallest weight and return the corresponding vertex.
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    if len(self.edge_table) &amp;gt; 0:
        least_weight = self.edge_table[0][1]
        least_weight_index = 0
        for i in range(1, len(self.edge_table)):
            if self.edge_table[i][1] &amp;lt; least_weight:
                least_weight = self.edge_table[i][1]
                least_weight_index = i
        least_weight_vertex = self.edge_table[least_weight_index][0]
        self.edge_table.pop(least_weight_index)
        return least_weight_vertex
    else:
        return None

def is_in(self, vertex):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    Return true if vertex is in table and false otherwise.
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    for edge in self.edge_table:
        if edge[0] == vertex:
            return True
    return False

def vertex_weight(self, vertex):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    Return the weight corresponding to vertex.
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    for edge in self.edge_table:
        if edge[0] == vertex:
            return edge[1]
    return None

def update_row(self, vertex, weight, parent_vertex):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    Changes the weight and parent_vertex corresponding to existing vertex.
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    for edge in self.edge_table:
        if edge[0] == vertex:
            edge[1] = weight
            edge[2] = parent_vertex

def print_table(self):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    Print edge_table.
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    print self.edge_table
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, we have our prim&amp;rsquo;s algorithm to sort out the minimum spanning tree of the  directed, weighted graph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;def prim(adj_ref, start):
&quot;&quot;&quot;
Finds a minimal spanning tree in a connected, weighted, n-vertex graph. 
The graph is represented using adjacency lists; adj[i] is a reference to the    first node in a linked list of nodes.
The start vertex is start. In the minial spanning tree, the parent of a vertex  is defined as the vertex where existing minimal tree vertex extends from. 
Start vertex(parent of itself) is = 0.
&quot;&quot;&quot;
table = Edges(adj_ref[4].next, start)   
chosen = []
chosen.append(start)

while len(table.get_table()) &amp;gt; 0:
    table.print_table()
    ver = table.pop_row()
    chosen.append(ver)
    print &quot;Child vertex %d chosen.&quot; % ver
    trav = adj_ref[ver].next

    while trav != None:
        if trav.vertex in chosen:
            trav = trav.next
            continue
        if trav.vertex == start:
            trav = trav.next
            continue    
        if table.is_in(trav.vertex): # table has vertex
            if trav.weight &amp;lt; table.vertex_weight(trav.vertex): # new edge weight                is less than existing table value
                table.update_row(trav.vertex, trav.weight, ver) # update table                  to new vertex and weight
        else:
            # insert vertex and its elements into table
            table.add_row(trav.vertex, trav.weight, ver)
        trav = trav.next
print chosen
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The function prim is module level function and uses both Edges and LinkList classes to maintain interity and coherence of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s time to test the program:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;if __name__ == &quot;__main__&quot;:
    adj_list = [0] * 6 # an array of adjacency list instances
    adj = copy.deepcopy(adj_list) # references to head node

    for i in range(len(adj_list)):
        adj_list[i] = LinkedList() # declare linked list instance
        adj[i] = adj_list[i].get_head() # reference adj[i] to head node

    # Setup the adjacency list
    adj_list[0].add(1,4)
    adj_list[0].add(2,2)
    adj_list[0].add(4,3)

    adj_list[1].add(0,4)
    adj_list[1].add(3,5)

    adj_list[2].add(0,2)
    adj_list[2].add(4,6)
    adj_list[2].add(5,3)
    adj_list[2].add(3,1)

    adj_list[3].add(1,5)
    adj_list[3].add(2,1)
    adj_list[3].add(5,6)

    adj_list[4].add(0,3)
    adj_list[4].add(2,6)
    adj_list[4].add(5,2)

    adj_list[5].add(4,2)
    adj_list[5].add(2,3)
    adj_list[5].add(3,6)

    prim(adj, 4)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the last line prim(adj,4), the output would be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;[[0, 3, 4], [2, 6, 4], [5, 2, 4]]
Child vertex 5 chosen.

[[0, 3, 4], [2, 3, 5], [3, 6, 5]]
Child vertex 0 chosen.

[[2, 2, 0], [3, 6, 5], [1, 4, 0]]
Child vertex 2 chosen.

[[3, 1, 2], [1, 4, 0]]
Child vertex 3 chosen.

[[1, 4, 0]]
Child vertex 1 chosen.

[4, 5, 0, 2, 3, 1]  
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okok some explaination on the output here, Every successive 2 lines indicates a successful selection of a vertex to be chosen as part of the minimal spanning tree. Each of the first line of 2d lists indicates the available options in the table. Second line, Child vertex x chosen. indicates which of the vertex(and its corresponding row) is chosen. The last line outputs the order of which the vertices are selected, with the first element being the start vertex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prim&amp;rsquo;s algorithm is also an optimal implementation of the greedy algorithm to achieve a minimal spanning tree. However, through repeated runtime tests, it seems Prim&amp;rsquo;s algorithm is consistently faster than &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.hguochen.com/programming/greedy%20algorithm/2014/06/17/Kruskal%27s-Algorithm/&quot;&gt;Kruskal&amp;rsquo;s Algorithm&lt;/a&gt;. I did a time complexity analysis of Prim&amp;rsquo;s and came up with the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prim&amp;rsquo;s algorithm time complexity(major functions):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;**Operation**                   **Worst-Case Time**
Edges(adj_ref, start)           O(n)
pop_row()                       O(lg n)
is_in(vertex)                   O(1)
vertex_weight(vertex)           O(n)
update_row(vertex, weight, ..)  O(n)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outer while loop take time O(n). The inner loop has a relation with the number of edges. Since we know that given n vertices, there can be a maximum of 2n edges so the time complexity of the inner while loop has complexity of O(n**2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the final time complexity of prim&amp;rsquo;s algorithm will be O(n**3). This is a bad time complexity given that the operations are not very convoluted. I think the bottleneck of this implementation is the abstract data structure used. I used a linked list data structure which in itself has a complexity of O(n). If we can use a more efficient data structure such as binary minheap structure which has O(lg n) complexity, we can really reduce the time complexity of Prim&amp;rsquo;s algorithm to O(n2 lg n ). Maybe i&amp;rsquo;ll try to implement a binary minheap structure later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hguochen/algorithms/blob/master/python/prim.py&quot;&gt;full implementation&lt;/a&gt;. I would love to hear suggestions on how to improve the time complexity or anything in general. Cheers :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2014 16:29:39 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//programming/greedy%20algorithm/2014/06/17/Prim%27s-Algorithm/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//programming/greedy%20algorithm/2014/06/17/Prim%27s-Algorithm/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Kruskal&#39;s Algorithm</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;Given six cities and the costs(in millions of dollars) of rebuilding roads between them. The road commission has decided to rebuild enough roads so that each pair of cities will be connected, either directly or by going through other cities, by rebuilt roads. Find a minimum cost set of roads meeting its criterion.
&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Screenshot2014-06-17004156.png&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; alt=&quot;city roads&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an example of using a greedy algorithm in graph theory to find a minimum spanning tree for a connected weighted graph. Vertices represent the cities and edges represent the roads to be rebuilt. Red digits indicates the amount of money to rebuild that stretch of road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To solve the problem, 3 problems have to be addressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to represent the graph?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to select the edges in nondecreasing order by its weight?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to determine whether adding an edge would create a cycle?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The algorithm pseudocode for this problem follows the Kruskal algorithm:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;kruskal_algorithm(edgelist, n) {
    sort(edgelist)
    for i = 1 to n
        makeset(i)
    count = 0
    i = 1
    while count &amp;lt; n-1:
        if(findset(vertex1) != findset(vertex2)) {
            count += 1
            union(vertex1, vertex2)
        }
        i += 1
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we use a 2d array to represent each of the edges in the graph. eg. [1,2] would indicate an edge between city 1 and 2. Then we store the edge&amp;rsquo;s corresponding weight in another array with the weight as its element. eg.[4] for city 1 and 2. We also need a 3rd array to store all the vertices involved(purpose to be discussed). To avoid excessive parameter passing, let&amp;rsquo;s declare a Weighted_graph class:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;class Weighted_graph:
&quot;&quot;&quot;
Implement a weighted graph with a 2d list and a corresponding weight list
Vertices are represented by elements(eg. 1,2,3) in the graph list and edges are represented by a list collection of each 2 vertices
(eg. [1,2])
&quot;&quot;&quot;
edges = []
weight = []
vertices = []

def __init__(self, edge_list, weight):
    self.edges.append(edge_list)
    self.weight.append(weight)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the above graph, the corresponding data would be represented in our class attributes as the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;edges = [[3, 4], [1, 3], [5, 6], [1, 5], [3, 6], [1, 2], [2, 4], [3, 5], [4, 6]]
weight = [4,2,3,5,1,6,3,6,2]
vertices = [[1],[3],[4],[5],[6],[2]]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also going to add utility functions, add() and print() to aid in our implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;def add(self, edge_list, weight):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    Add an edge(defined by 2 vertices in a list) and its corresponding weight to edges
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    self.edges.append(edge_list)
    self.weight.append(weight)

def print_graph(self):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    Print each set of edges in a graph and its corresponding edges
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    print self.edges
    print self.weight
    print self.vertices
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, in order to select edges in nondecreasing order, we need to sort its corresponding weight in nondecreasing order. Here we use a simple insertion sort algorithm to do the job:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;def __sort(self):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    Sorts both edges and weight lists in nondecreasing order of weight list elements
    &quot;&quot;&quot; 
    if len(self.edges) != len(self.weight):
        return
    for i in range(1, len(self.weight)):
        temp_weight = self.weight[i]
        temp_edge = self.edges[i]
        current = i - 1
        while current &amp;gt;= 0 and temp_weight &amp;lt; self.weight[current]:
            self.weight[current+1] = self.weight[current]
            self.edges[current+1] = self.edges[current]
            current -= 1
        self.weight[current+1] = temp_weight
        self.edges[current+1] = temp_edge
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we need to be able to initialize each vertex to its own component in vertices array. Let&amp;rsquo;s use a private makeset function to achieve this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;def __makeset(self):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    Initialize each vertex to its own component
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    for i in range(len(self.edges)):
        for j in range(len(self.edges[i])):             
            if self.edges[i][j] not in self.vertices:
                self.vertices.append(self.edges[i][j])

    for k in range(len(self.vertices)):
        self.vertices[k] = [self.vertices[k]]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we need a way to find the corresponding vertex in the vertices list of list and return a index to the location of the vertex in question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;def __findset(self, vertex):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    Find and return the index to which vertex belongs in vertices list
    &quot;&quot;&quot;     
    for i in range(len(self.vertices)):
        for element in self.vertices[i]:
            if element == vertex:
                return i
    return None
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just 1 last function! We need to be able to merge the 2 vertex in vertices list together to indicate that their corresponding edge have been selected. We use a union function to manipulate the vertices list directly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;def __union(self, vertex1, vertex2):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    Joins 2 vertex together         
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    index1 = self.__findset(vertex1)
    index2 = self.__findset(vertex2)
    for element in self.vertices[index2]:
        self.vertices[index1].append(element)
    self.vertices.pop(index2)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we have all the functions we need to implement Kruskal&amp;rsquo;s algorithm. Let&amp;rsquo;s convert the pseudocode earlier to python codes&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;def kruskal(self):
    self.__sort()
    self.__makeset()
    count, i = 0, 0     
    while len(self.vertices) &amp;gt; 1:
        if self.__findset(self.edges[i][0]) != self.__findset(self.edges[i][1]):
            print &quot;(%d %d) edge selected.&quot; % (self.edges[i][0], self.edges[i][1])
            count += 1
            self.__union(self.edges[i][0], self.edges[i][1])
        i += 1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this implementation, we test run the codes and should be able to get the following output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(3 4) edge selected.
(1 3) edge selected.
(5 6) edge selected.
(1 5) edge selected.
(1 2) edge selected.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that our vertices list starts off like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;vertices = [[1],[3],[4],[5],[6],[2]]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As each set of edges is selected, its 2 cities are combined to indicate selection. This helps in determining if the graph is cyclic at each new edge selection stage. Finally, our vertices list looks like this, which indicates all the vertices are connected minimally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;vertices = [[1, 3, 4, 5, 6, 2]]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kruskal&amp;rsquo;s algorithm is a optimal implementation of greedy algorithm. Here&amp;rsquo;s my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hguochen/algorithms/blob/master/python/kruskal.py&quot;&gt;full implementation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2014 00:02:54 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//programming/greedy%20algorithm/2014/06/17/Kruskal%27s-Algorithm/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//programming/greedy%20algorithm/2014/06/17/Kruskal%27s-Algorithm/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Steps to solving programming problems</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;If you are looking for a systematic approach to solving programming problems, i have one for you here. This is my variation from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.coursehero.com/file/7263502/Programing-with-the-problem-Analysis-Coding-Execution-Cycle/&quot;&gt;Problem analysis coding execution cycle&lt;/a&gt; that typical computer science class will teach. Hope it will be of use to you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Problem analysis coding execution cycle&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;1. Analyse the problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;a. Problem specification&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What is the problem asking for?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;b. Requirements&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What are the constraints and requirements?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;c. Assumptions&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What are the underlying assumptions on the question?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Is there any assumptions which could be challenged?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;d. Sample test cases&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Identify at least 1 sample test case.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How many test cases should there be minimally?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;e. Determine input &amp;amp; output&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Determine the input and output and their corresponding data types&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;f. Identify input boundary cases&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;List out all boundary cases for inputs and logic flows.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;2. Implement the algorithm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;a. Algorithm structure&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What is the best data structure and data types for this problem?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;b. Design Algorithm&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Write algorithm in plain english or pseudo code.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Identify repeated patterns if any.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;c. Testing algorithm correctness&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Verbally run through the algrithm with pre-defined test cases&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;d. Write code&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Write code incrementally with adequete tests at each step.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;e. Test code correctness&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Run the code with sample inputs to test for desired outputs.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;f. Testing boundary cases&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Run the code with boundary cases and lookout for unexpected behaviors.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;d. Verify program correctness&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Re-visit the question and and lookout for inconsistencies  and redundancies.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;3. Program maintenance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;a. Determine time complexity&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What is the average case complexity?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What is the worst case complexity?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;b. Determine space complexity&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Are there redundant or unused variables?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;c. Refactoring&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Can the code be refactored to improve readability?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Can the algorithm be redesigned to improve efficiency?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;d. Documentation&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Leave comments where the abstraction logic is unclear.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Are there any trivial comments?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Write formal documentations if the program is expected to be used by people.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2014 16:07:39 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//programming/web%20development/2014/06/04/Steps-to-solving-programming-problems/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//programming/web%20development/2014/06/04/Steps-to-solving-programming-problems/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Culture in the Silicon Valley</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;In a recent visit to California, i visited a number of famous companies in the Silicon Valley such as Google, Facebook, Evernote, Quora, Airbnb etc. These are all the &amp;lsquo;cool&amp;rsquo; companies with great cultures that many would die to get in. But what really does it mean to have a great culture? Sure the oversized bean bags, foosball tables, free meals and modern-looking workspaces forms part of it. But as i learnt from the many visits, great culture is more than materialistic satisfactions and cool company perks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key, is that everyone in the company thinks alike. What does it mean? It means a collective group of people come together to live and breathe on the same set of problems, every single day. They believe that a company is greater than the sum of its parts. They sweat the mission and vision of their greater entity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Facebook, everyone wants to build things that makes people stay connected. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter if their role isn&amp;rsquo;t engineering. The company hired people who care about being social no matter what discipline they are in so this trait integrates into their daily work. They ruthlessly scrutinize their work in order to produce the best products that makes millions of people say &amp;lsquo;hello&amp;rsquo; each day. It is this shared camaraderie the eliminates frustrations when a better design is shot down by an engineering manager who just wants to fix bugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Airbnb wants to unlock unique spaces worldwide. This vision tickles down to every single one of its employees. In order for that, the company built an environment where you can spend time building a global reach instead of having to fight for time to do your laundry, or get frustrated over expensive lunches. All mundane things are taken care of, so you can focus on what really matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these, brings the idea that executing a company vision needs to be everyone&amp;rsquo;s job. Is everybody sharing the company&amp;rsquo;s delights and sorrows? Does everyone talk about user&amp;rsquo;s problems or talk about their own problems? I think a big reason why these companies consistently hit the top of &amp;lsquo;Dream company to work for&amp;rsquo; list is that they&amp;rsquo;ve figured out how to solve its employee&amp;rsquo;s little problems, in return for these talents helping to solve company&amp;rsquo;s big problems. It is also this realization that differentiates between a good company and a great company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you walk into your office tomorrow, start listening to what your employees are saying. If you can&amp;rsquo;t help them solve their daily problems, don&amp;rsquo;t expect them to solve yours.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2014 23:12:51 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//random/startup/2014/05/29/Culture-in-the-Silicon-Valley/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//random/startup/2014/05/29/Culture-in-the-Silicon-Valley/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Reverse a singly linked list</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;I came across this interesting programming question today and decided to give it a go. Given a singly linked list, with reference to the head node, reverse the linked list so the head node becomes the last node and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my iterative solution:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;public Node reverse(Node head) {
    if (head == null || head.next == null) { // Linked list is empty or only has 1 node
        return;
    }
    Node current = new Node();
    Node next = new Node();
    Node prev = null;

    current = head; // current node starts at the first node, which is referenced by head. keep in mind that head acts like a pointer here instead of a real node
    while(current != null) { //run loop as long as current node is not the last node
        next = current.next; // stores a reference of the next node so we can manipulate current.next reference
        current.next = prev; // point the current.next to the new reference position -which is in reverse order
        prev = current; // prev has done its job of referencing the previous node, it now moves on to reference the subsequent node
        current = next; // current has referenced in the new order, move current pointer to the next node - which is referenced by next pointer.
    }
    head = prev; // the last node is now the new first node in the linked list, so we reference head to prev, which points to the node itself
    return head
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let&amp;rsquo;s try the recursive solution:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Identify base case&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The base case occurs when we reach the last node of the linked list. We identify this case by verifying that current.next is NULL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Base case operation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the base case, we need to set the head pointer to the very last node, which will in turn become the first node in the result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my recursive answer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;public Node reverse(Node current) {
    if (current == null) { //check for empty list
        return;
    }

    if (current.next == null) { // at tail node, this is recursive base case
        head = current; // set head to point to the last node in original list
        return;
    }

    reverse(current.next);
    current.next.next = current; // set the subsequent node as the current node
    current.next = null; // set the previous node to null. which eventually means the older next pointer is used and null
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This little devil took me quite awhile to figure out as it&amp;rsquo;s very confusing between the reference pointers and the current nodes in question. But in practicality, i just can&amp;rsquo;t imagine a scenario where i&amp;rsquo;ll need to reverse a singly linked list. Can you? Whatever, this also proves that as a norm, we should just use a double linked list in the rare case we need to do a reversal like this. Time complexity of both of the solutions are O(n).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edit: On a side note, we can also do a shallow copy of the linked list to an array-like data structure, use a reverse() function and push into a fresh linked list. Horrible on the space complexity, but alot easier to understand.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2014 21:01:58 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//web%20development/2014/05/26/Reverse-a-linked-list/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//web%20development/2014/05/26/Reverse-a-linked-list/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>What i got from tweeting Evernote&#39;s CEO</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;In 4 day&amp;rsquo;s time, i&amp;rsquo;ll be visiting California-US for the first time in my life. Being &lt;a href=&quot;http://hguochen.com&quot;&gt;a startup guy&lt;/a&gt; myself, this is a big deal for me. I&amp;rsquo;m really excited to see what the biggest startup ecosystem in the world is like. I wanted to make this trip a really memorable one but i didn&amp;rsquo;t have enough contacts there. So i shamelessly cold-emailed some of my favourite tech companies in California asking for an impromptu visit to their offices/campus. Some of these companies accepted my request(thank you so much!). But 1 of which just blew me away. Here&amp;rsquo;s what happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always been a big fan of &lt;a href=&quot;http://evernote.com&quot;&gt;Evernote&lt;/a&gt;. After several failed attempts to link up with evernote staff through friend introductions, i resorted to cold-emailing its CEO, Phil Libin on linkedin&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/email_phil_libin.jpg&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; alt=&quot;Email Phil Libin&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok i admit, its kinda cheesy. But hey, i wasn&amp;rsquo;t expecting a reply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so i didn&amp;rsquo;t. Then i tried to ping the CEO on twitter, and i got a reply! Well, not Phil Libin himself, but still a reply :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/08915870-515D-4157-83DE-FD8EAB45C3C1.png&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; alt=&quot;Tweeting Phil Libin&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things are looking good! So i followed the instructions and the following conversations ensue:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/6734508A-2E9D-4FD7-AC1E-9637083A4991.png&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; alt=&quot;evernote support 1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/05DA55F4-D808-4BB6-AF8D-4B360307A636.png&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; alt=&quot;evernote support 2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/9ECCB770-E4ED-4566-B3CA-7E9C0F8F1A8D.png&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; alt=&quot;evernote support 3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few days later, this email from Evernote&amp;rsquo;s marketing manager came:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/evernote_email.png&quot; width=&quot;1050&quot; alt=&quot;evernote email&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How excited was i to read this? Let&amp;rsquo;s just say that my laptop keyboard now comes coffee-flavoured. Thank you Evernote, you&amp;rsquo;ve just made a fan very very happy :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll be giving a full recount of my visit to Evernote HQ sometime later. In the meantime, please leave in the comments below if you have a request for me on visiting Evernote :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2014 02:24:07 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//random/startup/2014/04/23/What-i-got-from-tweeting-evernote%27s-CEO/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//random/startup/2014/04/23/What-i-got-from-tweeting-evernote%27s-CEO/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Designing Beebeta</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;A recent side project of mine, Beebeta, is about to launch its MVP. I was involved in both the frontend and backend engineering of Beebeta. Check out Beebeta&amp;rsquo;s stack at &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.hguochen.com/web%20development/2014/03/31/Beebeta-Engineering/&quot;&gt;Beebeta Engineering&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being new to the world of frontend designing, i&amp;rsquo;m not sure if my design would be used eventually. But still, i would like to share my frontend design experience and concepts in this post. Partly to document my design journey but more importantly, encourage other programmers(like me) to pick up web designing in their free time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What is Beebeta?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Search engines are vast, and non-targeted. While you will definitely be able to find valuable facts and informations on topics, it is not built to reflect the public&amp;rsquo;s opinions on questions at hand. That&amp;rsquo;s what Beebeta is for. It gives you insights to what the crowd thinks about an issue. Which could be questions as trivial as &amp;lsquo;Which restaurant serves the best Ramen?&amp;rsquo; or global issues such as &amp;lsquo;Should gay marriage be allowed?&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Design Goal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the above concept, it is evident that Beebeta is all about polling the public with questions. We are going to implement this by asking users questions and offer pre-determined choices for voting. Users may also add additional choices if they like. Here are a few design goals i&amp;rsquo;ve charted out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Questions are the prime content of the website&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All visual elements should contribute to better contents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User&amp;rsquo;s Call To Action(CTA) is voting and should be encouraged visually&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Page should be simple and minimalistic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Research and idea generation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do some googling to get the creativity juices flowing. These are some of the places i checkout to brainstorm design ideas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pinterest.com&quot;&gt;Pinterest&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://smashingmagazine.com&quot;&gt;Smashing Magazine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://quora.com&quot;&gt;Quora&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://createivebloq.com&quot;&gt;Creative Bloq&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I usually grab a pencil and sketchbook to jot down some of the things such as essential page elements, layout, colors, typefaces and navigation details. Sometimes i feel particularly artistic and try to draw&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/EBAE3B09-C994-459F-AEB7-9964CA67A066.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; alt=&quot;doodle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok fine i admit calling it &amp;lsquo;drawing&amp;rsquo; is an overstatement. Very-very crude mockups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All my page designs start from mockups. From grid layout, to box structure and eventually down to individual elements. For each step of this process, i pay attention to how elements in question interacts with each other and establish cohesiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Grid Layout&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I adopted the 12-grid system for &lt;a href=&quot;http://getbootstrap.com/&quot;&gt;Bootstrap 3&lt;/a&gt;. Boostrap 3 is designed &amp;lsquo;mobile first&amp;rsquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s newly renovated grid system caters to a whole array of digital devices from mobile phone to high resolution desktops. A nice tutorial about the new grid system for Bootstrap is found &lt;a href=&quot;http://scotch.io/bar-talk/understanding-the-bootstrap-3-grid-system&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used the following grid dimensions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;/* 12 col responsive grid */

.row {
    clear: both;
    max-width: 1040px;
    margin: 0 auto;
}

[class^=&quot;col-&quot;]:last-child {
    margin: 0;
}

[class^=&quot;col-&quot;] {
    float: left;
    margin: 0 3.84615384615% 0 0;
    list-style: none;
    position: relative;
}


.col-xs-1 { width: 4.8076923077% }
.col-xs-2 { width: 13.4615384615% }
.col-xs-3 { width: 22.1153846154% }
.col-xs-4 { width: 30.7692307692% }
.col-xs-5 { width: 39.4230769231% }
.col-xs-6 { width: 48.0769230769% }
.col-xs-7 { width: 56.7307692308% }
.col-xs-8 { width: 65.3846153846% }
.col-xs-9 { width: 74.0384615385% }
.col-xs-10 { width: 82.6923076923% }
.col-xs-11 { width: 91.3461538462% }
.col-xs-12 { width: 100%; margin: 0 }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Typeface&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think typeface of a website determines the longevity and pleasure of browsing its contents. Good typefaces gives readability and allows you to focus on the content. For beebeta, i used &lt;strong&gt;serif&lt;/strong&gt; typeface for block headers and &lt;strong&gt;helvetica neue&lt;/strong&gt; for body texts. These are generally pretty safe typefaces for websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-31at30154pm.png&quot; alt=&quot;beebeta icon&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Beebeta typeface in the icon is given to me pre-designed as &lt;strong&gt;OratorStd&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Colour&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used 3 colors as the theme of Beebeta. 2 triad colors, &lt;strong&gt;#4288CA&lt;/strong&gt;(Celestial Blue) &amp;amp; &lt;strong&gt;#5CB85C&lt;/strong&gt;(Fern) and 1 neutral color &lt;strong&gt;#F0F0F0&lt;/strong&gt;(Beige Grey).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-31at31235pm.png&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; alt=&quot;color theme&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fern green&lt;/strong&gt; is used for navigational contents and Call To Action(CTA) activites users performs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Netural color &lt;strong&gt;Beige Grey&lt;/strong&gt; will make the base color of the site. This effectively allows focus on contents without too much &amp;lsquo;noise&amp;rsquo; from the background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Celestial Blue&lt;/strong&gt; are used as cordoned containers for user details and personal spaces within the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Effectively the site is just a mix and match of these 3 simple colours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Navigation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Navigation determines the usability of the site. For our Minimum Viable Product(MVP), which has limited features, i want users to understand the purpose of the website at a glance through navigational bar without having it competing for user attention from the contents. Since posting questions is fundamental to the site. It should have a visual focus primarily, with user utility functions available nearby. Here is how it looks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-31at125833pm.png&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; alt=&quot;navigation bar&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-31at33130pm.png&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; alt=&quot;navigation bar 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Header&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted a simple header without any unnecessary contents. It should be so painfully simple that it looks almost undesigned at all. I think the benefits of a bare-bone header drives clarity. That users don&amp;rsquo;t derive too much assumptions of the contents of the website based on header. It invites users browse to find out more. Here&amp;rsquo;s how it looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-31at33337pm.png&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;header&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am experimenting with color-coding of question categories here. Each category is assigned a colour. My aim is to promote category classifications so users sub-consciously associate a colour to a category. I&amp;rsquo;m guessing this will contribute to an easier browsing experience over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Question Card&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Question card is the main content. It is what beebeta is all about. My design concept for questions takes the form of &amp;lsquo;question cards&amp;rsquo;. Each poll question is a unique question card served.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-31at34610pm.png&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;question card&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to synchronise the color-coding category concept earlier, i added a subtle colour border for each question card of its associated category. The question card displays the question text, user uploaded image, uploader&amp;rsquo;s name, number of choices and number of votes received so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Voting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I adopted the classic reddit style voting which allows users to vote up a choice and provide a visual feedback with updated vote count and fern green arrow up button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-31at40029pm.png&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; alt=&quot;voting&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Profile page&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an extension of the &amp;lsquo;question card&amp;rsquo; concept, i gave a similar box style to profile page. Users have 3 profile boxes which is unique to them, namely User Information, Questions and Votes counts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-31at40212pm.png&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; alt=&quot;profile page&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following tab, My questions, allows users to view and edit his posted questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-31at40736pm.png&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; alt=&quot;my questions&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Footer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve choosen flat white for footer, which colour synchronises with the header. Again, i&amp;rsquo;m experimenting with using lighter colours as opposed to heavy colors for headers and footers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-31at40922pm.png&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; alt=&quot;footer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;rsquo;s it folks! If you think that this design is really basic, you are right! I do agree that there are alot more to be done with the design of a polling site like Beebeta. I would like to hear your comments and suggestions on how i can improve my design. Peace out! :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2014 11:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//design/web%20development/2014/04/01/Designing-Beebeta/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//design/web%20development/2014/04/01/Designing-Beebeta/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Beebeta Engineering</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/leeagustiadi&quot;&gt;Agus&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/jaielhaevin&quot;&gt;Joel&lt;/a&gt; conceptualized the Beebeta project sometime ago and invited me to handle the technical aspect of it. I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what Beebeta was then but the moment i heard of the idea, i loved it! We spent our valuable weekends hacking out Beebeta and we are going to release it very soon! &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.beebeta.com&quot;&gt;Beebeta v1.0&lt;/a&gt; is finally out for public thrashing and hating! Ok but please be nice :(&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having architected the Beebeta backend, i thought it would be fun to give an idea of Beebeta from an engineering perspective. This is how we think an online polling system should be built. Feel free to disagree, we would love to hear your opinions :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, Beebeta is a web platform to gather crowdsourced knowledge. It is an online timeless repository of public opinions which is easily accessible through a poll-like web interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Why Beebeta?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Search engines are vast, and non-targeted. While you will definitely be able to find valuable facts and informations on topics, it is not built to reflect the public&amp;rsquo;s opinions on questions at hand. That&amp;rsquo;s what Beebeta is for. It gives you insights to what the crowd thinks. Which could be questions as trivial as &amp;lsquo;Which restaurant serves the best Ramen?&amp;rsquo; or global issues such as &amp;lsquo;Should gay marriage be allowed?&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok so much for pitching, that&amp;rsquo;s not the purpose of this post. We are here for the nerd stuff arn&amp;rsquo;t we?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Engineering Goal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the implementation of Beebeta, we had a few goals in mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t do unnecessary stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t reinvent the wheel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be versatile in technology options&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;OS/Hosting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beebeta runs Ubuntu 13.10(Saucy Salamander) on Amazon EC2. We tried Linux AMI(CentOS) on EC2 but find the environment not as usable as Ubuntu, plus the software updates were not consistently updated. Also, stress tests on the CentOS server resulted in unpredictable crashes. Since Beebeta is a small project, we ruled out self-hosting as an option. We definitely don&amp;rsquo;t want to waste time setting up servers ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Load Balancing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All server requests goes through our load balancers. We use Amazon&amp;rsquo;s Elastic Load Balancer(ELB) with 2 Nginx instances behind it. I admit now may be abit too early to devote load balancing resources but in case of unexpected traffic spikes, it will be good to pick up from here and scale instead of getting caught off-guard. I skipped using anything to handle the DNS though. But i may revisit the issue with Amazon&amp;rsquo;s Route53 in future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Application Server&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.python.org/download/releases/2.7.5/&quot;&gt;Python 2.7.5&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.djangoproject.com/&quot;&gt;Django 1.6.2&lt;/a&gt; was used on Amazon micro-instance machines. To encourage decoupling with the machine itself, we used &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.virtualenv.org&quot;&gt;virtualenv&lt;/a&gt; to sandbox the development environment. As such, the machines become stateless and we can easily spring up more instances and deploy direct when it comes to scaling up. Dedicated IP is also allocated to the instance. I&amp;rsquo;m guessing that most of the requests would be CPU-intensive than memory-intensive, so at the moment, a micro-instance would suffice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mod_wsgi is used as our WSGI server, together with Apache and Mysql. A typical LAMP stack. I&amp;rsquo;m exploring the possibility of shifting to &lt;a href=&quot;http://gunicorn.org&quot;&gt;Gunicorn&lt;/a&gt; in future. I read some tutorials on gunicorn and found it easier to configure. But the standard mod_wsgi is good for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Data storage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meta-data&amp;rsquo;s such as tags, url strings etc lives in MySql table rows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our BLOB data lives in Amazon&amp;rsquo;s S3 standard storage. I thought of using glacier storage for original files and standard storage for rendered files but unfortunately S3 does not provide glacier storage in Singapore region yet. I forsee using glacier storage would cut costs by about 30% for every 10GB of data. Will keep in view for future changes, once glacier storage is opened up in Singapore. Content Distribution wise, we use &lt;a href=&quot;http://aws.amazon.com/cloudfront&quot;&gt;Amazon CloudFront&lt;/a&gt;, which helps with page load times from users at different parts of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caching wise, we use memcached and currently have 1 memcached instance, which is connected to using pylibmc &amp;amp; libmemcached. I&amp;rsquo;m aware there&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://aws.amazon.com/elasticache/&quot;&gt;Amazon&amp;rsquo;s Elastic Cache&lt;/a&gt; service for this, but i havent got around to reading up on that yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Django apps&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of our goal not to reinvent the wheel. we used quite a few out-of-the-box django apps to facilitate building of Beebeta platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://boto.readthedocs.org/en/latest/ref/s3.html&quot;&gt;S3Boto&lt;/a&gt; is used to connect the server scripts with different Amazon web services seamlessly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pythonhosted.org/django-analytical/services/mixpanel.html&quot;&gt;Django-analytical&lt;/a&gt; is used to track various site metrics on the application itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pypi.python.org/pypi/django-debug-toolbar&quot;&gt;Django-debug-toolbar&lt;/a&gt;(my favourite debugging tool!) is used on development environments for almost all debugging tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pypi.python.org/pypi/django-pagination&quot;&gt;Django-pagination&lt;/a&gt; is used to paginate database querysets into proper pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://south.readthedocs.org/en/latest/&quot;&gt;Django-south&lt;/a&gt; is used to easily perform database migration tasks between ORM and the database itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bitbucket.org/ubernostrum/django-registration/&quot;&gt;Django-registration&lt;/a&gt; is used to handle user registration/login/logout issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Monitoring&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are using &lt;a href=&quot;https://mixpanel.com&quot;&gt;Mixpanel&lt;/a&gt; to track user activites on the site. These tracking statistics are filtered up to 2 timeless campaigns. First campaign to track site traffic activites such as page traffic, user sign ups etc. Second campaign to track question and choices interactions of all questions on the site. At any one time we will know which questions are most popular or which group of users are most active at different times of the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For backend monitoring, we are using &lt;a href=&quot;http://newrelic.com&quot;&gt;New Relic&lt;/a&gt; to track application performance and server performance. We establish a certain threshold for performance issues on both of these assets and issue warning emails to administrators when the threshold is almost reaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Python error reporting, we use &lt;a href=&quot;http://sentry.readthedocs.org/en/latest/&quot;&gt;Sentry&lt;/a&gt;, an open-source Django app written by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://disqus.com&quot;&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt; folks. We can closely monitor error messages at real-time relatively easy with this handy tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s your stack?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s so much for Beebeta stack. Feel free to leave your comments below if you think we&amp;rsquo;ve made a terrible mistake. Otherwise, I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear how you implement your stacks!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, i&amp;rsquo;ve been playing this song on repeats all day in my coding time. It just energizes me for the tasks at hand. Hope you like it too! :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;420&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/c_H3MWVx6JU?color=white&amp;theme=light&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

</description>
                                <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2014 16:19:30 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://blog.hguochen.com//web%20development/2014/03/31/Beebeta-Engineering/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.hguochen.com//web%20development/2014/03/31/Beebeta-Engineering/</guid>
                        </item>
                
        </channel>
</rss>