<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: startup | GuoChen | Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/categories/startup/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-21T18:20:07+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[GuoChen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Culture in the Silicon Valley]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/random/startup/2014/05/29/Culture-in-the-Silicon-Valley/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-29T23:12:51Z</updated>
    <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/random/startup/2014/05/29/Culture-in-the-Silicon-Valley</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a recent visit to California, i visited a number of famous companies in the Silicon Valley such as Google, Facebook, Evernote, Quora, Airbnb etc. These are all the &lsquo;cool&rsquo; companies with great cultures that many would die to get in. But what really does it mean to have a great culture? Sure the oversized bean bags, foosball tables, free meals and modern-looking workspaces forms part of it. But as i learnt from the many visits, great culture is more than materialistic satisfactions and cool company perks.</p>

<p>The key, is that everyone in the company thinks alike. What does it mean? It means a collective group of people come together to live and breathe on the same set of problems, every single day. They believe that a company is greater than the sum of its parts. They sweat the mission and vision of their greater entity.</p>

<p>At Facebook, everyone wants to build things that makes people stay connected. It doesn&rsquo;t matter if their role isn&rsquo;t engineering. The company hired people who care about being social no matter what discipline they are in so this trait integrates into their daily work. They ruthlessly scrutinize their work in order to produce the best products that makes millions of people say &lsquo;hello&rsquo; each day. It is this shared camaraderie the eliminates frustrations when a better design is shot down by an engineering manager who just wants to fix bugs.</p>

<p>Airbnb wants to unlock unique spaces worldwide. This vision tickles down to every single one of its employees. In order for that, the company built an environment where you can spend time building a global reach instead of having to fight for time to do your laundry, or get frustrated over expensive lunches. All mundane things are taken care of, so you can focus on what really matters.</p>

<p>All these, brings the idea that executing a company vision needs to be everyone&rsquo;s job. Is everybody sharing the company&rsquo;s delights and sorrows? Does everyone talk about user&rsquo;s problems or talk about their own problems? I think a big reason why these companies consistently hit the top of &lsquo;Dream company to work for&rsquo; list is that they&rsquo;ve figured out how to solve its employee&rsquo;s little problems, in return for these talents helping to solve company&rsquo;s big problems. It is also this realization that differentiates between a good company and a great company.</p>

<p>When you walk into your office tomorrow, start listening to what your employees are saying. If you can&rsquo;t help them solve their daily problems, don&rsquo;t expect them to solve yours.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What i got from tweeting Evernote's CEO]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/random/startup/2014/04/23/What-i-got-from-tweeting-evernote%27s-CEO/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-23T02:24:07Z</updated>
    <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/random/startup/2014/04/23/What-i-got-from-tweeting-evernote's-CEO</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In 4 day&rsquo;s time, i&rsquo;ll be visiting California-US for the first time in my life. Being <a href="http://hguochen.com">a startup guy</a> myself, this is a big deal for me. I&rsquo;m really excited to see what the biggest startup ecosystem in the world is like. I wanted to make this trip a really memorable one but i didn&rsquo;t have enough contacts there. So i shamelessly cold-emailed some of my favourite tech companies in California asking for an impromptu visit to their offices/campus. Some of these companies accepted my request(thank you so much!). But 1 of which just blew me away. Here&rsquo;s what happened.</p>

<p>I have always been a big fan of <a href="http://evernote.com">Evernote</a>. After several failed attempts to link up with evernote staff through friend introductions, i resorted to cold-emailing its CEO, Phil Libin on linkedin&hellip;</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/email_phil_libin.jpg" width="500" alt="Email Phil Libin" /></p>

<p>Ok i admit, its kinda cheesy. But hey, i wasn&rsquo;t expecting a reply.</p>

<p>And so i didn&rsquo;t. Then i tried to ping the CEO on twitter, and i got a reply! Well, not Phil Libin himself, but still a reply :)</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/08915870-515D-4157-83DE-FD8EAB45C3C1.png" width="250" alt="Tweeting Phil Libin" /></p>

<p>Things are looking good! So i followed the instructions and the following conversations ensue:</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/6734508A-2E9D-4FD7-AC1E-9637083A4991.png" width="250" alt="evernote support 1" />
<img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/05DA55F4-D808-4BB6-AF8D-4B360307A636.png" width="250" alt="evernote support 2" />
<img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/9ECCB770-E4ED-4566-B3CA-7E9C0F8F1A8D.png" width="250" alt="evernote support 3" /></p>

<p>A few days later, this email from Evernote&rsquo;s marketing manager came:</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/evernote_email.png" width="1050" alt="evernote email" /></p>

<p>How excited was i to read this? Let&rsquo;s just say that my laptop keyboard now comes coffee-flavoured. Thank you Evernote, you&rsquo;ve just made a fan very very happy :)</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll be giving a full recount of my visit to Evernote HQ sometime later. In the meantime, please leave in the comments below if you have a request for me on visiting Evernote :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Not all businesses are startups]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/startup/2013/12/07/Not-all-businesses-are-startups/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-07T12:07:49Z</updated>
    <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/startup/2013/12/07/Not-all-businesses-are-startups</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Had this conversation between some friends the other day and i realised there’s a few common misconceptions between startups and businesses. Not all businesses can be called startups, while startups most common entity is a business entity.</p>

<p>A start-up, by definition, is a temporary organisation designed to search for a scalable business model. Apart from typical business risks, there are more inherent risks such as finding product-market fit, research deficiencies etc.</p>

<p>A business is a corporate entity that is growth oriented. It has, by default, found its product-market fit and operating on a scalability model.</p>

<p>Starting a company on teleportation or building the next generation flying car is considered a startup. But opening a drink store selling sugared water is not a startup. The baseline being, if you are treading on a previously explored path then your entity is NOT a startup.</p>

<p>On a side note, startups should always move out of its current being as soon as possible. There is no glory in maintaining the buzzword title for x years.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
