<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: web | GuoChen | Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/categories/web/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-08T15:27:01+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[GuoChen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lesson 0 Why learn to draw]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/design/web/2014/01/01/lesson-0-why-learn-to-draw/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-01T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/design/web/2014/01/01/lesson-0-why-learn-to-draw</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Learning an all time amazement</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;m a web developer by trade and have never got around to the area of design. Which makes me all the more curious to explore the world of typography, colors, layouts etc.</p>

<p>Inspired by <a href="http://www.karenx.com/blog/how-to-become-a-designer-without-going-to-design-school/">Karen&rsquo;s learn design blogpost</a>, i&rsquo;ve decided to teach myself everything about design in the fresh year. Starting from the basics, i&rsquo;m learning to draw by hand. I believe the fundamental appreciation for design comes from hand-eye coordindation.</p>

<p>I got my hands on <a href="http://www.amazon.com/You-Can-Draw-30-Days/dp/0738212415/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1371607474&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=you+can+draw+in+30+days">You can draw in 30 days</a> to guide me along the fundamentals of drawing and dealing with my ridiculously ugly drawing base. If you are learning drawing as well, you may want to get a copy of this book if you are a fast learner. Or you could just follow along with my progress. I&rsquo;ll be documenting the things i learnt from this book and try to present them in a manner you can follow too. Please feel free to give me feedbacks on how to improve.</p>

<p>Ok enough background paintings, let&rsquo;s get started.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s begin with a little pretest to see how good or bad you are at drawing currently.</p>

<ol>
<li>Spend 2 minutes drawing a house, without referencing anything, just from your imagination.</li>
<li>Next, spend 2 minutes drawing an airplane. Again, from imagination.</li>
<li>Ok i promise it&rsquo;s the last one. Spend 2 minutes drawing a bagel.</li>
</ol>


<p>Don&rsquo;t worry if your drawing is hideous, no one has to see it! So now that you have your &lsquo;base&rsquo; work at hand, put this up somewhere secret so you can compare how much you have improved overtime. If it&rsquo;s any consolation, my work is attached below&hellip;feeling better now?</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/7A895527-8CB4-46BF-A0D1-F1DCF9514D0F.jpg" alt="Drawing_lesson_0" /></p>

<p>Ok now chuck it aside and hop on to <a href="/2014/01/02/lesson-1-the-sphere/">Lesson 1 The Sphere</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
