<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: random | GuoChen | Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/categories/random/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-24T16:12:36+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[GuoChen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Could this be the most discriminatory Job Description ever?]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/random/2014/09/24/Could-this-be-the-most-discriminatory-Job-Description-ever%3F/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-24T14:13:17Z</updated>
    <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/random/2014/09/24/Could-this-be-the-most-discriminatory-Job-Description-ever?</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So i just chanced upon what i think is the most discriminatory Job Description(JD) ever. Either the company is trying too hard to be hip or they are simply jerks.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the <a href="http://careers.wewantsugar.com/jobs/4413-lead-software-engineer-technical-sugar-singapore">brain numbing JD</a> by a Singapore startup called <a href="http://www.wewantsugar.com">wewantsugar</a>. Don&rsquo;t be fooled by its name, there&rsquo;s no sweetness whatsoever as far as i can see. Let&rsquo;s go through what&rsquo;s wrong with this piece of golden nugget.</p>

<p><strong>Here&rsquo;s what they want:</strong>
<img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Screen_Shot_2014-09-24_at_2_50_00_pm.png" width="600" alt="paragraph 1" /></p>

<p>First of all you sidelined majority of Singaporeans whose life inadvertently goes down the path of having kids, buying flat, cars and awaiting CPF withdrawal. So are you implying none of your employees would ever take this path? I&rsquo;d imagine that would be a really scary company to work with.</p>

<p>Next. The notion of working till midnight is a circumstance of situation, NOT a default choice. We developers never starts off a day telling ourselves &ldquo;damn i&rsquo;m gona make sure i work late into the night.&rdquo; When we do, it&rsquo;s because we are passionate for what we do and we feel responsible enough to finish what we started. How come you never mentioned anything about productivity? What&rsquo;s your reason for wanting someone who willingly want to work late into the night? So that you can work-torture the poor dude and slap a &lsquo;he likes it anyway&rsquo; statement to justify your abuse? That&rsquo;s a really cruel employer.</p>

<p><strong>Feeling good yet? Here&rsquo;s who they don&rsquo;t want:</strong>
<img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Screen_Shot_2014-09-24_at_3_22_59_pm.png" width="600" alt="paragraph 2" /></p>

<p>Just what&rsquo;s with shaming of the corporates by calling them &lsquo;shallow social climber&rsquo;? How does wanting to work for prestigious companies like Goldman Sachs make them shallow? The very organisations you marginalise gave you your bank account, connected your cellphone to your loved ones and makes sure there&rsquo;s food to be bought when you visit NTUCs. Your every statement tells me you despise people who doesn&rsquo;t share your beliefs and dreams while being painfully oblivious to what&rsquo;s around you. Speaking of shallow, this company seems to fit the bill quite well.</p>

<p>Oh and you don&rsquo;t want social misfits? You don&rsquo;t want people who were always the last to get picked? Sounds like you are the big bad bully in school whom everyone hated. You know what? Some of the most successful technology companies are where they are today because the misfits envisioned something others didn&rsquo;t and built products that made everyone else&rsquo;s life better. But i&rsquo;m glad you didn&rsquo;t see that. Least you ruin the opportunity cost of another genius in the making. By the way, your advice, &lsquo;go seek help from a mental health professional&rsquo; is totally misguided and only goes to show how ugly you are as a person. Misfits do not have a mental condition, this company&rsquo;s management does.</p>

<p><strong>Still Convinced you are perfect for this job? Here&rsquo;s their requirements:</strong></p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-09-24at31630pm.png" width="400" alt="paragraph 3" /></p>

<p>Holy shit! That&rsquo;s even longer than my mum&rsquo;s monthly shopping list. You must be looking to hire <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elon_Musk">Elon Musk</a> and ready to pay shitloads of salary compensation.</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Screen_Shot_2014-09-24_at_3_19_11_pm.png" width="600" alt="paragraph 4" /></p>

<p>Did you know that in <a href="http://www.mom.gov.sg/employment-practices/fair-employment/Pages/fair-employment.aspx">Singapore&rsquo;s Ministry of Manpower Employment Act</a>, it is forbidden to ask potential employees for photographs as a factor of employment considerations? Look like either you need to do more homework or you chose to disregard the employment act totally. Either ways, how can employees even start to trust that you will take care of them?</p>

<p>Oh look, for a Lead Software Engineer position and all that essential attributes and requirements, you are paying SGD4,000 &ndash; 5,000? It&rsquo;s like asking for whales and paying peanuts.</p>

<p>Those are two full pages of prejudices, discriminatory remarks and statements that shows how ugly this employer can get. I am a software engineer and i would NEVER work for this company ever. I would strongly advise every software engineer to stay clear of your company as well.</p>

<p>Again, here&rsquo;s the <a href="http://careers.wewantsugar.com/jobs/4413-lead-software-engineer-technical-sugar-singapore">brain numbing JD</a>. Just why isn&rsquo;t there some sort of ethics or personality test before someone is allowed to incorporate a company?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Culture in the Silicon Valley]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/random/startup/2014/05/29/Culture-in-the-Silicon-Valley/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-29T23:12:51Z</updated>
    <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/random/startup/2014/05/29/Culture-in-the-Silicon-Valley</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a recent visit to California, i visited a number of famous companies in the Silicon Valley such as Google, Facebook, Evernote, Quora, Airbnb etc. These are all the &lsquo;cool&rsquo; companies with great cultures that many would die to get in. But what really does it mean to have a great culture? Sure the oversized bean bags, foosball tables, free meals and modern-looking workspaces forms part of it. But as i learnt from the many visits, great culture is more than materialistic satisfactions and cool company perks.</p>

<p>The key, is that everyone in the company thinks alike. What does it mean? It means a collective group of people come together to live and breathe on the same set of problems, every single day. They believe that a company is greater than the sum of its parts. They sweat the mission and vision of their greater entity.</p>

<p>At Facebook, everyone wants to build things that makes people stay connected. It doesn&rsquo;t matter if their role isn&rsquo;t engineering. The company hired people who care about being social no matter what discipline they are in so this trait integrates into their daily work. They ruthlessly scrutinize their work in order to produce the best products that makes millions of people say &lsquo;hello&rsquo; each day. It is this shared camaraderie the eliminates frustrations when a better design is shot down by an engineering manager who just wants to fix bugs.</p>

<p>Airbnb wants to unlock unique spaces worldwide. This vision tickles down to every single one of its employees. In order for that, the company built an environment where you can spend time building a global reach instead of having to fight for time to do your laundry, or get frustrated over expensive lunches. All mundane things are taken care of, so you can focus on what really matters.</p>

<p>All these, brings the idea that executing a company vision needs to be everyone&rsquo;s job. Is everybody sharing the company&rsquo;s delights and sorrows? Does everyone talk about user&rsquo;s problems or talk about their own problems? I think a big reason why these companies consistently hit the top of &lsquo;Dream company to work for&rsquo; list is that they&rsquo;ve figured out how to solve its employee&rsquo;s little problems, in return for these talents helping to solve company&rsquo;s big problems. It is also this realization that differentiates between a good company and a great company.</p>

<p>When you walk into your office tomorrow, start listening to what your employees are saying. If you can&rsquo;t help them solve their daily problems, don&rsquo;t expect them to solve yours.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What i got from tweeting Evernote's CEO]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/random/startup/2014/04/23/What-i-got-from-tweeting-evernote%27s-CEO/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-23T02:24:07Z</updated>
    <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/random/startup/2014/04/23/What-i-got-from-tweeting-evernote's-CEO</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In 4 day&rsquo;s time, i&rsquo;ll be visiting California-US for the first time in my life. Being <a href="http://hguochen.com">a startup guy</a> myself, this is a big deal for me. I&rsquo;m really excited to see what the biggest startup ecosystem in the world is like. I wanted to make this trip a really memorable one but i didn&rsquo;t have enough contacts there. So i shamelessly cold-emailed some of my favourite tech companies in California asking for an impromptu visit to their offices/campus. Some of these companies accepted my request(thank you so much!). But 1 of which just blew me away. Here&rsquo;s what happened.</p>

<p>I have always been a big fan of <a href="http://evernote.com">Evernote</a>. After several failed attempts to link up with evernote staff through friend introductions, i resorted to cold-emailing its CEO, Phil Libin on linkedin&hellip;</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/email_phil_libin.jpg" width="500" alt="Email Phil Libin" /></p>

<p>Ok i admit, its kinda cheesy. But hey, i wasn&rsquo;t expecting a reply.</p>

<p>And so i didn&rsquo;t. Then i tried to ping the CEO on twitter, and i got a reply! Well, not Phil Libin himself, but still a reply :)</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/08915870-515D-4157-83DE-FD8EAB45C3C1.png" width="250" alt="Tweeting Phil Libin" /></p>

<p>Things are looking good! So i followed the instructions and the following conversations ensue:</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/6734508A-2E9D-4FD7-AC1E-9637083A4991.png" width="250" alt="evernote support 1" />
<img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/05DA55F4-D808-4BB6-AF8D-4B360307A636.png" width="250" alt="evernote support 2" />
<img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/9ECCB770-E4ED-4566-B3CA-7E9C0F8F1A8D.png" width="250" alt="evernote support 3" /></p>

<p>A few days later, this email from Evernote&rsquo;s marketing manager came:</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/evernote_email.png" width="1050" alt="evernote email" /></p>

<p>How excited was i to read this? Let&rsquo;s just say that my laptop keyboard now comes coffee-flavoured. Thank you Evernote, you&rsquo;ve just made a fan very very happy :)</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll be giving a full recount of my visit to Evernote HQ sometime later. In the meantime, please leave in the comments below if you have a request for me on visiting Evernote :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Ukraine problem explained]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/random/2014/03/09/The-Ukraine-problem-explained/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-09T23:03:29Z</updated>
    <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/random/2014/03/09/The-Ukraine-problem-explained</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The hottest global news recently has been about ouster of Ukraine president Viktor Yanukovych and the russian invasion of Ukraine. I&rsquo;m generally indifferent towards international politics but it&rsquo;s becoming pretty big of an issue such that even technology blogs that i follow started posting news about these messy squabbles. I spent about 2 hours reading up whatever i can find on this issue and i&rsquo;ll try to explain it as clear as possible. So other political frog-in-a-well people (like me) can understand. Beware, what&rsquo;s going on below is extremely complicated. I suggest you close this tab right now if you have something better to do.</p>

<p>Still up for this shit? Here goes.</p>

<h4>How did Ukraine come about?</h4>

<p><img src="http://www.lonelyplanet.com/maps/europe/ukraine/map_of_ukraine.jpg" alt="ukraine map" /></p>

<p>So this is Ukraine, the second largest country in europe by area and Crimea peninsula is that little almost-island like area below. During the crimean war, A.D 1853- A.D 1856, it was sort of the Catholics vs the Orthodox but in grandier scale it was the European powers vs Russia as the Ottoman empire decline. Eventually Russia was defeated and the war accumulated a death of 500,000. In a claim of territory for the victors, many european moved over to what is present day Ukraine and settled there, together with some of the indigenious russians. But trouble never ceased and somewhat contributed to the World War I 60 years later.</p>

<p>At the end of World War I, Russian revolution begun and gave birth to communism. The russians were too busy overthrowing their own government and had no time to bother its neighbours such as Ukraine. It was these brief period that Ukraine had some days of independence. Finally when Russia became USSR, under the soviet regime, they incited its neighbouring countries to embrace communism. So between 1917 &ndash; 1921, another 1.5million people died around the russian neighbours and eventually led to Ukraine being a satellite country of the mighty USSR. Things became worse after that. When Joseph Stalin took over, the purging began and almost 10 million Ukrainians died between 1932 &ndash; 1933. What&rsquo;s worse, during World War II, Stalin deported the entire population of Crimea to central asia and moved Russians into Ukraine. Imagine a foreigner coming to your home and kicking you out? That&rsquo;s what happened to Crimea. Nikita Khrushchev, stalin&rsquo;s successor, then decided to transfer the Crimean Peninsula from Russia to Ukraine in 1954. Why? Because Crimean Peninsula is not geographically attached to Russia mainland. It will be easier to administer places where you are geographically connected.</p>

<h4>What are the Ukraine ethnic groups?</h4>

<p><img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/b/ba/Nativelanguage2001ua.PNG/420px-Nativelanguage2001ua.PNG" alt="language" /></p>

<p>Today, 67% of people in Ukraine speaks Ukrainian as their first language. 30% speaks Russian, although only about 17% of them identify themselves as Russian. When USSR dissolved, many Russians from Crimea returned to their homes in Russian so as of today, only 12% of Russians are located in the Crimean Peninsula.</p>

<h4>What kind of government did Ukraine had?</h4>

<p>In December 1991, after the Soviet Union broke up, Ukraine had a nation-wide referendum and 90% of its people, including people in Crimean Peninsula, voted for independence from Russia. But in effect, Ukraine had much closer ties with Russia than any other previous Soviet satellite countries.</p>

<p>In 2004, there was a general election. The election was plagued with vote rigging and eventually the pro-Russian leader Viktor Yanukovych(the dude who got overthrown) was elected to become the president. His opponent, the opposition, Viktor Yushchenko led a series of massive protest on the injustice and rigged election. Eventually Viktor Yushchenko was disfigured, crucified and purged. In the following years, since Putin came to power in Russia, the number of assassinations and poisoning of political dissidents skyrocketed in Ukraine. Coincidence? Nope.</p>

<p>Viktor Yanukovych had almost dictatorial power in Ukraine. But despite being an economist, he wasn&rsquo;t particularly gifted in bringing the country&rsquo;s economy to prosperity and people suffered under his rule. Furthermore, his friendliness towards the western european countries angered Russia whom cut off gas supplies briefly in 2006 and led to few national disasters in Ukraine.</p>

<p>In 2010 election, Viktor Yanukovych was elected president.</p>

<h4>Ok enought history lesson. What is the latest Ukraine issue about?</h4>

<p>In November 2013, Viktor Yanukovych denounced an agreement to strengthen ties with the European Union and become a closer ally with Russia. This single event sparked the massive protest in the nation, starting from The Independence Square. The protests lasted several months and dozens of protesters were killed by military police and government troops. On 1st March 2014, Viktor Yanukovych fled from his house in Kiev. The protesters had won. Following on, the people called for new elections. Putin was not happy with this outcome. He ostensibly pushed his troops into the Crimean Peninsula in the name of protecting the ethnic Russians in the region. This violated the territory integrity of Ukraine and Ukraine kicked up a big freaking deal.</p>

<p>At this moment, Crimea is already an autonomous province. It had rights to govern itself without much interference from Ukraine. Although it&rsquo;s electricity and water still comes from Ukraine. So what does Crimea want? Independence? Unification with Russia? Well, Crimea doesn&rsquo;t know what she wants herself. And that&rsquo;s why there has been so much fuss on the international stage.</p>

<p>Ukraine has a law that Ukraine is only to be governed by Ukrainians. Sounds legit right? But the problem is, many people in the country still speak russian instead of Ukrainian. Furthermore, the new government wants to be a part of European Union which might mean that it will bring in North Atlantic Treat Organization(NATO) military defences into Ukraine. This is a huge deal for Russia as it means now we have missles deployed right at its doorstep. That is unacceptable to Russia.</p>

<p>But in the viewpoint of western countries, Ukrain had a tyrannical leader who ordered the murder of peaceful protestors and was chased away from power and replaced with a government that will transition Ukraine to a free and fair election. Russia responded to that by invading Ukraine.</p>

<p>I would attribute much of the present day tension between east and west to the differences in these viewpoints. Russia took a pre-emptive measure to secure its borders from unfriendly states while the western countries worried for a resurgence of Soviet Union and trampling of a democratic state.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s ironical is that the word &lsquo;Ukraine&rsquo; means border-land and it has been the border between eastern and western countries for decades. Much of what we are seeing now is just another re-enactment of previous clashes.</p>

<p>So that&rsquo;s about it. Do you have a good solution to this? I don&rsquo;t. I&rsquo;m just a programmer who writes &lsquo;hello world&rsquo; and wishes for world peace.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Don't distinguish between work and life]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/random/2014/02/25/Dont-distinguish-between-work-and-life/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-25T11:33:09Z</updated>
    <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/random/2014/02/25/Dont-distinguish-between-work-and-life</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.jamieleighto.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/07/Love-Your-Work.jpg" alt="work" />
Work is your life because work is your passion. If your work isn&rsquo;t your passion, only a means of getting to your passion, then take it as a necessity and look it in as positive a light as possible. Your work doesn’t suck because it is getting you to where you want to be. It’s necessary and unavoidable if you want to get to where you want to be, for the life you wish to lead.</p>

<p>Don’t distinguish between work and life. It is one in the same and the sooner you accept that, the sooner you can release all that negativity you feel every time you think about all the work that needs to be done.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
