<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: design | GuoChen | Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/categories/design/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-01-08T19:23:28-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[GuoChen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Redesigning marathonsingapore.com]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/web%20development/design/frontend/2014/09/11/Redesigning-marathonsingapore.com/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-11T06:19:34-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/web%20development/design/frontend/2014/09/11/Redesigning-marathonsingapore.com</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/marathonsingapore_redesign.jpg" width="600" alt="marathonsingapore redesigned" /></p>

<h2>The Situation</h2>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/screencapture-www-marathonsingapore-com.png" width="400" alt="Marathonsingapore.com" /></p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.marathonsingapore.com">Standard Chartered Marathon Singapore</a> has been around for years and has always been hailed as the golden running event of Singapore. However, for an event with such fame and recognition, its website <a href="http://www.marathonsingapore.com">www.marathonsingapore.com</a> is just really ugly and site navigation is nothing less than complete frustration. The frontpage looks cluttered without any form of information hierarchy. Contents are hidden among a sphagetti of flashy colours. On searching for information, i have to actually resort to googling about the site instead of navigating the site itself. I consider that a failure in content design.</p>

<p>Ok let&rsquo;s be systematic about its shortcomings. Here are the problems i have identified on the current site design:</p>

<ul>
<li>Page styles that can be rendered with HTML/CSS are instead done with raw jpg images. Looks like optimization concerns was thrown right out the building from the start.</li>
<li>A simple inspect element reveals a total of 8 colors used for the frontpage. Some of these colors are neither analogous nor complementary to each other. The resulting visual distraction is appalling.</li>
<li>Call to Action(CTA) buttons are hidden among less relevant contents.</li>
<li>Content flow on page are non-hierarchical.</li>
<li>Site navigation bar are cluttered and information meta-data is a mess.</li>
<li>Date, Time &amp; Place(DTP) are non obvious at a glance.</li>
<li>Lack of sitemap to aid user navigation.</li>
<li>Teaser box contents are prefixed with useless meta-info such as Images, Videos, Highlights etc.</li>
<li>For a running event, statistics banner information are totally irrelevant. Would the public seriously care about how many bananas or amount of water consumed in a race held last year? Since i&rsquo;m not your logistics officer, i would be more interested in learning how many runners participated in each category don&rsquo;t you think?</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-09-11at44030pm.png" width="600" alt="statistics banner" /></p>

<h2>My Task</h2>

<p>With the problems identified, my job scope is pretty clear from now on. Here are my design objectives:</p>

<ol>
<li>Re-introduce a color theme to the site such that it puts the focus on the content.</li>
<li>Organize the navigation bar that correctly depicts the meta-datas.</li>
<li>Collate a sitemap to be appended to the footer for easier site navigation.</li>
<li>Use visual cues to bring out the importance of CTAs.</li>
<li>Redesign teaser boxes as an entry point to the site&rsquo;s content.</li>
</ol>


<h2>Action</h2>

<h4>Logo and navigation bar</h4>

<p>Race date, time and venue are probably the 3 most important piece of information for a running event. So we are going to place them right where visitors first sees when visiting our page.</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-09-11at50832pm.png" width="600" alt="top banner" /></p>

<p>Since there are many race categories for Standard Chartered Marathon, the start times for different races are staggered. In this case, to prevent confusion, we obscure time information from the banner and present them in the event schedule instead.</p>

<p>Navigation bar is restructured and renamed to correctly identify relevant meta-datas. Some of the less relevant information such as &lsquo;2013 results&rsquo; are demoted from this piece of expensive real estate.</p>

<p>Before:</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-09-11at51610pm.png" width="600" alt="navigation bar before" /></p>

<p>After:</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-09-11at51738pm.png" width="600" alt="navigation bar after" /></p>

<h4>Carousel section</h4>

<p>Before:</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-09-11at52122pm.png" width="600" alt="carousel section before" /></p>

<p>After:</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-09-11at52134pm.png" width="600" alt="carousel section after" /></p>

<p>The current carousel section had a bad choice of picture. This contributes to obscuring the importance of CTAs. Instead of choosing pictures, we are going to completely remove pictures as part of carousel theme and introduce a reasonable tagline to supplement the website&rsquo;s agenda.</p>

<p>Clear CTAs sits just below the tagline to guide users on the appropriate course of action.</p>

<p>The countdown to race day is a pretty good idea, but it was previously obscured in the right corner of the page. I redesigned and moved the countdown timer to dead center.</p>

<h4>Teaser boxes</h4>

<p>Before:</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-09-11at53842pm.png" width="400" alt="teaser box before" /></p>

<p>After:</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-09-11at53817pm.png" width="400" alt="teaser box after" /></p>

<p>The existing teaser section didn&rsquo;t make sense to me. What does &lsquo;IMAGES&rsquo; and &lsquo;VIDEOS&rsquo; section header tell you? I re-worked this section completely to reflect the content groupings of the website. These teasers will serve as entry point to its respective array of contents.</p>

<h4>Footer and sitemap</h4>

<p>Before:</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-09-11at54535pm.png" width="600" alt="footer before" /></p>

<p>After:</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-09-11at54543pm.png" width="600" alt="footer after" /></p>

<p>For easier site navigation, i&rsquo;ve added a simple footer that allows users to view the content headers at a glance.</p>

<h2>Result</h2>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/screencapture-rawgit-com-hguochen-marathon_singapore-master-index-html.png" width="600" alt="redesigned marathonsingapore.com" /></p>

<p>The static page is hosted <a href="https://rawgit.com/hguochen/marathon_singapore/master/index.html">HERE</a> if you would like to inspect elements and dabble with my design. Otherwise, for the geeks out there, this project also sits on my <a href="https://github.com/hguochen/marathon_singapore.git">github repository</a>. Let me know what you think about my redesign and leave in the comments below!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Designing Beebeta]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/design/web%20development/2014/04/01/Designing-Beebeta/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-01T04:48:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/design/web%20development/2014/04/01/Designing-Beebeta</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A recent side project of mine, Beebeta, is about to launch its MVP. I was involved in both the frontend and backend engineering of Beebeta. Check out Beebeta&rsquo;s stack at <a href="http://blog.hguochen.com/web%20development/2014/03/31/Beebeta-Engineering/">Beebeta Engineering</a>.</p>

<p>Being new to the world of frontend designing, i&rsquo;m not sure if my design would be used eventually. But still, i would like to share my frontend design experience and concepts in this post. Partly to document my design journey but more importantly, encourage other programmers(like me) to pick up web designing in their free time.</p>

<h2>What is Beebeta?</h2>

<p>Search engines are vast, and non-targeted. While you will definitely be able to find valuable facts and informations on topics, it is not built to reflect the public&rsquo;s opinions on questions at hand. That&rsquo;s what Beebeta is for. It gives you insights to what the crowd thinks about an issue. Which could be questions as trivial as &lsquo;Which restaurant serves the best Ramen?&rsquo; or global issues such as &lsquo;Should gay marriage be allowed?&rsquo;.</p>

<h2>Design Goal</h2>

<p>With the above concept, it is evident that Beebeta is all about polling the public with questions. We are going to implement this by asking users questions and offer pre-determined choices for voting. Users may also add additional choices if they like. Here are a few design goals i&rsquo;ve charted out:</p>

<ul>
<li>Questions are the prime content of the website</li>
<li>All visual elements should contribute to better contents</li>
<li>User&rsquo;s Call To Action(CTA) is voting and should be encouraged visually</li>
<li>Page should be simple and minimalistic</li>
</ul>


<h2>Research and idea generation</h2>

<p>Do some googling to get the creativity juices flowing. These are some of the places i checkout to brainstorm design ideas:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://pinterest.com">Pinterest</a></li>
<li><a href="http://smashingmagazine.com">Smashing Magazine</a></li>
<li><a href="http://quora.com">Quora</a></li>
<li><a href="http://createivebloq.com">Creative Bloq</a></li>
</ul>


<p>I usually grab a pencil and sketchbook to jot down some of the things such as essential page elements, layout, colors, typefaces and navigation details. Sometimes i feel particularly artistic and try to draw&hellip;</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/EBAE3B09-C994-459F-AEB7-9964CA67A066.jpg" width="300" alt="doodle" /></p>

<p>Ok fine i admit calling it &lsquo;drawing&rsquo; is an overstatement. Very-very crude mockups.</p>

<h2>Design</h2>

<p>All my page designs start from mockups. From grid layout, to box structure and eventually down to individual elements. For each step of this process, i pay attention to how elements in question interacts with each other and establish cohesiveness.</p>

<h3>Grid Layout</h3>

<p>I adopted the 12-grid system for <a href="http://getbootstrap.com/">Bootstrap 3</a>. Boostrap 3 is designed &lsquo;mobile first&rsquo;. It&rsquo;s newly renovated grid system caters to a whole array of digital devices from mobile phone to high resolution desktops. A nice tutorial about the new grid system for Bootstrap is found <a href="http://scotch.io/bar-talk/understanding-the-bootstrap-3-grid-system">here</a>.</p>

<p>I used the following grid dimensions:</p>

<pre><code>/* 12 col responsive grid */

.row {
    clear: both;
    max-width: 1040px;
    margin: 0 auto;
}

[class^="col-"]:last-child {
    margin: 0;
}

[class^="col-"] {
    float: left;
    margin: 0 3.84615384615% 0 0;
    list-style: none;
    position: relative;
}


.col-xs-1 { width: 4.8076923077% }
.col-xs-2 { width: 13.4615384615% }
.col-xs-3 { width: 22.1153846154% }
.col-xs-4 { width: 30.7692307692% }
.col-xs-5 { width: 39.4230769231% }
.col-xs-6 { width: 48.0769230769% }
.col-xs-7 { width: 56.7307692308% }
.col-xs-8 { width: 65.3846153846% }
.col-xs-9 { width: 74.0384615385% }
.col-xs-10 { width: 82.6923076923% }
.col-xs-11 { width: 91.3461538462% }
.col-xs-12 { width: 100%; margin: 0 }
</code></pre>

<h3>Typeface</h3>

<p>I think typeface of a website determines the longevity and pleasure of browsing its contents. Good typefaces gives readability and allows you to focus on the content. For beebeta, i used <strong>serif</strong> typeface for block headers and <strong>helvetica neue</strong> for body texts. These are generally pretty safe typefaces for websites.</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-31at30154pm.png" alt="beebeta icon" /></p>

<p>The Beebeta typeface in the icon is given to me pre-designed as <strong>OratorStd</strong>.</p>

<h3>Colour</h3>

<p>I used 3 colors as the theme of Beebeta. 2 triad colors, <strong>#4288CA</strong>(Celestial Blue) &amp; <strong>#5CB85C</strong>(Fern) and 1 neutral color <strong>#F0F0F0</strong>(Beige Grey).</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-31at31235pm.png" width="500" alt="color theme" /></p>

<p><strong>Fern green</strong> is used for navigational contents and Call To Action(CTA) activites users performs.</p>

<p>Netural color <strong>Beige Grey</strong> will make the base color of the site. This effectively allows focus on contents without too much &lsquo;noise&rsquo; from the background.</p>

<p><strong>Celestial Blue</strong> are used as cordoned containers for user details and personal spaces within the site.</p>

<p>Effectively the site is just a mix and match of these 3 simple colours.</p>

<h3>Navigation</h3>

<p>Navigation determines the usability of the site. For our Minimum Viable Product(MVP), which has limited features, i want users to understand the purpose of the website at a glance through navigational bar without having it competing for user attention from the contents. Since posting questions is fundamental to the site. It should have a visual focus primarily, with user utility functions available nearby. Here is how it looks:</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-31at125833pm.png" width="700" alt="navigation bar" /></p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-31at33130pm.png" width="700" alt="navigation bar 2" /></p>

<h3>Header</h3>

<p>I wanted a simple header without any unnecessary contents. It should be so painfully simple that it looks almost undesigned at all. I think the benefits of a bare-bone header drives clarity. That users don&rsquo;t derive too much assumptions of the contents of the website based on header. It invites users browse to find out more. Here&rsquo;s how it looks like:</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-31at33337pm.png" width="600" alt="header" /></p>

<p>I am experimenting with color-coding of question categories here. Each category is assigned a colour. My aim is to promote category classifications so users sub-consciously associate a colour to a category. I&rsquo;m guessing this will contribute to an easier browsing experience over time.</p>

<h3>Question Card</h3>

<p>Question card is the main content. It is what beebeta is all about. My design concept for questions takes the form of &lsquo;question cards&rsquo;. Each poll question is a unique question card served.</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-31at34610pm.png" width="600" alt="question card" /></p>

<p>In order to synchronise the color-coding category concept earlier, i added a subtle colour border for each question card of its associated category. The question card displays the question text, user uploaded image, uploader&rsquo;s name, number of choices and number of votes received so far.</p>

<h3>Voting</h3>

<p>I adopted the classic reddit style voting which allows users to vote up a choice and provide a visual feedback with updated vote count and fern green arrow up button.</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-31at40029pm.png" width="200" alt="voting" /></p>

<h3>Profile page</h3>

<p>As an extension of the &lsquo;question card&rsquo; concept, i gave a similar box style to profile page. Users have 3 profile boxes which is unique to them, namely User Information, Questions and Votes counts.</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-31at40212pm.png" width="500" alt="profile page" /></p>

<p>The following tab, My questions, allows users to view and edit his posted questions.</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-31at40736pm.png" width="500" alt="my questions" /></p>

<h3>Footer</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ve choosen flat white for footer, which colour synchronises with the header. Again, i&rsquo;m experimenting with using lighter colours as opposed to heavy colors for headers and footers.</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-31at40922pm.png" width="700" alt="footer" /></p>

<p>So that&rsquo;s it folks! If you think that this design is really basic, you are right! I do agree that there are alot more to be done with the design of a polling site like Beebeta. I would like to hear your comments and suggestions on how i can improve my design. Peace out! :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to design your blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/design/development/2014/03/23/How-to-design-your-blog/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-23T11:18:25-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/design/development/2014/03/23/How-to-design-your-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently i redesigned my <a href="http://blog.hguochen.com">blog</a>. It was an enjoyable experience as i try to apply my new-acquired <a href="http://design.tutsplus.com/articles/50-totally-free-lessons-in-graphic-design-theory--psd-2916">design theories</a> learnt from <a href="http://design.tutsplus.com">tutsplus.com</a>. My goal was to create an <strong>elegant</strong> and <strong>easy-to-read</strong> blog that represents myself both visually and content-wise. In this post, i will bring you through some of my design considerations for my blog.</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at63512pm.png" width="500" alt="hguochen blog" /></p>

<p><em>A look behind the scene of my blog redesign</em></p>

<hr />

<h2>Define your brief</h2>

<p>As with any projects, it&rsquo;s important to figure what exactly you want to achieve and jot it down clearly. This can be a constant reminder as you progress through the design stages. At this point, we just need to figure out our ultimate goal without being worried about the details.</p>

<p>I wanted to design a blog that is <strong>simple to navigate</strong> on index page and contains <strong>easy-to-read</strong> blogposts across different devices. All of these pages should clearly define me and my thoughts.</p>

<h2>Research and idea generation</h2>

<p>Do some googling to get the creativity flowing. Inspirations can come from anywhere. Some of the best places i recommend to check out are:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://pinterest.com">Pinterest</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.smashingmagazine.com">Smashing Magazine</a></li>
<li><a href="http://wordpress.org/themes/">Wordpress Themes</a></li>
<li><a href="http://medium.com">Medium</a></li>
</ul>


<p>As you go through these websites, grab a pen and sketchbook to jot down some of the things such as positions of blog elements, layout, colours, typefaces and navigation details commonly used. This will give you a basic idea of the contents to cover in designing your blog.</p>

<h2>Design considerations</h2>

<p>I wanted users to easily browse through my blog and focus on what i&rsquo;ve written, so i&rsquo;m not going to have too many &lsquo;content&rsquo; pages such as about me, work, contact me etc. These side dishes are more for a portfolio page rather than a blog. In fact, i&rsquo;m only going to have 2 main pages:</p>

<ul>
<li>Index page</li>
<li>Content page</li>
</ul>


<p>Based on my these ideas, it seems that i will need total control of designing my blog. I can&rsquo;t afford to use ready made templates such as from <a href="http://wordpress.com">Wordpress</a>. Instead, i&rsquo;m using a blog engine called <a href="http://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a> where i have the freedom to configure every element of my blog.</p>

<h3>Index page</h3>

<p>This will be the main page of the blog, which is also what greets users when they type in my blog url. Considering a typical user has a short attention-span of only 5 seconds on a webpage, i will need to present the entirety of my blog in that timeframe. Its good to give a short introduction of myself and the genre of this blog.</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at72040pm.png" width="500" alt="blog intro" /></p>

<p>Next i need a way to quickly tell visitor what kind of topics i write about, and there&rsquo;s no better way than allowing them to glance through my blog topics in a short scroll. Many blogs present their latest blogposts at the top. I think this is a bad practice as your latest blogpost might not necessarily be of visitors' interest. Sieving through your entire post to look at your other blogposts is just too much of a pain to get to know you. I&rsquo;d advise against irritating your visitors.</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at73003pm.png" width="500" alt="blog index browsing" /></p>

<p>With the year-annotated scrolling, my visitors will be able to quickly scroll through my list of blogposts and look for interests. We are providing a &lsquo;simple to navigate&rsquo; index page, as part of our objective listed above.</p>

<h3>Content page</h3>

<p>This is the meat of the blog. In fact, most visitors will be entering your blog through a blogspot than index page itself. It is important to establish some form of coherence between the content page and the index page. I chose to do it subtlely by appending my blog thumbnail picture at the top of the page. Followed by the date of the blogpost and topic.</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at74802pm.png" width="500" alt="blogpost header" /></p>

<p>Footer of the blogpost should be dedicated to interactivity. If visitors has taken the time to read to the bottom, he/she most probably have enjoyed the post. It is good to elicit further action by either allowing the visitor to share on social domains or provide a comment for further discussion.</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at74945pm.png" width="500" alt="blogpost footer" /></p>

<h3>On Measure</h3>

<p><img src="http://www.markboulton.co.uk/images/uploads/measure_1.gif" alt="measure" /></p>

<p>Measure, is the name given to the width of a body of type. There are several units of measurement used for defining the measure&rsquo;s width. Three basic units are:</p>

<ul>
<li>One point = 1/72 of an inch</li>
<li>One pic = 12 points</li>
<li>One em = Distance horizontally equal to the type of size, in points. you are using. Eg. 1em of 12pt type is 12pt.</li>
</ul>


<p>For a full width monitor, the optimum measure for reading is between <strong>66-72 words</strong> a line. If you scale that down to a mobile screen, measure would come down to about <strong>8-13 words</strong> a line.</p>

<h3>On font-size</h3>

<p>Appropriate font size will greatly enhance the readability of texts. I shall not go into detail here but some tried and tested font sizes for blog contents adopts the following pixel sizes:</p>

<ul>
<li>16px - Body copy and leading</li>
<li>24px - Main heading &amp; section headings</li>
<li>18px - Subheadings</li>
<li>13px - All other headed elements</li>
</ul>


<p>This will give the following styles visually:</p>

<p><img src="http://www.markboulton.co.uk/images/uploads/typo4_headings.gif" width="300" alt="font sizes" /></p>

<p>For the frontend designers, your CSS could look like this with the specifications above:</p>

<pre><code>body {
    font: 16px/1.5em "Lucida Grande";
}

h1, h2, h3, h4, h5, h6 {
    font-family: helvetica, arial, verdana, sans-serif;
    font-weight: normal;
}

h1 {
    font-size: 218%;
}

h2 {
    font-size: 164%;
}

h3 {
    font-size: 145%;
}

h4 {
    font-size: 118%;
}
</code></pre>

<h3>On typefaces</h3>

<p>We read most easily with what we are most familiar with. This would mean the traditional serif family of typefaces. But even in the serif family, there are countless kinds of typefaces to choose from. On choosing a typeface, i&rsquo;ve had a long trial and error on this. Here are 3 different serif types i&rsquo;ve experimented with using on the same content:</p>

<hr />

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at82316pm.png" width="400" alt="helvetica_neue" />
<strong>helvetica neue</strong></p>

<p>Helvetica is a great font for texts, but it is not such a great typeface for continuous smooth reading. It lacks the &lsquo;legs&rsquo; seen on other typefaces which provides the smooth gliding feel when reading on a screen.</p>

<hr />

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at82347pm.png" width="400" alt="sans-serif" />
<strong>sans-serif</strong></p>

<p>Serif is a safe font. Generally you won&rsquo;t go wrong with this font. However, since i prefer a lighter shade of texts, i have to reduce the font-weight from normal 300 to 200. This didn&rsquo;t fare well with serif typeface and words appear to thin to read properly.</p>

<hr />

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at82121pm.png" width="400" alt="georgia" />
<strong>georgia</strong></p>

<p>Part of the serif typeface family, georgia has always been a strong choice for continous texts. Some of the most popular web such as <a href="http://medium.com">Medium</a> and <a href="http://www.nytimes.com">NyTimes</a> uses georgia to render their texts. An additional advantage of georgia typeface is that it&rsquo;s distinctive enough that font colors normally won&rsquo;t erode its readability.</p>

<hr />

<p>After weighing the considerations, i&rsquo;ve decided to use &lsquo;Helvetica Neue&rsquo; for headings and &lsquo;georgia&rsquo; for paragraph texts. Here&rsquo;s how it looks like:</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at74802pm.png" width="500" alt="blogpost header" /></p>

<h3>On font color</h3>

<p>Black text on white background offers the best readability. However, prolonged exposure on black contrasted texts could be painful to our eyes since modern screen brightness are getting better and better. As such, i&rsquo;ve decided to reduce the contrast of texts by changing paragraph texts to a &lsquo;greyier&rsquo; color while not compromising readability. After some trial and error, the color i&rsquo;ve chosen is a grey with hexcode: #333332.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.colorhexa.com/333332.png" height="150" width="200" alt="333332" /></p>

<h2>Responsive Design</h2>

<p>The last of my consideration is to make sure my blog is readable on both mobile and desktop devices alike.</p>

<p>I like to use a grid because it provides a structural foundation, whiel making the development process easier and more efficient. Using a flexible grid enables a website to sclae dynamically to fit any device width. Below is the CSS for my responsive grid, which is my variations from <a href="http://getbootstrap.com">bootstrap</a>&rsquo;s responsive grid.</p>

<pre><code>/* 12 col responsive grid */

.row {
    clear: both;
    max-width: 1040px;
    margin: 0 auto;
}

[class^="col-"]:last-child {
    margin: 0;
}

[class^="col-"] {
    float: left;
    margin: 0 3.84615384615% 0 0;
    list-style: none;
    position: relative;
}


.col-xs-1 { width: 4.8076923077% }
.col-xs-2 { width: 13.4615384615% }
.col-xs-3 { width: 22.1153846154% }
.col-xs-4 { width: 30.7692307692% }
.col-xs-5 { width: 39.4230769231% }
.col-xs-6 { width: 48.0769230769% }
.col-xs-7 { width: 56.7307692308% }
.col-xs-8 { width: 65.3846153846% }
.col-xs-9 { width: 74.0384615385% }
.col-xs-10 { width: 82.6923076923% }
.col-xs-11 { width: 91.3461538462% }
.col-xs-12 { width: 100%; margin: 0 }
</code></pre>

<p>My breakpoints for my responsive blog are:</p>

<ul>
<li>360px max-width for mobile</li>
<li>768px max-width for tablets</li>
<li>1024px max-width for desktops</li>
</ul>


<p>Keep in mind that with a growing array of devices, there is no longer a &lsquo;common&rsquo; width concepts. It is best to optimize for whichever devices you intend to serve.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s my blog&rsquo;s responsive layout on a few devices:</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/E88F66B9-1921-4E9E-8F48-FB5AF6571F4B.png" width="150" alt="iPhone" /></p>

<p><strong>iPhone 5</strong></p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/photo.png" width="300" alt="ipad" /></p>

<p><strong>iPad Mini</strong></p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/ScreenShot2014-03-23at85832pm.png" width="500" alt="desktop" /></p>

<p><strong>Desktop</strong></p>

<p>So, i&rsquo;ve designed and tested out my new blog layout. It is my first time designing a blog from scratch and i&rsquo;ve really learnt alot in the process! Designing is like a constant war between your left brain and right brain while still trying to grip on to established design principles. ROAR! But still, it is fun :) Hopefully my experience has provided you with a guideline to designing blogs. I&rsquo;d love to hear about your experiences in designing your own blog!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lesson 9 The Rose]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/design/2014/03/07/Lesson-9-The-Rose/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-07T11:00:28-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/design/2014/03/07/Lesson-9-The-Rose</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We will warm up for the rose by drawing simple shapes. It is always good to warm up by drawing serveral simple basic shapes.</p>

<ol>
<li>Draw two guide dota horizontally across from each other.</li>
<li>Connect the dots with a foreshortened circle.</li>
<li>Draw the body of the bowl.</li>
<li>Using a guide line in direction SW, position the light source in the top right. Shade the bowl with blended shading from drak to light, creating a smooth blended surface.</li>
<li>Before drawing the rose, let&rsquo;s try drawing the &ldquo;peeking&rdquo; line. This tiny detail of a small overlapping line that defines a fold or a wrinkle will have a huge visual effect in enabling you to make the rose petals appear to be curling around the bud in three dimensions.
5a. Draw a vertical flagpole.
5b. Draw two guide dots.
5c. Draw three-quarters of a foreshortened circle.
5d. Draw the vertical thickness of the flag.
5e. Curve the near bottom edge of the flag a bit more than the line above it. The bottom of the flag is a bit farther from your eye, so you need to distort it, curve it more than the top edge.
5f. Draw the &ldquo;peeking&rdquo; line, the most important line in this exercise. This teeny tiny dash will make or break the drawing and holds an enormous amount of visual power.</li>
</ol>


<p>Let&rsquo;s finally get to drawing a rose.</p>

<ol>
<li>Draw a foreshortened bowl, and add a stem.</li>
<li>Draw a guide dot in the middle of the rose bowl.</li>
<li>Begin to spiral out the rose petal with three-quarters of a foreshortened circle.</li>
<li>Keep spiraling, and keep these spiraled foreshortened circles squished. It&rsquo;s the distorted shape that will form the 3 dimensional rosebud.</li>
<li>Complete the spiral at the center of the petal. Erase the extra line.</li>
<li>Draw the center thickness of the rose petal and the first peeking thickness line.</li>
<li>Draw the next outer peeking line.</li>
<li>Draw the remaining thickness line. There it is, depth focused on our beautiful rose.</li>
<li>Draw the very dark, very small, nook and cranny shadows. Notice i even darkened a shadow along the edge of the rose petal.</li>
<li>Place the light source in the top right, and blend the shadin on each of the curved surfaces opposite. Draw a few thorns on the stem, and draw the leaves.</li>
</ol>


<p>Here is my work!
<img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/81630E2C-81A0-4EC6-9376-50AF1E655568.jpg" alt="lesson9-1" /></p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/9BD6F67E-D8D1-47A8-A47A-A85D4FBD472F.jpg" alt="lesson9-2" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lesson 8 Cool Koalas]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.hguochen.com/design/2014/03/03/Lesson-8-Cool-Koalas/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-03T11:59:12-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.hguochen.com/design/2014/03/03/Lesson-8-Cool-Koalas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Let&rsquo;s take a break from boxes and structures and draw a koala bear.</p>

<ol>
<li>Lightly sketch three circles in a row.</li>
<li>On the first circle, use curving dashes to create a &ldquo;soft fur texture along the outside edge&rdquo;.</li>
<li>Continuing to work on the first circle, use more curving dashes to fill in the left side of the circle, creating the illusion of shading with texture. You can use texture to shade an object.</li>
<li>Let&rsquo;s take this one step further. On the second circle, draw sharp lines around the outside, creating the feel of sharp spikes.</li>
<li>Place the light source in the top right corner of your page, and add a few more rows of spikes to the left side of the shape.</li>
<li>Draw scribbles around the third circle. Keep scribbling more circling lines around and around the shape to create a messy-looking ball of dryer lint. Continue to explore this idea of texture as a tool for shading.</li>
<li>Now its time to start drawing the Koala. Begin with a light circle.</li>
<li>Lightly sketch in the ears.</li>
<li>Lightly slope down the shoulders</li>
<li>When you draw the &ldquo;tapered nose, be sure to leave a small white area&rdquo;. This create the illusion of a light reflection off the shiny nose. You will do this same thing when drawing other animals, cats dogs etc.</li>
<li>Draw the koala&rsquo;s eyes, transferring the idea of reflection by leaving a small white spot in each pupil.</li>
<li>Let&rsquo;s take closer look at the ear. This is what is known in the art world as doing a study of a small portion of a picture.</li>
<li>Draw the overlapped line of the &ldquo;concha&rdquo;.</li>
<li>Draw the bump at the bottom of the aer. This is the &ldquo;tragus&rdquo;</li>
<li>Now Repeat this ear structure on the right ear.</li>
<li>Look back at the furry ball you drew at the beginning of this season. Notice how you created the soft feel of fur as ompared to the sharp feel of the spike ball. Draw the soft, furry texture around the outline of the koala.</li>
<li>Use more furry texture to shade the koala&rsquo;s head, ears, and body. Emphasize the undershadow under his chin and in his ear under the top helix line.</li>
</ol>


<p>Here&rsquo;s how my final drawing looks like:</p>

<p><img src="http://i1113.photobucket.com/albums/k508/houguochen/Mobile%20Uploads/0AB47825-2D43-42C9-978A-5D92445FCD41.jpg" alt="lesson8" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
